[SOUND]
In this lecture, we are going to talk about how
to improve the instantiation
of the vector space model.
This is a continued discussion
We're going to focus on how to improve
the instantiation of this model.
In the previous lecture,
you have seen that with simple
instantiations of the vector space model,
we can come up with a simple scoring
function that would give us basically
an account of how many unique query
terms are matched in the document.
We also have seen that this function
has a problem, as shown on this slide.
In particular,
if you look at these three documents,
they will all get the same score because
they match the three unique query words.
But intuitively we would like
d4 to be ranked above d3, and
d2 is really not relevant.
So the problem here is that this function
couldn't capture the following heuristics.
First, we would like to give
more credit to d4 because it
matched presidential more times than d3.
Second, intuitively, matching presidential
should be more important than
matching about, because about is a very
common word that occurs everywhere.
It doesn't really carry that much content.
So in this lecture,
let's see how we can improve the model
to solve these two problems.
It's worth thinking at this point
about why do we have these problems?
If we look back at assumptions we have
made while instantiating the vector
space model,
we'll realize that the problem
is really coming from
some of the assumptions.
In particular, it has to do with how we
placed the vectors in the vector space.
So then naturally,
in order to fix these problems,
we have to revisit those assumptions.
Perhaps we will have to use different ways
to instantiate the vector space model.
In particular, we have to place
the vectors in a different way.
So let's see how we can improve this.
One natural thought is in order to
consider multiple times of a term in
the document,
we should consider the term frequency
instead of just the absence or presence.
In order to consider the difference
between a document where a query
term occurred multiple times and one
where the query term occurred just once,
we have to consider the term frequency,
the count of a term in the document.
In the simplest model, we only modeled
the presence and absence of a term.
We ignored the actual number of times
that a term occurs in a document.
So let's add this back.
So we're going to then
represent a document by
a vector with term frequency as element.
So that is to say, now the elements
of both the query vector and
the document vector will not be 0 or
1s, but
instead they will be the counts of
a word in the query or the document.
So this would bring in additional
information about the document, so
this can be seen as more accurate
representation of our documents.
So now let's see what the formula
would look like if we change this
representation.
So as you'll see on this slide,
we still use dot product.
And so the formula looks
very similar in the form.
In fact, it looks identical.
But inside the sum, of course,
x i and y i are now different.
They are now the counts of word i in
the query and in the document.
Now at this point I also suggest you
to pause the lecture for a moment and
just to think about how we can interpret
the score of this new function.
It's doing something very similar
to what the simplest VSM is doing.
But because of the change of the vector,
now the new score has
a different interpretation.
Can you see the difference?
And it has to do with the consideration
of multiple occurrences of
the same term in a document.
More importantly, we would like to know
whether this would fix the problems
of the simplest vector space model.
So let's look at this example again.
So suppose we change the vector
representation to term frequency vectors.
Now let's look at these
three documents again.
The query vector is the same
because all these words occurred
exactly once in the query.
So the vector is still a 01 vector.
And in fact, d2 is also essentially
representing the same way
because none of these words
has been repeated many times.
As a result,
the score is also the same, still 3.
The same is true for d3,
and we still have a 3.
But d4 would be different, because
now presidential occurred twice here.
So the ending for presidential in the
document vector would be 2 instead of 1.
As a result, now the score for
d4 is higher.
It's a 4 now.
So this means by using term frequency,
we can now rank d4 above d2 and
d3, as we hoped to.
So this solved the problem with d4.
But we can also see that d2 and
d3 are still filtering the same way.
They still have identical scores,
so it did not fix the problem here.
So how can we fix this problem?
Intuitively, we would like
to give more credit for
matching presidential than matching about.
But how can we solve
the problem in a general way?
Is there any way to determine
which word should be treated
more importantly and
which word can be basically ignored?
About is such a word which does not
really carry that much content.
We can essentially ignore that.
We sometimes call such
a word a stock word.
Those are generally very frequent and
they occur everywhere.
Matching it doesn't really mean anything.
But computationally how
can we capture that?
So again, I encourage you to
think a little bit about this.
Can you came up with any statistical
approaches to somehow distinguish
presidential from about?
Now if you think about it for a moment,
you'll realize that one difference is
that a word like above occurs everywhere.
So if you count the occurrence of
the word in the whole collection,
then we will see that about has much
higher frequency than presidential,
which tends to occur
only in some documents.
So this idea suggests
that we could somehow use
the global statistics of terms or
some other information
to trying to down-weight
the element of about in
a vector representation of d2.
At the same time,
we hope to somehow increase
the weight of presidential
in the vector of d3.
If we can do that, then we can
expect that d2 will get the overall
score to be less than 3 while
d3 will get the score above 3.
Then we would be able to
rank d3 on top of d2.
So how can we do this systematically?
Again, we can rely on
some statistical count.
And in this case, the particular idea
is called inverse document frequency.
Now we have seen document
frequency as one signal used in
the modern retrieval functions.
We discussed this in a previous lecture.
So here is the specific way of using it.
Document frequency is the count of
documents that contain a particular term.
Here we say inverse document frequency
because we actually want to reward a word
that doesn't occur in many documents.
And so the way to incorporate this
into our vector representation
is then to modify the frequency
count by multiplying it by
the IDF of the corresponding word,
as shown here.
If we can do that,
then we can penalize common words,
which generally have a lower IDF, and
reward rare words,
which will have a higher IDF.
So more specifically,
the IDF can be defined as
the logarithm of M+1 divided by k,
where M is the total number of documents
in the collection, k is the DF or
document frequency, the total number
of documents containing the word W.
Now if you plot this
function by varying k,
then you would see the curve
would look like this.
In general, you can see it
would give a higher value for
a low DF word, a rare word.
You can also see the maximum value
of this function is log of M+1.
It would be interesting for you to think
about what's the minimum value for
this function.
This could be an interesting exercise.
Now the specific function
may not be as important as
the heuristic to simply
penalize popular terms.
But it turns out that this particular
function form has also worked very well.
Now whether there's a better
form of function here is
the open research question.
But it's also clear that if
we use a linear penalization,
like what's shown here with this line,
then it may not be as
reasonable as the standard IDF.
In particular, you can see
the difference in the standard IDF,
and we somehow have
a turning point of here.
After this point, we're going to say these
terms are essentially not very useful.
They can be essentially ignored.
And this makes sense when
the term occurs so frequently and
let's say a term occurs in more
than 50% of the documents,
then the term is unlikely very important
and it's basically a common term.
It's not very important
to match this word.
So with the standard IDF you can
see it's basically assumed that
they all have low weights.
There's no difference.
But if you look at
the linear penalization,
at this point that there
is still some difference.
So intuitively we'd want to
focus more on the discrimination
of low DF words rather
than these common words.
Well, of course,
which one works better still has to be
validated by using the empirically
correlated dataset.
And we have to use users to
judge which results are better.
So now let's see how
this can solve problem 2.
So now let's look at
the two documents again.
Now without the IDF weighting before,
we just have term frequency vectors.
But with IDF weighting we
now can adjust the TF weight
by multiplying with the IDF value.
For example,
here we can see is adjustment and
in particular for about there's adjustment
by using the IDF value of about,
which is smaller than the IDF
value of presidential.
So if you look at these,
the IDF will distinguish these two words.
As a result, adjustment here would be
larger, would make this weight larger.
So if we score with these new vectors,
then what would happen is that,
of course,
they share the same weights for news and
campaign, but the matching of
about will discriminate them.
So now as a result of IDF weighting,
we will have d3 to be ranked above d2
because it matched a rare word,
whereas d2 matched a common word.
So this shows that the IDF
weighting can solve problem 2.
So how effective is this model in
general when we used TF-IDF weighting?
Well, let's look at all these
documents that we have seen before.
These are the new scores
of the new documents.
But how effective is this new weighting
method and new scoring function point?
So now let's see overall how effective
is this new ranking function
with TF-IDF weighting.
Here we show all the five documents
that we have seen before, and
these are their scores.
Now we can see the scores for
the first four documents here
seem to be quite reasonable.
They are as we expected.
However, we also see a new
problem because now d5 here,
which did not have a very high score
with our simplest vector space model,
now actually has a very high score.
In fact, it has the highest score here.
So this creates a new problem.
This is actually a common phenomenon
in designing retrieval functions.
Basically, when you try
to fix one problem,
you tend to introduce other problems.
And that's why it's very tricky how
to design effective ranking function.
And what's the best ranking function
is their open research question.
Researchers are still working on that.
But in the next few lectures we're going
to also talk about some additional
ideas to further improve this model and
try to fix this problem.
So to summarize this lecture, we've talked
about how to improve the vector space
model, and
we've got to improve the instantiation of
the vector space model
based on TD-IDF weighting.
So the improvement is mostly on
the placement of the vector where we
give high weight to a term that
occurred many times in a document but
infrequently in the whole collection.
And we have seen that this
improved model indeed
looks better than the simplest
vector space model.
But it also still has some problems.
In the next lecture we're going to look at
how to address these additional problems.
[MUSIC]