[MUSIC]
In this lecture, we continue
the discussion of vector space model.
In particular, we're going to
talk about the TF transformation.
In the previous lecture,
we have derived a TF idea of weighting
formula using the vector space model.
And we have assumed that this model
actually works pretty well for
these examples as shown on this slide,
except for
d5, which has received a very high score.
Indeed, it has received the highest
score among all these documents.
But this document is intuitive and
non-relevant, so this is not desirable.
In this lecture,
we're going to talk about,
how we're going to use TF
transformation to solve this problem.
Before we discuss the details,
let's take a look at the formula for
this simple TF-IDF
weighting ranking function.
And see why this document has
received such a high score.
So this is the formula, and
if you look at the formula carefully,
then you will see it involves a sum
over all the matched query terms.
And inside the sum, each matched
query term has a particular weight.
And this weight is TF-IDF weighting.
So it has an idea of component,
where we see two variables.
One is the total number of documents
in the collection, and that is M.
The other is the document of frequency.
This is the number of
documents that are contained.
This word w.
The other variables
involved in the formula include
the count of the query term.
W in the query, and
the count of the word in the document.
If you look at this document again,
now it's not hard to realize that
the reason why it hasn't
received a high score is because
it has a very high count of campaign.
So the count of campaign in this document
is a 4, which is much higher than
the other documents, and has contributed
to the high score of this document.
So in treating the amount
to lower the score for
this document, we need to somehow
restrict the contribution
of the matching of this
term in the document.
And if you think about the matching
of terms in the document carefully,
you actually would realize,
we probably shouldn't reward
multiple occurrences so generously.
And by that I mean,
the first occurrence of a term
says a lot about
the matching of this term,
because it goes from zero
count to a count of one.
And that increase means a lot.
Once we see a word in the document,
it's very likely that the document
is talking about this word.
If we see a extra occurrence on
top of the first occurrence,
that is to go from one to two,
then we also can say that, well the second
occurrence kind of confirmed that it's
not a accidental managing of the word.
Now we are more sure that this
document is talking about this word.
But imagine we have seen, let's say,
50 times of the word in the document.
Now, adding one extra occurrence is not
going to test more about the evidence,
because we're already sure that
this document is about this word.
So if you're thinking this way, it seems
that we should restrict the contribution
of a high count of a term, and
that is the idea of TF Transformation.
So this transformation function is
going to turn the real count of
word into a term frequency weight for
the word in the document.
So here I show in x axis that we'll count,
and
y axis I show the term frequency weight.
So in the previous breaking functions,
we actually have imprison rate
use some kind of transformation.
So for example,
in the 0/1 bit vector recantation,
we actually use such a transformation
function, as shown here.
Basically if the count is 0,
then it has 0 weight,
otherwise it would have a weight of 1.
It's flat.
Now, what about using
term count as TF weight?
Well, that's a linear function, so it has
just exactly the same weight as the count.
Now we have just seen that
this is not desirable.
So what we want is something like this.
So for example,
with an algorithm function,
we can't have a sublinear
transformation that looks like this.
And this will control the influence
of really high weight,
because it's going to lower its inference.
Yet, it will retain
the inference of small counts.
Or we might want to even bend the curve
more by applying logarithm twice.
Now people have tried all these methods.
And they are indeed working better than
the linear form of the transformation.
But so far, what works the best seems
to be this special transformation,
called a BM25 transformation.
BM stands for best matching.
Now in this transformation,
you can see there's a parameter k here.
And this k controls the upper
bound of this function.
It's easy to see this
function has a upper bound,
because if you look at the x divided by
x + k, where k is a non-active number,
then the numerator will never be able
to exceed the denominator, right?
So it's upper bounded by k+1.
Now, this is also difference between
this transformation function and
a logarithm transformation.
Which it doesn't have upper bound.
Furthermore, one interesting property
of this function is that, as we vary k,
we can actually simulate different
transformation functions.
Including the two extremes
that are shown here.
That is, the 0/1 bit transformation and
the linear transformation.
So for example, if we set k to 0,
now you can see
the function value will be 1.
So we precisely recover
the 0/1 bit transformation.
If you set k to very large
number on the other hand,
it's going to look more like
the linear transformation function.
So in this sense,
this transformation is very flexible.
It allows us to control
the shape of the transformation.
It also has a nice property
of the upper bound.
And this upper bound is useful to control
the inference of a particular term.
And so that we can prevent a spammer
from just increasing the count
of one term to spam all queries
that might match this term.
In other words, this upper bound
might also ensure that all
terms would be counted when we aggregate
the weights to compute the score.
As I said, this transformation
function has worked well so far.
So to summarize this lecture,
the main point is that we need to do
Sublinear TF Transformation,
and this is needed to
capture the intuition of diminishing
return from higher term counts.
It's also to avoid the dominance by
one single term over all others.
This BM25 transformation that we
talked about is very interesting.
It's so far one of the best-performing
TF Transformation formulas.
It has upper bound, and so
it's also robust and effective.
Now if we're plugging this function into
our TF-IDF weighting vector space model.
Then we'd end up having
the following ranking function,
which has a BM25 TF component.
Now, this is already
very close to a state of
the odd ranking function called BM25.
And we'll discuss how we can further
improve this formula in the next lecture.
[MUSIC]