[SOUND]
This lecture is about
Document Length Normalization
in the Vector Space Model.
In this lecture, we will continue
the discussion of the vector space model.
In particular, we're going to discuss the
issue of document length normalization.
So far in the lectures about the vector
space model, we have used the various
signals from the document to assess
the matching of the document with a query.
In particular,
we have considered the tone frequency.
The count of a tone in a document.
We have also considered it's
global statistics such as,
IDF, Inverse Document Frequency.
But we have not considered
document lengths.
So here I show two example documents,
d4 is much shorter with only 100 words.
D6 on the other hand, has a 5000 words.
If you look at the matching
of these query words,
we see that in d6, there are more
matchings of the query words.
But one might reason that,
d6 may have matched
these query words in a scattered manner.
So maybe the topic of d6, is not
really about the topic of the query.
So, the discussion of the campaign
at the beginning of the document,
may have nothing to do with the managing
of presidential at the end.
In general,
if you think about the long documents,
they would have a higher chance for
matching any query.
In fact, if you generate a long document
randomly by assembling words from
a distribution of words, then eventually
you probably will match an inquiry.
So in this sense, we should penalize on
documents because they just naturally have
better chance matching to any query, and
this is idea of document normalization.
We also need to be careful in avoiding
to over penalize long documents.
On the one hand,
we want to penalize the long document.
But on the other hand,
we also don't want to over-penalize them.
Now, the reasoning is because
a document that may be long because of
different reasons.
In one case, the document may be
long because it uses more words.
So for example, think about the vortex
article on the research paper.
It would use more words than
the corresponding abstract.
So, this is a case where we probably
should penalize the matching of
long documents such as a full paper.
When we compare the matching
of words in such a long
document with matching of
the words in the shop abstract.
Then long papers in general,
have a higher chance of matching clearer
words, therefore, we should penalize them.
However, there is another case
when the document is long, and
that is when the document
simply has more content.
Now consider another
case of long document,
where we simply concatenate a lot
of abstracts of different papers.
In such a case, obviously, we don't want
to over-penalize such a long document.
Indeed, we probably don't want to penalize
such a document because it's long.
So that's why, we need to be careful about
using the right degree of penalization.
A method of that has been working well,
based on recent results,
is called a pivoted length normalization.
And in this case,
the idea is to use the average document
length as a pivot, as a reference point.
That means we'll assume that for
the average length documents,
the score is about right so
the normalizer would be 1.
But if the document is longer
than the average document length,
then there will be some penalization.
Whereas if it's a shorter,
then there is even some reward.
So this is illustrated at
using this slide, on the axis,
x-axis you can see the length of document.
On the y-axis, we show the normalizer.
In this case, the Pivoted Length
Normalization formula for the normalizer,
is seeing to be interpolation of 1 and
the normalize the document in length
controlled by a parameter B here.
So you can see here,
when we first divide the length
of the document by the average documents,
this not only gives us some
sense about how this document is
compared with average documents, but
also gives us a benefit of not
worrying about the unit of length.
We can measure the length by words or
by characters.
Anyway, this normalizer
has interesting property.
First we see that, if we set the parameter
b to 0 then the value would be 1.
So, there's no lens normalization at all.
So, b, in this sense,
controls the lens normalization.
Whereas, if we set b to a nonzero value,
then the normalizer would look like this.
All right, so
the value would be higher for
documents that are longer than
the average document lens.
Whereas, the value of
the normalizer would be shorter,
would be smaller for shorter documents.
So in this sense,
we see there is a penalization for
long documents, and
there's a reward for short documents.
The degree of penalization
is controlled by b,
because if we set b to a larger value,
then the normalizer would look like this.
There's even more penalization for
long documents and more reward for
the short documents.
By adjusting b, which varies from 0 to 1,
we can control the degree
of length normalization.
So, if we plug in this length
normalization fact that into
the vector space model, ranking functions
is that we have already examined them.
Then we will end up having
the following formulas.
And these are in fact the state of
the vector space model formulas.
Let's take a look at each of them.
The first one is called a pivoted length
normalization vector space model,
and a reference in [INAUDIBLE]
duration of this model.
And here we see that, it's basically
a TFI model that we have discussed,
the idea of component should
be very familiar to you.
There is also a query term
frequency component here.
And then, in the middle, there is
the normalizer tf and in this case,
we see we use the double logarithm
as we discussed before and
this is to achieve
a sublinear transformation.
But we also put a document
the length normalizer in the bottom.
Right, so this would cause
penalization for long document,
because the larger the denominator is,
then the smaller the is.
And this is of course controlled
by the parameter b here.
And you can see again, if b is set to 0
then there is no length normalization.
Okay, so this is one of the two most
effective at these base model formulas.
The next one called a BM25 or Okapi,
is also similar in that it
also has a IDF component here,
and query IDF component here.
But in the middle,
the normal issue's a little bit different.
As we explained,
there is our copy tf transformation here,
and that does sublinear
transformation with the upper bound.
In this case we have put the length
normalization factor here.
We're adjusting k but
it achieves a similar factor,
because we put a normalizer
in the denominator.
Therefore, again, if a document is longer
then the term weight will be smaller.
So you can see after we have gone through
all the n answers that we talked about,
and we have in the end reached
the basically the state of god functions.
So, So far, we have talked about
mainly how to place the document
vector in the vector space.
And, this has played an important role
in determining the effectiveness of
the simple function.
But there are also other dimensions,
where we did not really examine details.
For example, can we further
improve the instantiation of
the dimension of the Vector Space Model?
Now, we've just assumed that the bag
of words representation should issue
dimension as a word but obviously,
we can see there are many other choices.
For example, a stemmed word, those
are the words that haven't transformed
into the same root form, so
that computation and computing were all
become the same and they can be match.
We get those stop word removal.
This is to remove some very common words
that don't carry any content like the off.
We get use of phrases
to define dimensions.
We can even use later in
the semantical analysis, it will find
some clusters of words that represent the
a late in the concept as one by an engine.
We can also use smaller unit,
like a character end grams those
are sequences of and
the characters for dimensions.
However, in practice, people have found
that the bag-of-words representation with
phrases is still the most effective
one and it's also efficient.
So, this is still so far the most
popular dimension instantiation method.
And it's used in all major search engines.
I should also mention, that sometimes
we need to do language specific and
domain specific tokenization.
And this is actually very important, as we
might have variations of terms that might
prevent us from matching them with each
other, even when they mean the same thing.
In some languages like Chinese,
there is also the challenge in segmenting
text to obtain word band rates because
it's just a sequence of characters.
A word might correspond to one
character or two characters or
even three characters.
So, it's easier in English when we
have a space to separate the words.
In some other languages, we may need
to do some Americanize processing to
figure a way out of what
are the boundaries for words.
There is also the possibility to
improve the similarity of the function.
And so
far we have used as a top product, but
one can imagine there are other measures.
For example, we can measure the cosine
of the angle between two vectors.
Or we can use Euclidean distance measure.
And these are all possible, but
dot product seems still the best and
one reason is because it's very general.
In fact that it's sufficiently general,
if you consider the possibilities
of doing waiting in different ways.
So, for example,
cosine measure can be thought of as the
thought product of two normalized factors.
That means, we first normalize each factor
and then we take the thought product.
That would be critical
to the cosine measure.
I just mentioned that the BM25, seems to
be one of the most effective formulas.
But there has been also further
developments in improving BM25.
Although, none of these words have
changed the BM25 fundamental.
So in one line work,
people have divide the BM25 F.
Here, F stands for field, and this is
use BM25 for documents with structures.
So for example, you might consider
a title field, the abstract,
or body of the research article.
Or even anchor text on the web page,
those are the text fields that describe
links to other pages and
these can all be combined with
a proper way of different fields to help
improve scoring for different documents.
When we use BM25 for such a document and
the obvious choice is to apply BM25 for
each field and then combine the scores.
Basically, the idea of BM25F is
to first combine the frequency
counts of terms in all the fields,
and then apply BM25.
Now, this has advantage of avoiding over
counting the first occurrence of the term.
Remember in the sublinear
transformation of TF,
the first occurrence is very important and
it contributes a large weight.
And if we do that for all the fields,
then the same term might have gained
a lot of advantage in every field.
But when we combine these
word frequencies together,
we just do the transformation one time.
At that time,
then the extra occurrences will not be
counted as fresh first recurrences.
And this method has been working very well
for scoring structure with documents.
The other line of extension
is called a BM25+.
In this line,
risk is to have to address the problem of
over penalization of
long documents by BM25.
So to address this problem,
the fix is actually quite simple.
We can simply add a small constant
to the TF normalization formula.
But what's interesting is that,
we can analytically prove that by
doing such a small modification,
we will fix
the problem of over penalization of
law documents by the original BM25.
So the new formula called BM25+,
is empirically and
analytically shown to be better than BM25.
So to summarize all what we have
said about vector space model,
here are the major take away points.
First, in such a model,
we use the similarity of relevance.
Assuming that relevance of a document
with respect to a query, is
basically proportional to the similarity
between the query and the document.
So naturally,
that implies that the query and
document must have been
represented in the same way.
And in this case, we will present them as
vectors in high-dimensional vector space.
Where the dimensions are defined by words,
or concepts, or terms, in general.
And we generally, need to use a lot of
heuristics to design the ranking function.
We use some examples, which show
the needs for several heuristics,
including Tf weighting and transformation.
And IDF weighting, and
document length normalization.
These major heuristics are the most
important of heuristics,
to ensure such a general ranking function
to work well for all kinds of test.
And finally, BM25 and
pivoted normalization seem
to be the most effective formulas
out of the vector space model.
Now I have to say that, I put BM25 in
the category of vector space model, but
in fact, the BM25 has been derived
using probabilistic model.
So the reason why I've put it in
the vector space model is first,
the ranking function actually has a nice
interpretation in the vector space model.
We can easily see,
it looks very much like a vector space
model, with a special waiting function.
The second reason is because the original
BM25, has somewhat different form of IDF.
And that form of IDF after
the [INAUDIBLE] doesn't work so
well as the standard IDF
that you have seen here.
So as effective retrieval function,
BM25 should probably use a heuristic
modification of the IDF.
To make them even more look
like a vector space model
There are some additional readings.
The first is, a paper about
the pivoted length normalization.
It's an excellent example
of using empirical data
analysis to suggest the need for
length normalization and
then further derive the length
normalization formula.
The second, is the original paper
where the BM25 was proposed.
The third paper,
has a thorough discussion of BM25 and
its extensions, particularly BM25 F.
And finally, in the last paper
has a discussion of improving
BM25 to correct the over
penalization of long documents.
[MUSIC]