[MUSIC]
This lecture is about the implementation
of text retrieval systems.
In this lecture we will discuss
how we can implement a text
retrieval method to build a search engine.
The main challenge is to
manage a lot of text data and
to enable a query to be answered very
quickly and to respond to many queries.
This is a typical text
retrieval system architecture.
We can see the documents are first
processed by a tokenizer to
get tokenized units, for example, words.
And then, these words, or
tokens, will be processed by
a indexer that will create a index,
which is a data structure for
the search engine to use
to quickly answer a query.
And the query would be going
through a similar processing step.
So the Tokenizer would be
apprised of the query as well,
so that the text can be
processed in the same way.
The same units would be
matched with each other.
The query's representation would
then be given to the Scorer,
which would use the index to quickly
answer user's query by scoring
the documents and then ranking them.
The results will be given to the user.
And then the user can look at the results
and provided us some feedback that can be
explicit judgements of both
which documents are good,
which documents are bad.
Or implicit feedback such as so that
user didn't have to do anything extra.
End user will just look at the results,
and
skip some, and
click on some result to view.
So these interacting signals can be used
by the system to improve the ranking
accuracy by assuming that viewed documents
are better than the skipped ones.
So a search engine system then
can be divided into three parts.
The first part is the indexer, and
the second part is a Scorer that
responds to the users query, and
the third part is a Feedback mechanism.
Now typically, the Indexer is
done in the offline manner, so
you can pre-process the correct data and
to build the inventory index,
which we will introduce in moment.
And this data structure can then be used
by the online module which is a scorer
to process a user's query dynamically and
quickly generate search results.
The feedback mechanism can be done online
or offline, depending on the method.
The implementation of the indexer and
the scorer is very standard,
and this is the main topic of this
lecture and the next few lectures.
The feedback mechanism,
on the other hand, has variations,
it depends on which method is used.
So that is usually done in
algorithms specific way.
Let's first talk about the tokenizer.
Tokernization is a normalized lexical
units in through the same form,
so that semantically similar words
can be matched with each other.
Now, in the language like English,
stemming is often used and
this will map all the inflectional
forms of words into the same root form.
So for example, computer, computation, and
computing can all be matched
to the root form compute.
This way all these different forms of
computing can be matched with each other.
Now normally, this is a good idea,
to increase the coverage of documents
that are matched up with this query.
But it's also not always beneficial,
because sometimes the subtlest
difference between computer and
computation might still suggest the
difference in the coverage of the content.
But in most cases,
stemming seems to be beneficial.
When we tokenize the text in some other
languages, for example Chinese, we might
face some special challenges in segmenting
the text to find the word boundaries.
Because it's not obvious
where the boundary is as
there's no space to separate them.
So here of course, we have to use some
language specific processing techniques.
Once we do tokenization, then we would
index the text documents and than it'll
convert the documents and do some data
structure that can enable faster search.
The basic idea is to precompute
as much as we can basically.
So the most commonly used index
is call an Inverted index.
And this has been used
in many search engines
to support basic search algorithms.
Sometimes the other indices, for example,
document index might be needed in order
to support feedback, like I said.
And these kind of techniques
are not really standard in
that they vary a lot according
to the feedback methods.
To understand why we want to use
inverted index it will be useful for
you to think about how you would
respond to a single term query quickly.
So if you want to use more time to
think about that, pause the video.
So think about how you can
pre process the text data so
that you can quickly respond
to a query with just one word.
Where if you have thought
about that question,
you might realize that where
the best is to simply create
the list of documents that match
every term in the vocabulary.
In this way, you can basically
pre-construct the answers.
So when you see a term you can simply just
to fetch the random list of documents for
that term and return the list to the user.
So that's the fastest way to
respond to a single term here.
Now the idea of the invert index
is actually, basically, like that.
We're going to do pre-constructed
search an index, that will allows
us to quickly find all the documents
that match a particular term.
So let's take a look at this example.
We have three documents here,
and these are the documents that you
have seen in some previous lectures.
Suppose that we want to create
an inverted index for these documents.
Then we want to maintain a dictionary, in
the dictionary we will have one entry for
each term and we're going to store
some basic statistics about the term.
For example, the number of
documents that match the term, or
the total number of code or
frequency of the term,
which means we would kind of duplicate
the occurrences of the term.
And so, for example, news,
this term occur in all
the three documents,
so the count of documents is three.
And you might also realize we needed this
count of documents, or document frequency,
for computing some statistics to
be used in the vector space model.
Can you think of that?
So what weighting heuristic
would need this count.
Well, that's the idea, right,
inverse document frequency.
So, IDF is the property of a term,
and we can compute it right here.
So, with the document that count here,
it's easy to compute the idea of,
either at this time, or
with the old index, or.
At random time when we see a query.
Now in addition to these basic statistics,
we'll also store all the documents
that matched the news,
and these entries are stored
in the file called Postings.
So in this case it matched
three documents and
we store information about
these three documents here.
This is the document id,
document 1 and the frequency is 1.
The tf is one for news, in the second
document it's also 1, et cetera.
So from this list, we can get all
the documents that match the term news and
we can also know the frequency
of news in these documents.
So, if the query has just one word,
news, and
we have easily look up to this
table to find the entry and
go quicker into the postings to fetch
all the documents that matching yours.
So, let's take a look at another term.
This time, let's take a look
at the word presidential.
This would occur in only one document,
document 3.
So the document frequency is 1 but
it occurred twice in this document.
So the frequency count is two, and
the frequency count is used for
some other reachable method where
we might use the frequency to
assess the popularity of
a term in the collection.
Similarly we'll have a pointer
to the postings here,
and in this case,
there is only one entry here because
the term occurred in just one document and
that's here.
The document id is 3 and
it occurred twice.
So this is the basic
idea of inverted index.
It's actually pretty simple, right?
With this structure we can easily fetch
all the documents that match a term.
And this will be the basis for
scoring documents for a query.
Now sometimes we also want to store
the positions of these terms.
So in many of these cases the term
occurred just once in the document.
So there's only one position for
example in this case.
But in this case, the term occurred
twice so there's two positions.
Now the position information is very
useful for the checking whether
the matching of query terms is
actually within a small window of,
let's say, five words or ten words.
Or, whether the matching of the two query
terms is, in fact, a phrase of two words.
That this can all be checked quickly
by using the position from each.
So, why is inverted index good for
fast search?
Well, we just talked about the possibility
of using the two answer single-term query.
And that's very easy.
What about the multiple term queries?
Well let's first look at the some
special cases of the Boolean query.
A Boolean query is basically
a Boolean expression like this.
So I want the value in the document
to match both term A and term B.
So that's one conjunctive query.
Or I want the web documents
to match term A or term B.
That's a disjunctive query.
But how can we answer such
a query by using inverted index?
Well if you think a bit about it,
it would be obvious because
we have simply fetch all
the documents that match term A and also
fetch all the documents that match term B.
And then just take the intersection
to answer a query like A and B.
Or to take the union to
answer the query A or B.
So this is all very easy to answer.
It's going to be very quick.
Now what about the multi-term
keyword query?
We talked about the vector space model for
example and
we will do a match such query with
document and generate the score.
And the score is based on
aggregated term weights.
So in this case it's not
the Boolean query but
the scoring can be actually
done in similar way.
Basically it's similar to
disjunctive Boolean query.
Basically, it's like A or B.
We take the union of all the documents
that match at least one query term and
then we would aggregate the term weights.
So this is a basic idea of using inverted
index for scoring documents in general.
And we're going to talk about
this in more detail later.
But for now,
let's just look at the question
why is in both index, a good idea?
Basically why is more efficient than
sequentially just scanning documents.
This is the obvious approach.
You can just compute a score for each
document and then you can then sort them.
And this is a straightforward method but
this is going to be very slow imagine
the wealth, there's a lot of documents.
If you do this then it will take
a long time to answer your query.
So the question now is why would
the invert index be much faster?
Well it has to do is the word
distribution in text.
So, here's some common phenomena
of word distribution in the text.
There are some languages independent
of patterns that seem to be stable.
And these patterns are basically
characterized by the following pattern.
A few words like the common
words like the, a, or
we occur very, very frequently in text.
So they account for
a large percent of occurrences of words.
But most words would occur just rarely.
There are many words that occur just once,
let's say, in a document or
once in the collection.
And there are many such.
It's also true that the most
frequent the words in one corpus
they have to be rare in another.
That means although the general
phenomenon is applicable,
was observed in many cases that
exact words that are common
may vary from context to context.
So this phenomena is characterized
by what's called a Zipf's Law.
This law says that the rank of a word
multiplied by the frequency of
the word is roughly constant.
So formally if we use F(w)
to denote the frequency,
r(w) to denote the rank of a word.
Then this is the formula.
It basically says the same thing,
just mathematical term.
Where C is basically a constant and
so, and there is also a parameter,
alpha, that might be adjusted to
better fit any empirical observations.
So if I plot the word
frequencies in sorted order,
then you can see this more easily.
The x axis is basically the word rank.
This is r(w) and
the y axis is word frequency or F(w).
Now this curve shows that the product
of the two is roughly the constant.
Now if you look at these words, we can see
They can be separated into three groups.
In the middle,
it's the intermediary frequency words.
These words tend to occur
quite in a few documents, but
they are not like those
most frequent words.
And they are also not very rare.
So they tend to be often used in
queries and they also tend
to have high TF-IDF weights.
These intermediate frequency words.
But if you look at the left
part of the curve,
these are the highest frequency words.
They are covered very frequently.
They are usually words,
like the, we, of Etc.
Those words are very, very frequent and
they are in fact the two frequent to be
discriminated, and they are generally
not very useful for retrieval.
So they are often removed and
this is called the stop words removal.
So you can use pretty much just the kind
of words in the collection to kind of
infer what words might be stop words.
Those are basically
the highest frequency words.
And they also occupy a lot of
space in the inverted index.
You can imagine the posting entries for
such a word would be very long.
And then therefore,
if you can remove such words you can save
a lot of space in the inverted index.
We also show the tail part,
which has a lot of rare words.
Those words don't occur very frequently,
and there are many such words.
Those words are actually very useful for
search also, if a user happens to
be interested in such a topic.
But because they're rare,
it's often true that users
aren't necessarily
interested in those words.
But retain them would allow us to
match such a document accurately.
They generally have very high IDF.
So what kind of data structures should
we use to store inverted index?
Well, it has two parts, right.
If you recall, we have a dictionary and
we also have postings.
The dictionary has modest size, although
for the web it's still going to be very
large but compare it with
postings it's more distinct.
And we also need to have fast
random access to the entries
because we're going to look up
on the query term very quickly.
So therefore, we'd prefer to keep such
a dictionary in memory if it's possible.
If the collection is not very large,
this is feasible, but
if the collection is very large
then it's in general not possible.
If the vocabulary size is very large,
obviously we can't do that.
So, in general that's how it goes.
So the data structures
that we often use for
storing dictionary,
it would be direct access.
There are structures like hash table, or
b-tree if we can't store
everything in memory or use disk.
And then try to build a structure that
would allow it to quickly look up entries.
For postings they are huge.
And in general, we don't have to have
direct access to a specific entry.
We generally would just look up
a sequence of document IDs and
frequencies for all the documents
that matches the query term.
So would read those entries sequentially.
And therefore because it's large and
we generally have store postings on disc,
they have to stay on disc and they would
contain information such as document IDs,
term frequency or
term positions, etcetera.
Now because they are very large,
compression is often desirable.
Now this is not only to save disc space,
and this is of course
one benefit of compression, it It's
not going to occupy that much space.
But it's also to help improving speed.
Can you see why?
Well, we know that input and
output would cost a lot of time.
In comparison with the time taken by CPU.
So, CPU is much faster but
IO takes time and
so by compressing the inverter index,
opposing files will become smaller, and
the entries, that we have the readings,
and memory to process a query term,
would be smaller, and
then, so we can reduce
the amount of tracking IO and
that can save a lot of time.
Of course, we have to then do more
processing of the data when we
uncompress the data in the memory.
But as I said CPU is fast.
So over all we can still save time.
So compression here is both
to save disc space and
to speed up the loading of the index.
[MUSIC]