[SOUND]
This lecture is about the inverted index
construction.
In this lecture, we will continue
the discussion of system implementation.
In particular, we're going to discuss
how to construct the inverted index.
The construction of the inverted index
is actually very easy if the dataset is
very small.
It's very easy to construct a dictionary
and then store the postings in a file.
The problem is that when our data
is not able to fit to the memory
then we have to use some
special method to deal with it.
And unfortunately, in most retrieval
applications the dataset will be large.
And they generally cannot be
loaded into memory at once.
And there are many approaches to
solve that problem, and sorting-based
method is quite common and
works in four steps as shown here.
First, you collect the local termID,
documentID and frequency tuples.
Basically you will locate the terms
in a small set of documents.
And then once you collect those accounts
you can sort those count based on terms.
So that you will be able to local
a partial inverted index and
these are called rounds.
And then you write them into
a temporary file on the disk and
then you merge in step 3.
Do pairwise merging of these runs, until
you eventually merge all the runs and
generate a single inverted index.
So this is an illustration of this method.
On the left you see some documents and
on the right we have a term lexicon and
a document ID lexicon.
These lexicons are to map string-based
representations of document IDs or
terms into integer representations or
map back from integers to
the stream representation.
The reason why we want our interest
using integers to present these
IDs is because integers
are often easier to handle.
For example,
integers can be used as index for
array, and they are also easy to compress.
So this is one reason why we tend
to map these strings into integers,
so that we don't have to
carry these strings around.
So how does this approach work?
Well, it's very simple.
We're going to scan these
documents sequentially and
then parse the documents and
count the frequencies of terms.
And in this stage we generally sort
the frequencies by document IDs,
because we process each
document sequentially.
So we'll first encounter all
the terms in the first document.
Therefore the document IDs
are all ones in this case.
And this will be followed by document IDs
two and they are natural results in this
only just because we process
the data in a sequential order.
At some point,
we will run out of memory and
that would have to write
them into the disc.
Before we do that we 're going to sort
them, just use whatever memory we have.
We can sort them and then this time
we're going to sort based on term IDs.
Note that here,
we're using the term IDs as a key to sort.
So all the entries that share the same
term would be grouped together.
In this case,
we can see all the IDs of documents
that match term 1 would
be grouped together.
And we're going to write this into
that this is a temporary file.
And would that allows you to
use the memory to process and
makes a batch of documents.
And we're going to do that for
all the documents.
So we're going to write a lot of
temporary files into the disc.
And then the next stage is
we do merge sort basically.
We're going to merge them and
then sort them.
Eventually, we will get
a single inverted index,
where the entries are sorted
based on term IDs.
And on the top, we're going to see
these are the older entries for
the documents that match term ID 1.
So this is basically, how we can do
the construction of inverted index.
Even though the data cannot be
all loaded into the manner.
Now, we mention earlier that
because of hostings are very large,
it's desirable to compress them.
So let's now take a little bit
how we compressed inverted index.
Well the idea of compression in general,
is for
leverage skewed distributions of values.
And we generally have to use
variable-length encoding,
instead of the fixed-length
encoding as we use by default in
a program manager like C++.
And so how can we leverage
the skewed distributions of values
to compress these values?
Well in general, we will use few
bits to encode those frequent
words at the cost of using longer
bit string code those rare values.
So in our case, let's think about how
we can compress the TF, tone frequency.
Now, if you can picture what
the inverted index look like, and
you will see in post things,
there are a lot of tone frequencies.
Those are the frequencies of
terms in all those documents.
Now, if you think about it, what kind
of values are most frequent there?
You probably will be able to guess
that small numbers tend to occur
far more frequently than large numbers.
Why?
Well, think about the distribution of
words and this is to do the sip of slopes,
and many words occur just rarely so
we see a lot of small numbers.
Therefore, we can use fewer bits for
the small, but
highly frequent integers and
that's cost of using more bits for
larger integers.
This is a trade off of course.
If the values are distributed to uniform,
then this won't save us any space,
but because we tend to see many small
values, they are very frequent.
We can save on average even though
sometimes when we see a large number
we have to use a lot of bits.
What about the document IDs
that we also saw in postings?
Well they are not distributed
in the skewed way.
So how can we deal with that?
Well it turns out that we can
use a trick called a d-gap and
that is to store the difference
of these term IDs.
And we can imagine if a term has
matched that many documents then
there will be longest of document IDs.
So when we take the gap, and we take the
difference between adjacent document IDs,
those gaps will be small.
So again, see a lot of small numbers.
Whereas if a term occurred
in only a few documents,
then the gap would be large,
the large numbers would not be frequent.
So this creates some skewed distribution,
that would allow us to
compress these values.
This is also possible because
in order to uncover or
uncompress these document IDs,
we have to sequentially process the data.
Because we stored the difference and
in order to recover the exact
document ID we have to first
recover the previous document ID.
And then we can add the difference to
the previous document ID to restore
the current document ID.
Now this was possible because we only
needed to have sequential access to
those document IDs.
Once we look up the term, we look up all
the document IDs that match the term,
then we sequentially process them.
So it's very natural,
that's why this trick actually works.
And there are many different methods for
encoding.
So binary code is a commonly used
code in just any program language.
We use basically fixed glance in coding.
Unary code, gamma code, and
delta code are all possibilities and
there are many other possibilities.
So let's look at some
of them in more detail.
Binary coding is really
equal length coding, and
that's a property for
randomly distributed values.
The unary coding is a variable
length in coding method.
In this case, integer this 1 will be
encoded as x -1, 1 bit followed by 0.
So for example, 3 will be encoded as 2,
1s followed by 0,
whereas 5 will be encoded as 4,
1s, followed by 0, etc.
So now you can imagine how many bits do we
have to use for a large number like 100?
So how many bits do you have to
use exactly for a number like 100?
Well exactly, we have to use 100 bits.
So it's the same number of bits
as the value of this number.
So this is very inefficient if you
were likely to see some large numbers.
Imagine if you occasionally see a number
like 1,000, you have to use 1,000 bits.
So this only works well if you
are absolutely sure that there will be
no large numbers, mostly very
often you see very small numbers.
Now, how do you decode this code?
Now since these are variable
length encoding methods,
you can't just count how many bits and
then just stop.
You can't say 8-bits or 32-bits,
then you will start another code.
They are variable length, so
you will have to rely on some mechanism.
In this case for unary, you can see
it's very easy to see the boundary.
Now you can easily see 0 would
signal the end of encoding.
So you just count up how many 1s you
have seen and at the end you hit 0.
You have finished one number,
you will start another number.
Now we just saw that unary
coding is too aggressive.
In rewarding small numbers, and
if you occasionally can see a very
big number, it would be a disaster.
So what about some other
less aggressive method?
Well gamma coding's one of them and
in this method we can use unary coding for
a transform form of that.
So it's 1 plus the floor of log of x.
So the magnitude of this value is
much lower than the original x.
So that's why we can afford
using unary code for that.
And so first I have the unary code for
coding this log of x.
And this would be followed by
a uniform code or binary code.
And this basically the same uniform code,
and binary code are the same.
And we're going to use this coder to code
the remaining part of the value of x.
And this is basically precisely
x-1 to the floor of log of x
So the unary code are basically
called the flow of log of x,
well add one there and here.
But the remaining part
we'll be using uniform
code through actually code the difference
between the x and this 2 to the log of x.
And it's easy to show that for this
difference we only need to use up
to this many bits and
the floor of log of x bits.
And this is easy to understand,
if the difference is too large, then we
would have a higher floor of log of x.
So here are some examples for
example, 3 is is encoded as 101.
The first two digits are the unary code.
So this isn't for the value 2,
10 encodes 2 in unary coding.
And so that means the floor of
log of x is 1,
because we won't actually use unary codes.
In code 1 plus the flow of log of x,
since this is two then we know that
the flow of log of x is actually 1.
So that 3 is still larger than 2 to the 1.
So the difference is 1, and
the 1 is encoded here at the end.
So that's why we have 101 for 3.
Now similarly 5 is encoded as 110,
followed by 01.
And in this case the unary code in code 3.
And so this is a unary code 110 and
so the flow of log of x is 2.
And that means we're going to
compute a difference between 5 and
the 2 to the 2 and that's 1.
And so we now have again 1 at the end.
But this time we're going to use 2 bits,
because with this level
of flow of log of x.
We could have more numbers a 5, 6, 7 they
would all share the same prefix here, 110.
So in order to differentiate them,
we have to use 2 bits in
the end to differentiate them.
So you can imagine 6 would be 10 here
in the end instead of 01 after 10.
It's also true that the form of
a gamma code is always the first
odd number of bits, and
in the center there is a 0.
That's the end of the unary code.
And before that or on the left side
of this 0, there will be all 1s.
And on the right side of this 0,
it's binary coding or uniform coding.
So how can you decode such code?
Well you again first do unary coding.
Once you hit 0, you have got the unary
code and this also tell you how
many bits you have to read further
to decode the uniform code.
So this is how you can
decode a gamma code.
There is also a delta code that's
basically the same as a gamma code except
that you replace the unary
prefix with the gamma code.
So that's even less
conservative than gamma code
in terms of wording the small integers.
So that means, it's okay if you
occasionally see a large number.
It's okay with delta code.
It's also fine with the gamma code,
it's really a big loss for unary code.
And they are all operating of course,
at different degrees of favoring short or
favoring small integers.
And that also means they would be
appropriate for a sorting distribution.
But none of them is perfect for
all distributions.
And which method works the best would
have to depend on the actual distribution
in your dataset.
For inverted index compression,
people have found that gamma
coding seems to work well.
So how to uncompress inverted index?
I will just talk about this.
Firstly, you decode
those encoded integers.
And we just I think discussed the how we
decode unary coding and gamma coding.
What about the document IDs that
might be compressed using d-gap?
Well, we're going to do
sequential decoding so
supposed the encoded I list is x1,
x2, x3 etc.
We first decode x1 to obtain
the first document ID, ID1.
Then we can decode x2,
which is actually the difference between
the second ID and the first one.
So we have to add the decoder
value of x2 to ID1 to recover
the value of the ID at
this secondary position.
So this is where you can
see the advantages of
converting document IDs to integers.
And that allows us to do
this kind of compression.
And we just repeat until we
decode all the documents.
Every time we use the document ID in
the previous position to help to recover
the document ID in the next position.
[MUSIC]