[SOUND]
This lecture is about how to do faster
search by using invert index.
In this lecture, we're going to continue
the discussion of system implementation.
In particular,
we're going to talk about how to support
a faster search by using invert index.
So let's think about what a general
scoring function might look like.
Now of course, the vector space
model is a special case of this, but
we can imagine many other retrieval
functions of the same form.
So the form of this
function is as follows.
We see this scoring function
of a document D and
a query Q is defined as
first a function of fa
that adjustment a function that
would consider two factors.
That I'll assume here at the end,
f sub d of d and f sub q of q.
These are adjustment factors
of a document and a query,
so they are at the level of a document and
the query.
So and then inside of this function,
we also see there's
another function called h.
So this is the main part
of the scoring function and
these as I just said of
the scoring factors at
the level of the whole document and
the query.
For example, document [INAUDIBLE] and
this aggregate punching would
then combine all these.
Now inside this h function,
there are functions that
would compute the weights
of the contribution of
a matched query term ti.
So this g,
the function g gives us the weight
of a matched query term ti in document d.
And this h function would then
aggregate all these weights.
So for example,
take a sum of all the matched query terms,
but it can also be a product or it could
be another way of aggregating them.
And then finally, this adjustment
the functioning would then consider
the document level or query level
factors to further adjust this score,
for example, document [INAUDIBLE].
So, this general form would cover
many state of [INAUDIBLE] functions.
Let's look at how we can score documents
with such a function using virtual index.
So, here's a general algorithm
that works as follows.
First this query level and
document level factors can be
pre-computed in the indexing time.
Of course, for the query we have to
compute it at the query time but for
document, for example,
document [INAUDIBLE] can be pre-computed.
And then, we maintain a score accumulator
for each document d to computer h.
An h is an aggregation function
over all the matching query terms.
So how do we do that?
For each period term we're going to
do fetch the inverted list
from the invert index.
This will give us all the documents
that match this query term
and that includes d1, f1 and so dn fn.
So each pair is a document ID and
the frequency of the term in the document.
Then for each entry d sub j and
f sub j are particular match
of the term in this
particular document d sub j.
We'll going to compute the function
g that would give us something like
weight of this term, so
we're computing the weight completion of
matching this query term in this document.
And then, we're going to update
the score accumulator for
this document and
this would allow us to add this to our
accumulator that would
incrementally compute function h.
So this is basically a general
way to allow pseudo computer or
functions of this form by
using the inbound index.
Note that we don't have to
attach any of document and
that didn't match any query term.
Well, this is why it's fast,
we only need to process the documents
that matched at least one query term.
In the end, then we're going to adjust
the score the computer this function f
sub a and then we can sort.
So let's take a look
at a specific example.
In this case, let's assume the scoring
function is a very simple one,
it just takes the sum of t f, the role of
t f, the count of a term in the document.
This simplification would help
shield the algorithm clearly.
It's very easy to extend the computation
to include other weights like
the transformation of tf, or [INAUDIBLE]
or IDF [INAUDIBLE].
So let's take a look at specific example,
where the queries information security
and it show some entries of
invert index on the right side.
Information occurred in four documents and
their frequencies are also there,
security occurred in three documents.
So let's see how the arrows works, so
first we iterate overall query terms
and we fetch the first query then,
what is that?
That's information, right?
And imagine we have all these
score accumulators who score the,
scores for these documents.
We can imagine there will be other but
then they will only be
allocated as needed.
So before we do any waiting of terms,
we don't even need a score of.
That comes actually we have these score
accumulators eventually allocating.
So lets fetch the interest from
the entity [INAUDIBLE] for
information, that the first one.
So these four accumulators obviously
would be initialize as zeros.
So, the first entry is d1 and 3,
3 is occurrences of
information in this document.
Since our scoring function assume that the
score is just a sum of these raw counts.
We just need to add a 3 to the score
accumulator to account for
the increase of score due to matching
this term information, a document d1.
And then, we go to the next entry,
that's d2 and 4 and
then we add a 4 to the score
accumulator of d2.
Of course, at this point, that we will
allocate the score accumulator as needed.
And so at this point, we allocated
the d1 and d2, and the next one is d3,
and we add one, we allocate another
score [INAUDIBLE] d3 and add one to it.
And then finally,
the d4 gets a 5, because the term
information occurred five
times in this document.
Okay, so this completes the processing of
all the entries in the invert index for
information.
It processed all the contributions
of matching information in this
four documents.
So now, our error will go to
the next that's security.
So, we're going to fetch all
the inverted index entries for security.
So, in this case,
there are three entries, and
we're going to go through each of them.
The first is d2 and 3 and
that means security occur three
humps in d2 and what do we do?
Well, we do exactly the same,
as what we did for information.
So, this time we're going to change the
score [INAUDIBLE] d2 since it's already
allocated and
what we do is we'll add 3 to the existing
value which is a 4, so
we now get a 7 for d2.
D2 score is increased because the match
that falls the information and
the security.
Go to the next entry, that's d4 and
1, so we would the score for
d4 and again, we add 1 to d4 so
d4 goes from 5 to 6.
Finally, we process d5 and a 3.
Since we have not yet allocated a score
accumulated for d5, at this point,
we're going to allocate 1 for d5,
and we're going to add a 3 to it.
So, those scores, of the last rule,
are the final scores for these documents.
If our scoring function is just
a simple some of TF values.
Now, what if we, actually,
would like to do form addition?
Well, we going to do the [INAUDIBLE]
at this point, for each document.
So, to summarize this,
all right, so you can see,
we first process the information
determine query term information and
we processed all the entries
in what index for this term.
Then we process the security,
all right, its worst think about
what should be the order of processing
here when we can see the query terms?
It might make a difference especially
if we don't want to keep all
the score accumulators.
Let's say, we only want to keep
the most promising score accumulators.
What do you think would be
a good order to go through?
Would you process a common term first or
would you process a rare term first?
The answers is we just go to who
should process the rare term first.
A rare term would match a few documents,
and then the score contribution would
be higher,
because the ideal value would be higher.
And then, it allows us to attach
the most diplomacy documents first.
So, it helps pruning
some non-promising ones,
if we don't need so
many documents to be returned to the user.
So those are all heuristics for
further improving the accuracy.
Here you can also see how we can
incorporate the idea of waiting, right?
So they can [INAUDIBLE] when we
incorporate [INAUDIBLE] when we process
each query time.
When we fetch the inverted index we
can fetch the document frequency and
then we can compute IDF.
Or maybe perhaps the IDF value
has already been precomputed
when we indexed the documents.
At that time, we already computed
the IDF value that we can just fetch it,
so all these can be done at this time.
So that would mean when we process
all the entries for information,
these words would be adjusted by the same
IDF, which is IDF for information.
So this is the basic idea of using
inverted index for fast research and
it works well for all kinds of
formulas that are of the general form.
And this generally,
the general form covers actually
most state of art retrieval functions.
So there are some tricks to
further improve the efficiency,
some general techniques
to encode the caching.
This is we just store some results of
popular queries, so that next time
when you see the same query,
you simply return the stored results.
Similarly, you can also slow the list
of inverted index in the memory for
a popular term.
And if the query term is popular likely,
you will soon need to factor the inverted
index for the same term again.
So keeping it in the memory would help,
and these are general techniques for
improving efficiency.
We can also keep only the most promising
accumulators because a user generally
doesn't want to examine so many documents.
We only need to return high
qualities subset of documents that
likely are ranked on the top.
For that purpose,
we can then prune the accumulators.
We don't have to store
all the accumulators.
At some point, we just keep
the highest value accumulators.
Another technique is to do parallel
processing and that's needed for
really process in such a large
data set like the web data set.
And you scale up to
the Web-scale really to have
the special techniques you
do parallel processing and
to distribute the storage
of files on machines.
So here is a list of some text retrieval
toolkits, it's not a complete list.
You can find more information
at this URL on the bottom.
And here, I listed your four here,
Lucene's one of the most popular toolkits
that can support a lot of applications and
it has very nice support for applications.
You can use it to build a search
engine application very quickly.
The downside is that it's not
that easy to extend it, and
the algorithms implemented they are also
not the most advanced algorithms.
Lemur or Indri is another
toolkit that does not have such
a nice support web
application as Lucene but
it has many advanced search algorithms and
it's also easy to extend.
Terrier is yet another toolkit
that also has good support for
application capability and
some advanced algorithms.
So that's maybe in between Lemur or
Lucene, or
maybe rather combining
the strands of both,
so that's also useful tool kit.
MeTA is a toolkit that we will use for
the problem assignment and
this is a new toolkit that has
a combination of both text retrieval
algorithms and text mining algorithms.
And so talking models are implement they
are a number of text analysis algorithms
implemented in the toolkit as
well as basic search algorithms.
So to summarize all the discussion
about the System Implementation,
here are the major takeaway points.
Inverted index is the primary data
structure for supporting a search engine
and that's the key to enable
faster response to a user's query.
And the basic idea is to preprocess
the data as much as we can, and
we want to do compression
when appropriate.
So that we can save disk space and
we can speed up IO and
processing of inverted index in general.
We talked about how to construct the
invert index when the data can't fit into
the memory.
And then we talk about faster search using
that index basically, what's we exploit
the invective index to accumulate a scores
for documents [INAUDIBLE] algorithm.
And we exploit the Zipf's law to
avoid the touching many documents
that don't match any query term and
this algorithm can actually support
a wide range of ranking algorithms.
So these basic techniques
have great potential for
further scaling up using distributed file
system, parallel processing, and caching.
Here are two additional readings you
can take a look, if you have time and
you are interested in
learning more about this.
The first one is a classical
textbook on the efficiency
o inverted index and
the compression techniques.
And how to,
in general feel that the efficient
any inputs of the space,
overhead and speed.
The second one is a newer textbook that
has a nice discussion of implementing and
evaluating search engines.
[MUSIC]