[SOUND]
This
lecture is about
the Probabilistic Retrieval Model.
In this lecture,
we're going to continue the discussion
of the Text Retrieval Methods.
We're going to look at another kind of
very different way to design ranking
functions than the Vector Space Model
that we discussed before.
In probabilistic models,
we define the ranking function,
based on the probability that this
document is relevant to this query.
In other words, we introduce
a binary random variable here.
This is the variable R here.
And we also assume that the query and
the documents are all observations
from random variables.
Note that in the vector-based models,
we assume they are vectors, but
here we assume they are the data
observed from random variables.
And so, the problem of retrieval becomes
to estimate the probability of relevance.
In this category of models,
there are different variants.
The classic probabilistic model has
led to the BM25 retrieval function,
which we discussed in in
the vectors-based model
because its a form is actually
similar to a backwards space model.
In this lecture,
we will discuss another sub class in this
P class called a language
modeling approaches to retrieval.
In particular, we're going to discuss
the query likelihood retrieval model,
which is one of the most effective
models in probabilistic models.
There was also another line called
the divergence from randomness model
which has led to the PL2 function,
it's also one of the most effective
state of the art retrieval functions.
In query likelihood, our assumption
is that this probability of relevance
can be approximated by the probability
of query given a document and relevance.
So intuitively, this probability just
captures the following probability.
And that is if a user likes document d,
how likely would
the user enter query q ,in
order to retrieve document d?
So we assume that the user likes d,
because we have a relevance value here.
And then we ask the question about how
likely we'll see this particular query
from this user?
So this is the basic idea.
Now, to understand this idea,
let's take a look at the general idea or
the basic idea of
Probabilistic Retrieval Models.
So here, I listed some imagined
relevance status values or
relevance judgments of queries and
documents.
For example, in this line,
it shows that q1 is a query
that the user typed in.
And d1 is a document
that the user has seen.
And 1 means the user thinks
d1 is relevant to q1.
So this R here can be also approximated
by the click-through data that a search
engine can collect by watching how you
interacted with the search results.
So in this case, let's say
the user clicked on this document.
So there's a 1 here.
Similarly, the user clicked on d2 also,
so there is a 1 here.
In other words,
d2 is assumed to be relevant to q1.
On the other hand,
d3 is non-relevant, there's a 0 here.
And d4 is non-relevant and then d5 is
again, relevant, and so on and so forth.
And this part, maybe,
data collected from a different user.
So this user typed in q1 and then found
that the d1 is actually not useful,
so d1 is actually non-relevant.
In contrast, here we see it's relevant.
Or this could be the same query typed
in by the same user at different times.
But d2 is also relevant, etc.
And then here,
we can see more data about other queries.
Now, we can imagine we
have a lot of such data.
Now we can ask the question,
how can we then estimate
the probability of relevance?
So how can we compute this
probability of relevance?
Well, intuitively that just means
if we look at all the entries
where we see this particular d and
this particular q, how likely we'll
see a one on this other column.
So basically that just means that
we can just collect the counts.
We can first count how many
times we have seen q and
d as a pair in this table and
then count how many times
we actually have also seen
1 in the third column.
And then, we just compute the ratio.
So let's take a look at
some specific examples.
Suppose we are trying to compute this
probability for d1, d2 and d3 for q1.
What is the estimated probability?
Now, think about that.
You can pause the video if needed.
Try to take a look at the table.
And try to give your
estimate of the probability.
Have you seen that,
if we are interested in q1 and d1,
we'll be looking at these two pairs?
And in both cases, well,
actually, in one of the cases, the user
has said this is 1, this is relevant.
So R = 1 in only one of the two cases.
In the other case, it's 0.
So that's one out of two.
What about the d1 and the d2?
Well, they are here, d1 and d2, d1 and d2,
in both cases, in this case, R = 1.
So it's a two out of two and
so on and so forth.
So you can see with this approach,
we can actually score these documents for
the query, right?
We now have a score for d1,
d2 and d3 for this query.
And we can simply rank them
based on these probabilities and
so that's the basic idea
probabilistic retrieval model.
And you can see it makes a lot of sense,
in this case,
it's going to rank d2 above
all the other documents.
Because in all the cases,
when you have c and q1 and d2, R = 1.
The user clicked on this document.
So this also should show that
with a lot of click-through data,
a search engine can learn a lot from
the data to improve their search engine.
This is a simple example
that shows that with even
with small amount of entries here we can
already estimate some probabilities.
These probabilities would give us
some sense about which document
might be more relevant or more useful
to a user for typing this query.
Now, of course, the problems that we
don't observe all the queries and
all the documents and
all the relevance values, right?
There would be a lot of unseen documents,
in general,
we have only collected the data from the
documents that we have shown to the users.
And there are even more unseen queries
because you cannot predict what
queries will be typed in by users.
So obviously,
this approach won't work if we apply
it to unseen queries or unseen documents.
Nevertheless, this shows the basic idea
of probabilistic retrieval model and
it makes sense intuitively.
So what do we do in such a case when
we have a lot of unseen documents and
unseen queries?
Well, the solutions that we have
to approximate in some way.
So in this particular case called
a query likelihood retrieval model,
we just approximate this by
another conditional probability.
p(q given d, R=1).
So in the condition part, we assume that
the user likes the document because we
have seen that the user
clicked on this document.
And this part shows that
we're interested in how
likely the user would
actually enter this query.
How likely we will see this
query in the same row.
So note that here, we have made
an interesting assumption here.
Basically, we're going to do, assume that
whether the user types in this query
has something to do with whether
user likes the document.
In other words,
we actually make the following assumption.
And that is a user formulates a query
based on an imaginary relevant document.
Where if you just look at this
as conditional probability,
it's not obvious we
are making this assumption.
So what I really meant is that
to use this new conditional
probability to help us score,
then this new conditional
probability will have to somehow
be able to estimate this
conditional probability without
relying on this big table.
Otherwise we would be having
similar problems as before, and
by making this assumption,
we have some way to bypass this big table,
and try to just model how the user
formulates the query, okay?
So this is how you can
simplify the general model so
that we can derive a specific
relevant function later.
So let's look at how this model work for
our example.
And basically,
what we are going to do in this case
is to ask the following question.
Which of these documents is most
likely the imaginary relevant
document in the user's mind when
the user formulates this query?
So we ask this question and we quantify
the probability and this probability is
a conditional probability of observing
this query if a particular document is in
fact the imaginary relevant
document in the user's mind.
Here you can see we've computed all
these query likelihood probabilities.
The likelihood of queries
given each document.
Once we have these values,
we can then rank these documents
based on these values.
So to summarize, the general idea
of modern relevance in the proper
risk model is to assume the we introduce
a binary random variable R, here.
And then,
let the scoring function be defined
based on this conditional probability.
We also talked about approximating
this by using the query likelihood.
And in this case we have a ranking
function that's basically
based on the probability of
a query given the document.
And this probability should be interpreted
as the probability that a user who
likes document d, would pose query q.
Now, the question of course is, how do
we compute this conditional probability?
At this in general has to do with how
you compute the probability of text,
because q is a text.
And this has to do with a model
called a Language Model.
And these kind of models
are proposed to model text.
So more specifically, we will be
very interested in the following
conditional probability
as is shown in this here.
If the user liked this document,
how likely the user would pose this query.
And in the next lecture we're going to do,
giving introduction to language
models that we can see how we
can model text that was a probable
risk model, in general.
[MUSIC]