[SOUND] This lecture is about
the statistical language model.
In this lecture,
we're going to give an introduction
to statistical language model.
This has to do with how do you model
text data with probabilistic models.
So it's related to how we model
query based on a document.
We're going to talk about
what is a language model.
And then we're going to talk about the
simplest language model called the unigram
language model, which also happens to be
the most useful model for text retrieval.
And finally, what this class
will use is a language model.
What is a language model?
Well, it's just a probability
distribution over word sequences.
So here, I'll show one.
This model gives the sequence Today
is Wednesday a probability of 0.001.
It give Today Wednesday is a very,
very small probability
because it's non-grammatical.
You can see the probabilities
given to these sentences or
sequences of words can vary
a lot depending on the model.
Therefore, it's clearly context dependent.
In ordinary conversation,
probably Today is Wednesday is most
popular among these sentences.
Imagine in the context of
discussing apply the math,
maybe the eigenvalue is positive,
would have a higher probability.
This means it can be used to
represent the topic of a text.
The model can also be regarded
as a probabilistic mechanism for
generating text.
And this is why it's also often
called a generating model.
So what does that mean?
We can imagine this is a mechanism that's
visualised here as a stochastic system
that can generate sequences of words.
So, we can ask for a sequence,
and it's to send for
a sequence from the device if you want,
and it might generate, for example,
Today is Wednesday, but it could
have generated any other sequences.
So for example,
there are many possibilities, right?
So in this sense,
we can view our data as basically
a sample observed from
such a generating model.
So, why is such a model useful?
Well, it's mainly because it can quantify
the uncertainties in natural language.
Where do uncertainties come from?
Well, one source is simply
the ambiguity in natural language
that we discussed earlier in the lecture.
Another source is because we don't
have complete understanding,
we lack all the knowledge
to understand the language.
In that case,
there will be uncertainties as well.
So let me show some examples of questions
that we can answer with a language model
that would have interesting
applications in different ways.
Given that we see John and feels,
how likely will we see happy
as opposed to habit as the next
word in a sequence of words?
Now, obviously, this would be very useful
for speech recognition because happy and
habit would have similar acoustic sound,
acoustic signals.
But, if we look at the language model,
we know that John feels happy would be
far more likely than John feels habit.
Another example, given that we
observe baseball three times and
game once in a news article,
how likely is it about sports?
This obviously is related to text
categorization and information retrieval.
Also, given that a user is
interested in sports news,
how likely would the user
use baseball in a query?
Now, this is clearly related
to the query likelihood
that we discussed in the previous lecture.
So now,
let's look at the simplest language model,
called a unigram language model.
In such a case,
we assume that we generate a text by
generating each word independently.
So this means the probability of
a sequence of words would be then
the product of
the probability of each word.
Now normally,
they're not independent, right?
So if you have single word in like
a language, that would make it far more
likely to observe model than if
you haven't seen the language.
So this assumption is not
necessarily true, but
we make this assumption
to simplify the model.
So now the model has precisely N
parameters, where N is vocabulary size.
We have one probability for each word, and
all these probabilities must sum to 1.
So strictly speaking,
we actually have N-1 parameters.
As I said,
text can then be assumed to be assembled,
drawn from this word distribution.
So for example,
now we can ask the device or
the model to stochastically generate
the words for us, instead of sequences.
So instead of giving a whole sequence,
like Today is Wednesday,
it now gives us just one word.
And we can get all kinds of words.
And we can assemble these
words in a sequence.
So that will still allow you
to compute the probability of
Today is Wednesday as the product
of the three probabilities.
As you can see, even though we have not
asked the model to generate the sequences,
it actually allows us to compute
the probability for all the sequences, but
this model now only needs N
parameters to characterize.
That means if we specify
all the probabilities for
all the words, then the model's
behavior is completely specified.
Whereas if we don't make this assumption,
we would have to specify probabilities for
all kinds of combinations
of words in sequences.
So by making this assumption, it makes it
much easier to estimate these parameters.
So let's see a specific example here.
Here I show two unigram language
models with some probabilities.
And these are high probability
words that are shown on top.
The first one clearly suggests
a topic of text mining,
because the high probability
was all related to this topic.
The second one is more related to health.
Now we can ask the question,
how likely were observe a particular
text from each of these two models?
Now suppose we sample
words to form a document.
Let's say we take the first distribution,
would you like to sample words?
What words do you think would be
generated while making a text or
maybe mining maybe another word?
Even food,
which has a very small probability,
might still be able to show up.
But in general, high probability
words will likely show up more often.
So we can imagine what general text
of that looks like in text mining.
In fact, with small probability,
you might be able to actually generate
the actual text mining paper.
Now, it will actually be meaningful,
although the probability will be very,
very small.
In an extreme case, you might
imagine we might be able to generate
a text mining paper that would be
accepted by a major conference.
And in that case,
the probability would be even smaller.
But it's a non-zero probability,
if we assume none of the words
have non-zero probability.
Similarly from the second topic,
we can imagine we can generate
a food nutrition paper.
That doesn't mean we cannot generate this
paper from text mining distribution.
We can, but the probability would be very,
very small, maybe smaller than even
generating a paper that can be accepted
by a major conference on text mining.
So the point is that
the keeping distribution,
we can talk about the probability of
observing a certain kind of text.
Some texts will have higher
probabilities than others.
Now let's look at the problem
in a different way.
Suppose we now have available
a particular document.
In this case, many of the abstract or
the text mining table, and
we see these word counts here.
The total number of words is 100.
Now the question you ask here
is an estimation question.
We can ask the question which model,
which one of these distribution has
been used to generate this text,
assuming that the text has been generated
by assembling words from the distribution.
So what would be your guess?
What we have to decide are what
probabilities text mining, etc.,
would have.
Suppose the view for a second, and
try to think about your best guess.
If you're like a lot of people,
you would have guessed that well,
my best guess is text has a probability
of 10 out of 100 because I've
seen text 10 times, and
there are in total 100 words.
So we simply normalize these counts.
And that's in fact the word justified, and
your intuition is consistent
with mathematical derivation.
And this is called the maximum
likelihood estimator.
In this estimator,
we assume that the parameter settings
of those that would give our observe
the data the maximum probability.
That means if we change these
probabilities, then the probability of
observing the particular text
data would be somewhat smaller.
So you can see,
this has a very simple formula.
Basically, we just need to look at
the count of a word in a document,
and then divide it by the total number of
words in the document or document lens.
Normalize the frequency.
A consequence of this is,
of course, we're going to assign
zero probabilities to unseen words.
If we have an observed word,
there will be no incentive to assign a
non-zero probability using this approach.
Why?
Because that would take away probability
mass for these observed words.
And that obviously wouldn't maximize
the probability of this
particular observed text data.
But one has still question whether
this is our best estimate.
Well, the answer depends on what kind
of model you want to find, right?
This estimator gives a best model
based on this particular data.
But if you are interested in a model
that can explain the content of the full
paper for this abstract, then you
might have a second thought, right?
So for thing,
there should be other words in the body
of that article, so
they should not have zero probabilities,
even though they're not
observed in the abstract.
So we're going to cover this
a little bit more later
in this class in the query
likelihood model.
So let's take a look at some possible
uses of these language models.
One use is simply to use
it to represent the topics.
So here I show some general
English background texts.
We can use this text to
estimate a language model,
and the model might look like this.
Right, so on the top, we have those
all common words, the, a, is, we,
etc., and then we'll see some
common words like these, and
then some very,
very rare words in the bottom.
This is a background language model.
It represents the frequency of
words in English in general.
This is the background model.
Now let's look at another text,
maybe this time,
we'll look at the computer
science research papers.
So we have a collection of
computer science research papers,
we do as mentioned again, we can just
use the maximum likelihood estimator,
where we simply normalize the frequencies.
Now in this case, we'll get
the distribution that looks like this.
On the top, it looks similar because
these words occur everywhere,
they are very common.
But as we go down,
we'll see words that are more related to
computer science,
computer software, text, etc.
And so although here, we might also see
these words, for example, computer, but
we can imagine the probability here is
much smaller than the probability here.
And we will see many other words here that
would be more common in general English.
So you can see this distribution
characterizes a topic of
the corresponding text.
We can look at even the smaller text.
So in this case,
let's look at the text mining paper.
Now if we do the same,
we have another distribution,
again the can be expected
to occur in the top.
The sooner we see text, mining,
association, clustering,
these words have relatively
high probabilities.
In contrast, in this distribution, the
text has a relatively small probability.
So this means, again,
based on different text data,
we can have a different model,
and the model captures the topic.
So we call this document
the language model, and
we call this collection language model.
And later, you will see how they're
used in the retrieval function.
But now,
let's look at another use of this model.
Can we statistically find what words
are semantically related to computer?
Now how do we find such words?
Well, our first thought is that let's take
a look at the text that match computer.
So we can take a look at all the documents
that contain the word computer.
Let's build a language model.
We can see what words we see there.
Well, not surprisingly, we see these
common words on top as we always do.
So in this case, this language model gives
us the conditional probability of seeing
the word in the context of computer.
And these common words will
naturally have high probabilities.
But we also see the computer itself and
software will have relatively
high probabilities.
But if we just use this model,
we cannot just say all these words
are semantically related to computer.
So ultimately, what we'd like to
get rid of is these common words.
How can we do that?
It turns out that it's possible
to use language model to do that.
But I suggest you think about that.
So how can we know what
words are very common,
so that we want to kind
of get rid of them?
What model will tell us that?
Well, maybe you can think about that.
So the background language model
precisely tells us this information.
It tells us what was
our common in general.
So if we use this background model,
we would know that these words
are common words in general.
So it's not surprising to observe
them in the context of computer.
Whereas computer has a very
small probability in general, so
it's very surprising that we have seen
computer with this probability, and
the same is true for software.
So then we can use these two
models to somehow figure out
the words that are related to computer.
For example, we can simply take the ratio
of these group probabilities and
normalize the topic of language model
by the probability of the word in
the background language model.
So if we do that, we take the ratio,
we'll see that then on the top,
computer is ranked, and
then followed by software,
program, all these words
related to computer.
Because they occur very frequently in the
context of computer, but not frequently in
the whole collection, whereas these common
words will not have a high probability.
In fact,
they have a ratio about 1 down there
because they are not really
related to computer.
By taking the sample of text
that contains the computer,
we don't really see more occurrences
of that than in general.
So this shows that even with
these simple language models,
we can do some limited
analysis of semantics.
So in this lecture,
we talked about language model,
which is basically a probability
distribution over text.
We talked about the simplest language
model called unigram language model,
which is also just a word distribution.
We talked about the two
uses of a language model.
One is we represent the topic in a
document, in a collection, or in general.
The other is we discover
word associations.
In the next lecture, we're going to talk
about how language model can be used to
design a retrieval function.
Here are two additional readings.
The first is a textbook on statistical
natural language processing.
The second is an article that
has a survey of statistical
language models with a lot of
pointers to research work.
[MUSIC]