[SOUND]
This lecture is about query likelihood,
probabilistic retrieval model.
In this lecture,
we continue the discussion of
probabilistic retrieval model.
In particular, we're going to talk about
the query light holder retrieval function.
In the query light holder retrieval model,
our idea is model.
How like their user who likes a document
with pose a particular query?
So in this case,
you can imagine if a user likes this
particular document about
a presidential campaign news.
Now we assume,
the user would use this a document as
a basis to impose a query to try and
retrieve this document.
So again, imagine use a process
that works as follows.
Where we assume that
the query is generated by
assembling words from the document.
So for example, a user might
pick a word like presidential,
from this document and
then use this as a query word.
And then the user would pick
another word like campaign, and
that would be the second query word.
Now this of course is an assumption
that we have made about
how a user would pose a query.
Whether a user actually followed this
process may be a different question, but
this assumption has allowed us to formerly
characterize this conditional probability.
And this allows us to also not rely on
the big table that I showed you earlier
to use empirical data to
estimate this probability.
And this is why we can use this
idea then to further derive
retrieval function that we can
implement with the program language.
So as you see the assumption
that we made here is each query
word is independent of the sample.
And also each word is basically
obtained from the document.
So now let's see how this works exactly.
Well, since we are completing
a query likelihood
then the probability here is just
the probability of this particular query,
which is a sequence of words.
And we make the assumption that each
word is generated independently.
So as a result, the probability
of the query is just a product
of the probability of each query word.
Now how do we compute
the probability of each query word?
Well, based on the assumption that a word
is picked from the document
that the user has in mind.
Now we know the probability of each word
is just the relative frequency of each
word in the document.
So for example, the probability of
presidential given the document.
Would be just the count
of presidential document
divided by the total number of words
in the document or document s.
So with these assumptions we now have
actually a simple formula for retrieval.
We can use this to rank our documents.
So does this model work?
Let's take a look.
Here are some example documents
that you have seen before.
Suppose now the query is
presidential campaign and
we see the formula here on the top.
So how do we score this document?
Well, it's very simple.
We just count how many times do
we have seen presidential or
how many times do we have seen campaigns,
etc.
And we see here 44, and
we've seen presidential twice.
So that's 2 over the length of
document 4 multiplied by 1 over
the length of document 4 for
the probability of campaign.
And similarly, we can get probabilities
for the other two documents.
Now if you look at these numbers or
these formulas for
scoring all these documents,
it seems to make sense.
Because if we assume d3 and
d4 have about the same length,
then looks like a nominal rank d4
above d3 and which is above d2.
And as we would expect,
looks like it did captures
a TF query state, and so
this seems to work well.
However, if we try a different
query like this one,
presidential campaign update
then we might see a problem.
Well what problem?
Well think about the update.
Now none of these documents
has mentioned update.
So according to our assumption that a user
would pick a word from a document to
generate a query, then the probability of
obtaining the word update would be what?
Would be 0.
So that causes a problem,
because it would cause all these documents
to have zero probability
of generating this query.
Now why it's fine to have zero probability
for d2, which is non-relevant?
It's not okay to have 0 for d3 and
d4 because now we no longer
can distinguish them.
What's worse?
We can't even distinguish them from d2.
So that's obviously not desirable.
Now when a [INAUDIBLE] has such result,
we should think about what
has caused this problem?
So we have to examine what
assumptions have been made,
as we derive this ranking function.
Now is you examine those assumptions
carefully you will realize,
what has caused this problem?
So take a moment to think about it.
What do you think is the reason why update
has zero probability and how do we fix it?
So if you think about this from the moment
you realize that that's because we
have made an assumption
that every query word must
be drawn from the document
in the user's mind.
So in order to fix this, we have to
assume that the user could have drawn
a word not necessarily from the document.
So that's the improved model.
An improvement here is to say that,
well instead of drawing
a word from the document,
let's imagine that the user would actually
draw a word from a document model.
And so I show a model here.
And we assume that this document is
generated using this unigram language
model.
Now, this model doesn't necessarily assign
zero probability for update in fact,
we can assume this model does not
assign zero probability for any word.
Now if we're thinking this way then
the generation process is a little bit
different.
Now the user has this model in mind
instead of this particular document.
Although the model has to be
estimated based on the document.
So the user can again generate
the query using a singular process.
Namely, pick a word for example,
presidential and another word campaign.
Now the difference is that this time
we can also pick a word like update,
even though update doesn't
occur in the document
to potentially generate
a query word like update.
So that a query was updated
1 times 0 probabilities.
So this would fix our problem.
And it's also reasonable because when our
thinking of what the user is looking for
in a more general way, that is unique
language model instead of fixed document.
So how do we compute
this query likelihood?
If we make this sum wide
involved two steps.
The first one is compute this model, and
we call it document language model here.
For example, I've shown two pulse models
here, it's major based on two documents.
And then given a query like a data mining
algorithms the thinking is that we'll
just compute the likelihood of this query.
And by making independence
assumptions we could then have this
probability as a product of
the probability of each query word.
We do this for both documents, and
then we can score these two documents and
then rank them.
So that's the basic idea of this
query likelihood retrieval function.
So more generally this ranking function
would look like in the following.
Here we assume that the query has n words,
w1 through wn, and
then the scoring function.
The ranking function is the probability
that we observe this query,
given that the user is
thinking of this document.
And this is assume it will be product of
probabilities of all individual words.
This is based on independent assumption.
Now we actually often score
the document before this query by
using log of the query likelihood
as shown on the second line.
Now we do this to avoid
having a lot of small probabilities,
mean multiply together.
And this could cause under flow and we
might loose the precision by transforming
the value in our algorithm function.
We maintain the order of these documents
yet we can avoid the under flow problem.
And so if we take longer than
transformation of course,
the product would become a sum
as you on the second line here.
So the sum of all the query
words inside of the sum
that is one of the probability of
this word given by the document.
And then we can further rewrite
the sum to a different form.
So in the first sum here, in this sum,
we have it over all the query words and
query word.
And in this sum we have a sum
of all the possible words.
But we put a counter here
of each word in the query.
Essentially we are only considering
the words in the query,
because if a word is not in the query,
the count will be 0.
So we're still considering
only these n words.
But we're using a different form as
if we were going to take a sample of
all the words in the vocabulary.
And of course, a word might occur
multiple times in the query.
That's why we have a count here.
And then this part is log of
the probability of the word,
given by the document language model.
So you can see in this retrieval function,
we actually know the count
of the word in the query.
So the only thing that we don't know
is this document language model.
Therefore, we have converted
the retrieval problem
include the problem of estimating
this document language model.
So that we can compute the probability of
each query word given by this document.
And different estimation methods would
lead to different ranking functions.
This is just like a different way to
place document in the vector space
which leads to a different ranking
function in the vector space model.
Here different ways to
estimate will lead to
a different ranking function for
query likelihood.
[MUSIC]