[SOUND]
This
lecture is about smoothing
of language models.
In this lecture,
we're going to continue talking about
the probabilistic retrieval model.
In particular,
we're going to talk about the smoothing of
language model in the query
likelihood retrieval method.
So you have seen this slide
from a previous lecture.
This is the ranking function
based on the query likelihood.
Here, we assume that the independence of
generating each query word And the formula
would look like the following where
we take a sum of all the query words.
And inside the sum there is a log
of probability of a word given by
the document or document image model.
So the main task now is to estimate this
document language model as we
said before different methods for
estimating this model would lead
to different retrieval functions.
So in this lecture, we're going to
be looking to this in more detail.
So how do we estimate this language model?
Well the obvious choice would be
the maximum likelihood estimate
that we have seen before.
And that is we're going to normalize
the word frequencies in the document.
And estimate the probability
it would look like this.
This is a step function here.
Which means all of the words that have
the same frequency count will
have identical problem with it.
This is another freedom to count,
that has different probability.
Note that for words that have not
occurred in the document here
they will have 0 probability.
So we know this is just like the model
that we assume earlier in the lecture.
Where we assume that the use of
the simple word from the document to
a formula to clear it.
And there's no chance of assembling any
word that's not in the document and
we know that's not good.
So how do we improve this?
Well in order to assign
a none 0 probability
to words that have not been observed in
the document, we would have to take away
some probability mass from the words
that are observed in the document.
So for example here, we have to take away
some probability of the mass because we
need some extra probability mass for
the words otherwise they won't sum to 1.
So all these probabilities must sum to 1.
So to make this transformation and to
improve the maximum likelihood estimated
by assigning non zero probabilities to
words that are not observed in the data.
We have to do smoothing and
smoothing has to do with improving
the estimate by considering
the possibility that if the author
had been asking to write more words for
the document,
the author might have written other words.
If you think about this factor
then the a smoothed language model
would be a more accurate than
the representation of the actual topic.
Imagine you have seen an abstract
of a research article.
Let's say this document is abstract.
If we assume and see words in this
abstract that we have a probability of 0.
That would mean there's
no chance of sampling
a word outside the abstract
of the formulated query.
But imagine a user who is interested
in the topic of this subject.
The user might actually
choose a word that's not in
that chapter to use as query.
So obviously,
if we has asked this author to write more
author would have written
a full text of the article.
So smoothing of the language
model is an attempt to try
to recover the model for
the whole article.
And then of course,
we don't have knowledge about any
words that are not
observed in the abstract.
So that's why smoothing is
actually a tricky problem.
So let's talk a little more about
how to smooth a language model.
The key question here is, what probability
should be assigned to those unseen words?
And there are many different
ways of doing that.
One idea here, that's very useful for
retrieval is let the probability of unseen
word be proportional to its probability
given by a reference language model.
That means if you don't observe
the word in the dataset.
We're going to assume that its
probability is kind of governed
by another reference language
model that we will construct.
It will tell us which unseen words
would have a higher probability.
In the case of retrieval,
a natural choice would be to
take the collection language model
as the reference language model.
That is to say, if you don't
observe a word in the document,
we're going to assume that
the probability of this word
would be proportional to the probability
of word in the whole collection.
So more formally,
we'll be estimating the probability
of a word key document as follows.
If the word is seen in
the document then the probability
would be this counted the maximum
likelihood estimate P sub c here.
Otherwise, if the word is not seen in the
document we're going to let probability
be proportional to the probability
of the word in the collection.
And here the coefficient that offer is to
control the amount of probability
mass that we assign to unseen words.
Obviously, all these
probabilities must sum to 1, so
alpha sub d is constrained in some way.
So what if we plug in this
smoothing formula into our
query likelihood ranking function?
This is what we will get.
In this formula, we have this
as a sum over all the query words and
those that we have written here as the sum
of all the vocabulary, you see here.
This is the sum of all
the words in the vocabulary,
but not that we have a count
of the word in the query.
So in fact, we are just taking
a sample of query words.
This is now a common
way that we would use,
because of its convenience
in some transformations.
So this is as I said,
this is sum of all the query words.
In our smoothing method,
we assume that the words that
are not observed in the method would have
a somewhat different form of probability.
Name it's four, this foru.
So we're going to do then,
decompose the sum into two parts.
One sum is over all the query words
that are matching the document.
That means that in this sum, all the words
have a non zero probability
in the document.
Sorry, it's the non zero count
of the word in the document.
They all occur in the document.
And they also have to of course
have a non zero count in the query.
So these are the query words
that are matching the document.
On the other hand, in this sum we
are taking a sum of all the words
that are not all query was
not matching the document.
So they occur in the query
due to this term, but
they don't occur in the document.
In this case,
these words have this probability because
of our assumption about the smoothing.
That here, these seen words
have a different probability.
Now, we can go further by
rewriting the second sum
as a difference of two other sums.
Basically, the first sum is
the sum of all the query words.
Now, we know that the original sum
is not over all the query words.
This is over all the query words that
are not matched in the document.
So here we pretend that they
are actually over all the query words.
So we take a sum over all the query words.
Obviously, this sum has extra
terms that are not in this sum.
Because, here we're taking
sum over all the query words.
There, it's not matched in the document.
So in order to make them equal, we will
have to then subtract another sum here.
And this is the sum over all the query
words that are matching in the document.
And this makes sense, because here
we are considering all query words.
And then we subtract the query
that was matched in the document.
That would give us the query that
was not matched in the document.
And this is almost a reverse
process of the first step here.
And you might wonder why
do we want to do that.
Well, that's because if we do this,
then we have different forms
of terms inside of these sums.
So now, you can see in this sum
we have all the words matched,
the query was matching the document
with this kind of term.
Here we have another sum over the same set
of terms, matched query terms in document.
But inside the sum, it's different.
But these two sums can clearly be merged.
So if we do that, we'll get another form
of the formula that looks like
before me at the bottom here.
And note that this is
a very interesting formula.
Because here we combine
these two that all or
some of the query words matching in
the document in the one sum here.
And the other sum now is
decomposing into two parts.
And these two parts
look much simpler just,
because these are the probabilities
of unseen words.
This formula is very interesting
because you can see the sum is now over
the match the query terms.
And just like in the vector space model,
we take a sum
of terms that are in the intersection of
query vector and the document vector.
So it already looks a little bit
like the vector space model.
In fact, there's even more similarity
here as we explain on this slide.
[MUSIC]