[SOUND]
So I showed you how we rewrite the query
like holder which is a function into
a form that looks like the formula
of this slide after if we make
the assumption about the smoothing,
the language model based on
the collection language model.
Now if you look at this rewriting,
it will actually give us two benefits.
The first benefit is it helps us better
understand this ranking function.
In particular, we're going to show that
from this formula we can see smoothing
with the collection language model would
give us something like a TF-IDF weighting
and length normalization.
The second benefit is that
it also allows us to compute
the query like holder more efficiently.
In particular we see that
the main part of the formula
is a sum over the match
of the query terms.
So this is much better than if we
take a sum over all the words.
After we smooth the document the damage
model we essentially have non zero problem
for all the words.
So this new form of the formula is
much easier to score or to compute.
It's also interesting to note that
the last term here is actually
independent of the document.
Since our goal is to
rank the documents for
the same query we can ignore this term for
ranking.
Because it's going to be the same for
all the documents.
Ignoring it wouldn't affect
the order of the documents.
Inside the sum, we
also see that each matched query
term would contribute a weight.
And this weight actually
is very interesting because it
looks like a TF-IDF weighting.
First we can already see it has
a frequency of the word in a query
just like in the vector space model.
When we take a thought product,
we see the word frequency in
the query to show up in such a sum.
And so naturally this part would
correspond between the vector
element from the documented vector.
And here indeed we can see it actually
encodes a weight that has similar
in factor to TF-IDF weight.
I'll let you examine it, can you see it?
Can you see which part is capturing TF?
And which part is
a capturing IDF weighting?
So if want you can pause
the video to think more about it.
So have you noticed that this P sub
seen is related to the term frequency
in the sense that if a word occurs
very frequently in the document,
then the s made through probability
here will tend to be larger.
So this means this term is really
doing something like a TF weight.
Now have you also noticed that
this term in the denominator
is actually achieving the factor of IDF?
Why, because this is the popularity
of the term in a collection.
But it's in the denominator, so if the
probability in the collection is larger
then the weight is actually smaller.
And this means a popular term.
We actually have a smaller weight and this
is precisely what IDF weighting is doing.
Only that we now have
a different form of TF and IDF.
Remember IDF has a logarithm
of documented frequency.
But here we have something different.
But intuitively it
achieves a similar effect.
Interestingly, we also have something
related to the length of libation.
Again, can you see which factor is related
to the document length in this formula?
What I just say is that this term
is related to IDF weighting.
This collection probability,
but it turns out that
this term here is actually related
to document length normalization.
In particular, F of sub d might
be related to document length.
So it encodes how much probability
mass we want to give to unseen worlds.
How much smoothing do we want to do?
Intuitively, if a document is long,
then we need to do less smoothing because
we can assume that data is large enough.
We probably have observed all the words
that the author could have written.
But if the document is short then r of
sub t could be expected to be large.
We need to do more smoothing.
It's likey there are words that have
not been written yet by the author.
So this term appears to paralyze
the non document in that
other sub D would tend to be longer
than or larger than for a long document.
But note that alpha sub d
also occurs here and so
this may not actually be necessary
paralyzing long documents.
The effect is not so clear yet.
But as we will see later, when we
consider some specific smoothing methods,
it turns out that they do
paralyze long documents.
Just like in TF-IDF weighting and
document length normalization
formula in the vector space model.
So, that's a very interesting
observation because it means
we don't even have to think about
the specific way of doing smoothing.
We just need to assume that if we smooth
with this collection memory model,
then we would have a formula that
looks like TF-IDF weighting and
documents length violation.
What's also interesting that we have
very fixed form of the ranking function.
And see we have not heuristically
put a logarithm here.
In fact, you can think about why
we would have a logarithm here.
You look at the assumptions that
we have made, it would be clear
it's because we have used a logarithm
of query like for scoring.
And we turned the product into a sum
of logarithm of probability, and
that's why we have this logarithm.
Note that if only want to heuristically
implement a TF weighting and
IDF weighting, we don't necessary
have to have a logarithm here.
Imagine if we drop this logarithm,
we would still have TF and IDF weighting.
But what's nice with problem risk modeling
is that we are automatically given
the logarithm function here.
And that's basically a fixed form
of the formula that we did not
really have to heuristically design,
and in this case if you try to drop
the logarithm the model probably won't
work as well as if you keep the logarithm.
So a nice property of problem risk
modeling is that by following some
assumptions and the probability rules
we'll get a formula automatically.
And the formula would have
a particular form like in this case.
And if we heuristically design
the formula we may not necessarily
end up having such a specific formula.
So to summarize, we talked about the need
for smoothing the document imaging model.
Otherwise it would give zero probability
for unseen words in the document, and
that's not good for
storing a query with such an unseen word.
It's also necessary, in general,
to improve the accuracy of estimating
the model represent
the topic of this document.
The general idea of smoothing in retrieval
is to use the connecting memory model to,
to give us some clue about which unseen
words should have a higher probability.
That is, the probability of an unseen
word is assumed to be proportional
to its probability in the collection.
With this assumption, we've shown that we
can derive a general ranking formula for
query likelihood that has
effect of TF-IDF weighting and
document length normalization.
We also see that, through some rewriting,
the scoring of such a ranking function
is primarily based on sum of weights on
matched query terms,
just like in the vector space model.
But, the actual ranking
function is given us
automatically by the probability rules and
assumptions that we have made.
And like in the vector space model
where we have to heuristically
think about the form of the function.
However, we still need to address
the question how exactly we should
smooth the document and the model.
How exactly we should
use the reference and
model based on the connection
to adjust the probability of
the maximum micro is made of and
this is the topic of the next batch.
[MUSIC]