[SOUND]
This lecture is about the specific
smoothing methods for language models
used in probabilistic retrieval model.
In this lecture, we will continue
the discussion of language models for
information retrieval, particularly
the query likelihood retrieval method.
And we're going to talk about specifically
the smoothing methods used for
such a retrieval function.
So this is a slide from a previous
lecture where we show that with a query
likelihood ranking and smoothing
with the collection language model,
we add up having a retrieval function
that looks like the following.
So this is the retrieval function based on
these assumptions that we have discussed.
You can see it's a sum of all
the matching query terms, here.
And inside its sum is the count
of the term in the query and
some weight for the term in the document.
We have t of i, the f weight here, and
then we have another constant here in n.
So clearly if we want to implement this
function using programming language,
we still need to figure
out a few variables.
In particular, we're going to need to
know how to estimate the probability
of a word exactly and how do we set alpha.
So in order to answer this question,
we have to think about very specific
smoothing methods, and
that is main topic of this lecture.
We're going to talk about
two smoothing methods.
The first is simple linear
interpolation with a fixed coefficient.
And this is also called
a Jelinek-Mercer smoothing.
So the idea is actually very simple.
This picture shows how
we estimate a document
language model by using
maximum likelihood estimate.
That gives us word counts normalized by
the total number of words in the text.
The idea of using this method
is to maximize the probability
of the observed text.
As a result,
if a word like network is not observed
in the text, it's going to get
0 probability, as shown here.
So the idea of smoothing, then,
is to rely on collection language model
where this word is not going to have
a zero probability to help us decide what
nonzero probability should
be assigned to such a word.
So we can note that network has
a nonzero probability here.
So in this approach what we do is we do
a linear interpolation between the maximum
likelihood placement here and
the collection language model, and this
is computed by the smoothing parameter
lambda, which is between 0 and 1.
So this is a smoothing parameter.
The larger lambda is,
the more smoothing we will have.
So by mixing them together,
we achieve the goal of assigning nonzero
probabilities to a word like network.
So let's see how it works for
some of the words here.
For example, if we compute
the smooth probability for text.
Now the maximum likelihood
estimated gives us 10 over 100, and
that's going to be here.
But the collection probability is this.
So we'll just combine them
together with this simple formula.
We can also see the word network,
which used to have a zero probability,
now is getting a non-zero
probability of this value.
And that's because the count is
going to be zero for network here.
But this part is nonzero, and
that's basically how this method works.
Now if you think about this and
you can easily see now the alpha
sub d in this smoothing
method is basically lambda.
Because that's remember the coefficient
in front of the probability
of the word given by the collection
language model here.
Okay, so
this is the first smoothing method.
The second one is similar but
it has a tie-in into the coefficient for
linear interpolation.
It's often called Dirichlet Prior,
or Bayesian, Smoothing.
So again here we face problem
of zero probability for
an unseen word like network.
Again we will use the collection
language model, but in this case,
we're going to combine them
in somewhat different ways.
The formula first can be seen as
a interpolation of the maximum
likelihood estimate and
the collection language model as before,
as in the J-M smoothing method.
Only that the coefficient now
is not lambda, a fixed number,
but a dynamic coefficient in this form,
where mu is a parameter,
it's a non-negative value.
And you can see if we
set mu to a constant,
the effect is that a long document would
actually get a smaller coefficient here.
Because a long document
will have longer lengths,
therefore the coefficient
is actually smaller.
And so a long document would have
less smoothing, as we would expect.
So this seems to make more sense
than a fixed coefficient smoothing.
Of course,
this part would be of this form so
that the two coefficients would sum to 1.
Now this is one way to
understand this smoothing.
Basically, it means it's a dynamic
coefficient interpolation.
There is another way to understand
this formula which is even
easier to remember, and
that's on this side.
So it's easier to see how we can rewrite
the smoothing method in this form.
Now in this form we can easily
see what change we have made to
the maximum likelihood estimate,
which would be this part.
So normalize the count
by the document length.
So in this form we can see what we did is
we add this to the count of every word.
So what does this mean?
Well, this is basically something related
to the probability of the word in
the collection.
And we multiply that by the parameter mu.
And when we combine this
with the count here,
essentially we are adding
pseudocounts to the observed text.
We pretend every word has
got this many pseudocount.
So the total count would be
the sum of these pseudocounts and
the actual count of
the word in the document.
As a result, in total we would
have added this many pseudocounts.
Why?
Because if you take somewhat this one
over all the words, then we'll see the
probability of the words would sum to 1,
and that gives us just mu.
So this is the total number of
pseudocounts that we added.
And so
these probabilities would still sum to 1.
So in this case, we can easily
see the method is essentially to
add this as a pseudocount to this data.
Pretend we actually augment the data
by including some pseudo data
defined by the collection language model.
As a result, we have more counts is that
the total counts for
a word would be like this.
And as a result, even if a word has zero
count here, let's say if we have zero
count here, then it would still have
nonzero count because of this part.
So this is how this method works.
Let's also take a look at
some specific example here.
So for text again we will
have 10 as the original count
that we actually observe, but
we also add some pseudocount.
And so the probability of
text would be of this form.
Naturally, the probability of
network would be just this part.
And so here you can also see
what's alpha sub d here.
Can you see it?
If you want to think about it,
you can pause the video.
But you'll notice that this
part is basically alpha sub d.
So we can see, in this case,
alpha sub d does depend on the document,
because this length
depends on the document,
whereas in the linear interpolation,
the J-M smoothing method,
this is a constant.
[MUSIC]