[MUSIC]
This lecture is about Evaluation of
Text Retrieval Systems In the previous
lectures, we have talked about
the a number of Text Retrieval Methods,
different kinds of ranking functions.
But how do we know which
one works the best?
In order to answer this question,
we have to compare them and that means we
have to evaluate these retrieval methods.
So this is the main topic of this lecture.
First, lets think about why
do we have to do evaluation?
I already give one reason.
That is, we have to use evaluation
to figure out which retrieval method
works better.
Now this is very important for
advancing our knowledge.
Otherwise, we wouldn't know whether a new
idea works better than an old idea.
In the beginning of this course, we talked
about the problem of text retrieval.
We compare it with data base retrieval.
There we mentioned that text retrieval
is an empirically defined problem.
So evaluation must rely on users.
Which system works better,
would have to be judged by our users.
So, this becomes a very
challenging problem
because how can we get users
involved in the evaluation?
How can we do a fair comparison
of different method?
So just go back to the reasons for
evaluation.
I listed two reasons here.
The second reason, is basically what I
just said, but there is also another
reason which is to assess the actual
utility of a Text Regional system.
Imagine you're building your
own such annual applications,
it would be interesting knowing how well
your search engine works for your users.
So in this case,
matches must reflect the utility to
the actual users in real occasion.
And typically, this has to be
done by using user starters and
using the real search engine.
In the second case, or the second reason,
the measures actually all need to collated
with the utility to actually use this.
Thus, they don't have to accurately
reflect the exact utility to users.
So the measure only needs to be good
enough to tell which method works better.
And this is usually done
through a test collection.
And this is the main idea that we'll
be talking about in this course.
This has been very important for
comparing different algorithms and
for improving search
engine system in general.
So let's talk about what to measure.
There are many aspects of searching
that we can measure, we can evaluate.
And here,
I listed the three major aspects.
One, is effectiveness or accuracy.
How accurate are the search results?
In this case, we're measuring a system's
capability of ranking relevant documents
on top of non relevant ones.
The second, is efficiency.
How quickly can you get the results?
How much computing resources
are needed to answer a query?
In this case, we need to measure the space
and time overhead of the system.
The third aspect is usability.
Basically the question is,
how useful is a system for new user tasks.
Here, obviously, interfaces and
many other things also important and
would typically have to do user studies.
Now in this course, we're going to
talk mostly about effectiveness and
accuracy measures.
Because the efficiency and
usability dimensions are not
really unique to search engines.
And so they are needed for
without any other software systems.
And there is also good coverage
of such and other causes.
But how to evaluate search
engine's quality or accuracy is
something unique to text retrieval and
we're going to talk a lot about this.
The main idea that people have proposed
before using a test set to evaluate
the text retrieval algorithm is called
the Cranfield Evaluation Methodology.
This one actually was developed
a long time ago, developed in 1960s.
It's a methodology for
laboratory test of system components.
Its sampling methodology that has
been very useful, not just for
search engine evaluation.
But also for evaluating virtually
all kinds of empirical tasks, and
for example in natural language processing
or in other fields where the problem
is empirical to find, we typically
would need to use such a methodology.
And today with the big data challenging
with the use of machine
learning everywhere.
This methodology has been very popular,
but it was first developed for
a search engine application in the 1960s.
So the basic idea of this approach is
to build a reusable test collection and
define measures.
Once such a test collection is built,
it can be used again and
again to test different algorithms.
And we're going to define measures
that allow you to quantify
performance of a system and algorithm.
So how exactly will this work?
Well we can do have a sample collection of
documents and this is adjusted to simulate
the real document collection
in the search application.
We're going to also have a sample
set of queries, or topics.
This is a little simulator
that uses queries.
Then, we'll have to have
those relevance judgments.
These are judgments of which documents
should be returned for which queries.
Ideally, they have to be made by
users who formulated the queries.
Because those are the people that know
exactly what documents would be used for.
And finally, we have to have matches for
quantify how well our system's result
matches the ideal ranked list.
That would be constructed base
on user's relevance judgements.
So this methodology is very useful for
starting retrieval algorithms,
because the test can be reused many times.
And it will also provide a fair
comparison for all the methods.
We have the same criteria or
same dataset to be used to
compare different algorithms.
This allows us to compare
a new algorithm with
an old algorithm that was divided many
years ago, by using the same standard.
So this is the illustration of this works,
so as I said,
we need our queries that are showing here.
We have Q1, Q2 etc.
We also need the documents and
that's called the document caching and
on the right side you will see
we need relevance judgments.
These are basically the binary judgments
of documents with respect to a query.
So for example,
D1 is judged as being relevant to Q1,
D2 is judged as being relevant as well,
and D3 is judged as not relevant.
And the Q1 etc.
These will be created by users.
Once we have these, and
we basically have a test collection.
And then if you have two systems,
you want to compare them,
then you can just run each
system on these queries and
the documents and
each system would then return results.
Let's say if the queries Q1 and
then we would have the results here.
Here I show R sub A as
the results from system A.
So this is, remember we talked about
task of computing approximation
of the relevant document set.
R sub A is system A's approximation here.
And R sub B is system B's
approximation of relevant documents.
Now, let's take a look at these results.
So which is better?
Now imagine if a user,
which one would you like?
Now let's take a look at the both results.
And there are some differences and
there are some documents that
are returned by both systems.
But if you look at the results,
you will feel that maybe
A is better in the sense that we don't
have many number element documents.
And among the three documents returned,
the two of them are relevant.
So that's good, it's precise.
On the other hand one council
say maybe B is better,
because we've got all of
them in the documents.
We've got three instead of two.
So which one is better and
how do we quantify this?
Well, obviously this question
highly depends on a user's task.
It depends on users as well.
You might even imagine for
some users may be system A is better.
If the user is not interested in
getting all the random documents.
Right, in this case the user doesn't
have to read a million users will
see most of the relevant documents.
On the other hand,
one can also imagine the user might need
to have as many random
documents as possible.
For example, if you're doing a literature
survey you might be in the sigma category,
and you might find that
system B is better.
So in the case, we will have to also
define measures that will quantify them.
And we might need it to define multiple
measures because users have different
perspectives of looking at the results.
[MUSIC]