[SOUND]
This
lecture is about the basic measures for
evaluation of text retrieval systems.
In this lecture,
we're going to discuss how we design basic
measures to quantitatively
compare two retrieval systems.
This is a slide that you have seen
earlier in the lecture where we talked
about the Granville
evaluation methodology.
We can have a test faction that consists
of queries, documents, and [INAUDIBLE].
We can then run two systems on these
data sets to contradict the evaluator.
Their performance.
And we raise the question,
about which set of results is better.
Is system A better or is system B better?
So let's now talk about how to
accurately quantify their performance.
Suppose we have a total of 10 relevant
documents in the collection for
this query.
Now, the relevant judgments show on
the right in [INAUDIBLE] obviously.
And we have only seen 3 [INAUDIBLE] there,
[INAUDIBLE] documents there.
But, we can imagine there are other Random
documents in judging for this query.
So now, intuitively,
we thought that system
A is better because it
did not have much noise.
And in particular we have seen
that among the three results,
two of them are relevant but in system B,
we have five results and
only three of them are relevant.
So intuitively it looks like
system A is more accurate.
And this infusion can be captured
by a matching holder position,
where we simply compute to what extent
all the retrieval results are relevant.
If you have 100% position,
that would mean that all
the retrieval documents are relevant.
So in this case system A has
a position of two out of
three System B has some
sweet hold of 5 and
this shows that system
A is better frequency.
But we also talked about System B
might be prefered by some other units
would like to retrieve as many
random documents as possible.
So in that case we'll have to compare
the number of relevant documents that they
retrieve and
there's another method called recall.
This method uses the completeness
of coverage of random documents
In your retrieval result.
So we just assume that there are ten
relevant documents in the collection.
And here we've got two of them,
in system A.
So the recall is 2 out of 10.
Whereas System B has called a 3,
so it's a 3 out of 10.
Now we can see by recall
system B is better.
And these two measures turn out to
be the very basic of measures for
evaluating search engine.
And they are very important because
they are also widely used in many
other test evaluation problems.
For example, if you look at
the applications of machine learning,
you tend to see precision recall numbers
being reported and for all kinds of tasks.
Okay so, now let's define these
two measures more precisely.
And these measures are to evaluate a set
of retrieved documents, so that means
we are considering that approximation
of the set of relevant documents.
We can distinguish 4 cases depending
on the situation of the documents.
A document can be retrieved or
not retrieved, right?
Because we are talking
about a set of results.
A document can be also relevant or
not relevant depending on whether the user
thinks this is a useful document.
So we can now have counts of documents in.
Each of the four categories again
have a represent the number of
documents that have been retrieved and
relevant.
B for documents that are not retrieved but
rather etc.
No with this table then
we can define precision.
As the ratio of the relevant
retrieved documents A to the total
of relevant retrieved documents.
So, this is just A divided
by The sum of a and c.
The sum of this column.
Singularly recall is defined by
dividing a by the sum of a and b.
So that's again to divide a by.
The sum of the row instead of the column.
All right, so we can see precision and
recall is all focused on looking at the a,
that's the number of
retrieved relevant documents.
But we're going to use
different denominators.
Okay, so what would be an ideal result.
Well, you can easily see being
the ideal case would have precision and
recall oil to be 1.0.
That means We have got 1% of
all the Relevant documents
in our results, and all of the results
that we returned all Relevant.
At least there's no single
Not Relevant document returned.
In reality, however, high recall tends
to be associated with low precision.
And you can imagine why that's the case.
As you go down the to try to get as
many random documents as possible,
you tend to encounter a lot of documents,
so the precision has to go down.
Note that this set can also
be defined by a cut off.
In the rest of this, that's why although
these two measures are defined for
retrieve the documents, they are actually
very useful for evaluating a rank list.
They are the fundamental measures in
task retrieval and many other tasks.
We often are interested in The precision
at ten documents for web search.
This means we look at how many documents
among the top ten results
are actually relevant.
Now, this is a very meaningful measure,
because it tells us how many relevant
documents a user can expect to see
On the first page of where they
typically show ten results.
So precision and recall
are the basic matches and we need to
use them to further evaluate a search
engine, but they are the Building blocks.
We just said that there tends to be
a trailoff between precision and recall,
so naturally it would be
interesting to combine them.
And here's one method that's often used,
called F-measure And
it's a [INAUDIBLE] mean of precision and
recall as defined on this slide.
So, you can see at first, compute the.
Inverse of R and P here,
and then it would interpret
the 2 by using coefficients
depending on parameter beta.
And after some transformation you can
easily see it would be of this form.
And in any case it just becomes
an agent of precision and
recall, and beta is a parameter,
that's often set to 1.
It can control the emphasis
on precision or recall always
set beta to 1 We end up having a special
case of F-Measure, often called F1.
This is a popular measure that's often
used as a combined precision and recall.
And the formula looks very simple.
It's just this, here.
Now it's easy to see that if
you have a Larger precision, or
larger recall than f
measure would be high.
But, what's interesting is that
the trade off between precision and
recall is captured
an interesting way in f1.
So, in order to understand that, we
can first look at the natural
Why not just the combining and
using the symbol arithmetically
as efficient here?
That would be likely the most natural way
of combining them So what do you think?
If you want to think more,
you can pause the video.
So why is this not as good as F1?
Or what's the problem with this?
Now, if you think about
the arithmetic mean,
you can see this is
the sum of multiple terms.
In this case,
it's the sum of precision and recall.
In the case of a sum, the total value
tends to be dominated by the large values.
that means if you have a very high P or
very high R then you really
don't care about whether the other value
is low so the whole sum would be high.
Now this is not desirable because one
can easily have a perfect recall.
We have perfect recall easily.
Can we imagine how?
It's probably very easy to
imagine that we simply retrieve
all the documents in the collection and
then we have a perfect recall.
And this will give us 0.5 as the average.
But such results are clearly not
very useful for the users even
though the average using this
formula would be relevantly high.
In contrast you can see F 1 would
reward a case where precision and
recall are roughly That seminar, so
it would a case where you had
extremely high value for one of them.
So this means f one encodes
a different trade off between that.
Now this example shows
actually a very important.
Methodology here.
But when you try to solve a problem you
might naturally think of one solution,
let's say in this it's
this error mechanism.
But it's important not to
settle on this source.
It's important to think whether you
have other ways to combine that.
And once you think about the multiple
variance It's important to analyze their
difference, and then think about
which one makes more sense.
In this case, if you think more carefully,
you will think that F1
probably makes more sense.
Than the simple.
Although in other cases there
may be different results.
But in this case the seems not reasonable.
But if you don't pay attention
to these subtle differences
you might just take a easy way to
combine them and then go ahead with it.
And here later, you will find that,
the measure doesn't seem to work well.
All right.
So this methodology is actually very
important in general, in solving problems.
Try to think about the best solution.
Try to understand the problem very well,
and then
know why you needed this measure, and why
you need to combine precision and recall.
And then use that to guide you in
finding a good way to solve the problem.
To summarize, we talked about
precision which addresses the question
are there retrievable
results all relevant?
We also talk about the Recall.
Which addresses the question, have all of
the relevant documents been retrieved.
These two, are the two,
basic matches in text and retrieval in.
They are used for
many other tasks, as well.
We talk about F measure as a way to
combine Precision Precision and recall.
We also talked about the tradeoff
between precision and recall.
And this turns out to depend
on the user's search tasks and
we'll discuss this point
more in a later lecture.
[MUSIC]