[MUSIC]
This lecture is about how to evaluate
the text retrieval system when we have
multiple levels of judgements.
In this lecture, we will continue
the discussion of evaluation.
We're going to look at how to
evaluate a text retrieval system,
when we have multiple
levels of judgements.
So far we have talked about
the binary judgements,
that means a document is judged as
being relevant or not relevant.
But earlier, we also talk about
the relevance as a medal of degrees.
So we often can distinguish
very high relevant documents,
those are very useful documents,
from moderately relevant documents.
They are okay, they are useful perhaps.
And further from now, we're adding
the documents, those are not useful.
So imagine you can have ratings for
these pages.
Then, you would have
multiple levels of ratings.
For example, here I show example of three
levels, 3 for relevant, sorry 3 for
very relevant, 2 for marginally relevant,
and 1 for non-relevant.
Now, how do we evaluate the search
engine system using these judgements?
Obvious that the map doesn't work, average
of precision doesn't work, precision, and
recall doesn't work,
because they rely on binary judgements.
So let's look at some top ranked
results when using these judgements.
Imagine the user would be mostly
care about the top ten results here.
And we marked the rating levels,
or relevance levels,
for these documents as shown here,
3, 2, 1, 1, 3, etcetera.
And we call these gain.
And the reason why we call it
the gain is because the measure
that we are infusing is called the NDCG
normalized or accumulated gain.
So this gain, basically,
can measure how much a gain of random
information a user can obtain by
looking at each document, right?
So looking at the first document,
the user can gain 3 points.
Looking at the non-relevant document
user would only gain 1 point.
Looking at the moderator or
marginally relevant,
document the user would get 2 points,
etcetera.
So, this gain to each of the measures is
a utility of the document from a user's
perspective.
Of course, if we assume the user
stops at the 10 documents and
we're looking at the cutoff at 10,
we can look at the total gain of the user.
And what's that?
Well, that's simply the sum of these,
and we call it the Cumulative Gain.
So if the user stops after the position 1,
that's just a 3.
If the user looks at another document,
that's a 3+2.
If the user looks at the more documents,
then the cumulative gain is more.
Of course this is at the cost of
spending more time to examine the list.
So cumulative gain gives
us some idea about how
much total gain the user would have if
the user examines all these documents.
Now, in NDCG, we also have another letter
here, D, discounted cumulative gain.
So, why do we want to do discounting?
Well, if you look at this cumulative gain,
there is one deficiency,
which is it did not consider the rank
position of these documents.
So for example, looking at this sum here,
and we only know there is 1
highly relevant document,
1 marginally relevant document,
2 non-relevant documents.
We don't really care
where they are ranked.
Ideally, we want these two to be ranked
on the top which is the case here.
But how can we capture that intuition?
Well we have to say, well this is 3 here
is not as good as this 3 on the top.
And that means the contribution
of the gain from different
positions has to be
weighted by their position.
And this is the idea of discounting,
basically.
So we're going to to say, well, the first
one does not need to be discounted
because the user can be assumed
that will always see this document.
But the second one,
this one will be discounted a little bit
because there's a small possibility
that the user wouldn't notice it.
So we divide this gain by
a weight based on the position.
So log of 2,
2 is the rank position of this document.
And when we go to the third position,
we discounted even more,
because the normalizer is log of 3,
and so on and so forth.
So when we take such a sum that a lower
ranked document would not contribute
that much as a highly ranked document.
So that means if you, for example,
switch the position of this, let's say
this position, and this one, and then
you would get more discount if you put,
for example very relevant
document here as opposed to here.
Imagine if you put the 3 here,
then it would have to be discounted.
So it's not as good as if
you we would put the 3 here.
So this is the idea of discounting.
Okay, so now at this point that we have
got a discounted cumulative gain for
measuring the utility of this ranked
list with multiple levels of judgements.
So are we happy with this?
Well, we can use this to rank systems.
Now, we still need to do a little bit more
in order to make this measure
comparable across different topics.
And this is the last step, and by the way,
here we just show the DCG at 10,
so this is the total sum of DCG,
all these 10 documents.
So the last step is called N,
normalization.
And if we do that,
then we'll get the normalized DCG.
So how do we do that?
Well, the idea here is we're
going to normalize DCG by
the ideal DCG at the same cutoff.
What is the ideal DCG?
Well, this is the DCG of an ideal ranking.
So imagine if we have 9 documents in
the whole collection rated 3 here.
And that means in total we
have 9 documents rated 3.
Then our ideal rank lister would have put
all these 9 documents on the very top.
So all these would have to be 3 and
then this would be followed by a 2 here.
Because that's the best we could
do after we have run out of the 3.
But all these positions would be 3.
Right?
So this would our ideal ranked list.
And then we had computed the DCG for
this ideal rank list.
So this would be given by this
formula that you see here.
And so this ideal DCG would then
be used as the normalizer DCG.
So here.
And this idea of DCG would
be used as a normalizer.
So you can imagine now,
normalization essentially is to
compare the actual DCG with the best DCG
you can possibly get for this topic.
Now why do we want to do this?
Well, by doing this we'll map the DCG
values into a range of 0 through 1.
So the best value, or the highest value,
for every query would be 1.
That's when your rank list is,
in fact, the ideal list but
otherwise, in general,
you will be lower than one.
Now, what if we don't do that?
Well, you can see, this transformation,
or this normalization,
doesn't really affect the relative
comparison of systems for
just one topic, because this ideal
DCG is the same for all the systems,
so the ranking of systems based on
only DCG would be exactly the same as
if you rank them based
on the normalized DCG.
The difference however is
when we have multiple topics.
Because if we don't do normalization,
different topics will have
different scales of DCG.
For a topic like this one,
we have 9 highly relevant documents,
the DCG can get really high,
but imagine in another case,
there are only two very relevant documents
in total in the whole collection.
Then the highest DCG that
any system could achieve for
such a topic would not be very high.
So again, we face the problem of
different scales of DCG values.
When we take an average,
we don't want the average to be
dominated by those high values.
Those are, again, easy queries.
So, by doing the normalization,
we can have avoided the problem,
making all the queries contribute
to equal to the average.
So, this is a idea of NDCG, it's used for
measuring a rank list based on multiple
level of relevance judgements.
In a more general way this
is basically a measure
that can be applied to any ranked task
with multiple level of judgements.
And the scale of the judgements
can be multiple, can be more than
binary not only more than binary they
can be much multiple levels like 1,
0, 5 or
even more depending on your application.
And the main idea of this measure,
just to summarize,
is to measure the total utility
of the top k documents.
So you always choose a cutoff and
then you measure the total utility.
And it would discount the contribution
from a lowly ranked document.
And then finally,
it would do normalization to ensure
comparability across queries.
[MUSIC]