[SOUND].
This lecture is about some practical
issues that you would have to address in
evaluation of text retrieval systems.
In this lecture, we will continue
the discussion of evaluation.
We'll cover some practical
issues that you have to solve
in actual evaluation of
text retrieval systems.
So, in order to create
the test collection,
we have to create a set of queries.
A set of documents and
a set of relevance judgments.
It turns out that each is
actually challenging to create.
First, the documents and
queries must be representative.
They must represent the real queries and
real documents that the users handle.
And we also have to use many queries and
many documents in order to
avoid a bias of conclusions.
For the matching of relevant
documents with the queries.
We also need to ensure that there exists a
lot of relevant documents for each query.
If a query has only one, that's
a relevant option we can actually then.
It's not very informative to
compare different methods
using such a query because there's not
that much room for us to see difference.
So ideally, there should be more
relevant documents in the clatch but yet
the queries also should represent
the real queries that we care about.
In terms of relevance judgments,
the challenge is to ensure
complete judgments of all
the documents for all the queries.
Yet, minimizing human and
fault, because we have to use human
labor to label these documents.
It's very labor intensive.
And as a result, it's impossible to
actually label all the documents for
all the queries, especially considering
a giant data set like the web.
So this is actually a major challenge,
it's a very difficult challenge.
For measures, it's also challenging,
because we want measures that would
accurately reflect
the perceived utility of users.
We have to consider carefully
what the users care about.
And then design measures to measure that.
If your measure is not
measuring the right thing,
then your conclusion would be misled.
So it's very important.
So we're going to talk about
a couple of issues here.
One is the statistical significance test.
And this also is a reason why
we have to use a lot of queries.
And the question here is how sure can
you be that observe the difference
doesn't simply result from
the particular queries you choose.
So here are some sample results of
average position for System A and
System B into different experiments.
And you can see in the bottom,
we have mean average of position.
So the mean, if you look at the mean
average of position, the mean average
of positions are exactly the same
in both experiments, right?
So you can see this is 0.20,
this is 0.40 for System B.
And again here it's also 0.20 and
0.40, so they are identical.
Yet, if you look at these exact average
positions for different queries.
If you look at these numbers in detail,
you would realize that in one case,
you would feel that you can trust
the conclusion here given by the average.
In the another case, in the other case,
you will feel that, well, I'm not sure.
So, why don't you take a look at all these
numbers for a moment, pause the media.
So, if you look at the average,
the mean average of position,
we can easily, say that well,
System B is better, right?
So, after all it's 0.40 and
this is twice as much as 0.20,
so that's a better performance.
But if you look at these two experiments,
look at the detailed results.
You will see that, we've been more
confident to say that, in the case one,
in experiment one.
In this case.
Because these numbers seem to be
consistently better for System B.
Whereas in Experiment 2, we're not sure
because looking at some results like this,
after System A is better and
this is another case System A is better.
But yet if we look at only average,
System B is better.
So, what do you think?
How reliable is our conclusion,
if we only look at the average?
Now in this case, intuitively,
we feel Experiment 1 is more reliable.
But how can we quantitate
the answer to this question?
And this is why we need to do
statistical significance test.
So, the idea of the statistical
significance test is basically to
assess the variants across
these different queries.
If there is a big variance,
that means the results could fluctuate
a lot according to different queries.
Then we should believe that,
unless you have used a lot of queries,
the results might change if we
use another set of queries.
Right, so this is then not so
if you have c high variance
then it's not very reliable.
So let's look at these results
again in the second case.
So, here we show two different
ways to compare them.
One is a sign test where
we just look at the sign.
If System B is better than System A,
we have a plus sign.
When System A is better we
have a minus sign, etc.
Using this case, if you see this,
well, there are seven cases.
We actually have four cases
where System B is better.
But three cases of System A is better,
intuitively,
this is almost like a random results,
right?
So if you just take a random
sample of you flip seven coins and
if you use plus to denote the head and
minus to denote the tail and
that could easily be the results of just
randomly flipping these seven coins.
So, the fact that the average is
larger doesn't tell us anything.
We can't reliably conclude that.
And this can be quantitatively
measured by a p value.
And that basically means
the probability that this result is
in fact from a random fluctuation.
In this case, probability is 1.0.
It means it surely is
a random fluctuation.
Now in Willcoxan test,
it's a non-parametric test,
and we would be not only
looking at the signs,
we'll be also looking at
the magnitude of the difference.
But we can draw a similar conclusion,
where you say it's very
likely to be from random.
To illustrate this, let's think
about that such a distribution.
And this is called a now distribution.
We assume that the mean is zero here.
Lets say we started with
assumption that there's
no difference between the two systems.
But we assume that because of random
fluctuations depending on the queries,
we might observe a difference.
So the actual difference might
be on the left side here or
on the right side here, right?
So, and this curve kind of shows
the probability that we will
actually observe values that
are deviating from zero here.
Now, so if we look at this picture then,
we see that
if a difference is observed here, then
the chance is very high that this is
in fact a random observation, right?
We can define a region of
likely observation because of
random fluctuation and
this is that 95% of all the outcomes.
And in this then the observed may
still be from random fluctuation.
But if you observe a value in this
region or a difference on this side,
then the difference is unlikely
from random fluctuation.
All right, so there's a very small
probability that you are observe
such a difference just because
of random fluctuation.
So in that case, we can then conclude
the difference must be real.
So System B is indeed better.
So this is the idea of
Statical Significance Test.
The takeaway message here is that you
have to use many queries to avoid
jumping into a conclusion.
As in this case,
to say System B is better.
There are many different ways of doing
this Statistical Significance Test.
So now, let's talk about the other
problem of making judgments and,
as we said earlier,
it's very hard to judge all the documents
completely unless it's
a very small data set.
So the question is,
if we can afford judging all the documents
in the collection,
which is subset should we judge?
And the solution here is Pooling.
And this is a strategy that has been used
in many cases to solve this problem.
So the idea of Pooling is the following.
We would first choose a diverse
set of ranking methods.
These are Text Retrieval systems.
And we hope these methods can help us
nominate like the relevant documents.
So the goal is to pick out
the relevant documents.
We want to make judgements on relevant
documents because those are the most
useful documents from users perspectives.
So then we're going to have
each to return top-K documents.
The K can vary from systems.
But the point is to ask them to suggest
the most likely relevant documents.
And then we simply combine
all these top-K sets
to form a pool of documents for
human assessors.
To judge, so imagine you have many
systems each were ten k documents.
We take the top-K documents,
and we form a union.
Now, of course, there are many
documents that are duplicated because
many systems might have retrieved
the same random documents.
So there will be some duplicate documents.
And there are also unique documents
that are only returned by one system.
So the idea of having diverse
set of ranking methods is to
ensure the pool is broad.
And can include as many possible
relevant documents as possible.
And then, the users would,
human assessors would make complete
the judgments on this data set, this pool.
And the other unjudged the documents are
usually just assumed to be non relevant.
Now if the pool is large enough,
this assumption is okay.
But if the pool is not very large,
this actually has to be reconsidered.
And we might use other
strategies to deal with them and
there are indeed other
methods to handle such cases.
And such a strategy is generally okay for
comparing systems that
contribute to the pool.
That means if you participate
in contributing to the pool,
then it's unlikely that it
would penalize your system
because the problematic
documents have all been judged.
However, this is problematic for
evaluating a new system that may
have not contributed to the pool.
In this case, a new system might
be penalized because it might have
nominated some read only documents
that have not been judged.
So those documents might be
assumed to be non relevant.
That's unfair.
So to summarize the whole part of textual
evaluation, it's extremely important.
Because the problem is the empirically
defined problem, if we
don't rely on users, there's no way to
tell whether one method works better.
If we have in the property
experiment design,
we might misguide our research or
applications.
And we might just draw wrong conclusions.
And we have seen this is
in some of our discussions.
So make sure to get it right for
your research or application.
The main methodology is the Cranfield
evaluation methodology.
And they are the main paradigm used in
all kinds of empirical evaluation tasks,
not just a search engine variation.
Map and nDCG are the two main
measures that you should definitely
know about and they are appropriate for
comparing ranking algorithms.
You will see them often
in research papers.
Precision at 10 documents is easier
to interpret from user's perspective.
So that's also often useful.
What's not covered is some other
evaluation strategy like A-B Test.
Where the system would mix two,
the results of two methods, randomly.
And then would show
the mixed results to users.
Of course, the users don't see
which result, from which method.
The users would judge those results or
click on those documents in
a search engine application.
In this case then, the search engine
can check or click the documents and
see if one method has contributed
more through the click the documents.
If the user tends to click on one,
the results from one method,
then it suggests that
message may be better.
So this is what leverages the real users
of a search engine to do evaluation.
It's called A-B Test and
it's a strategy that is often used by
the modern search engines or
commercial search engines.
Another way to evaluate IR or
textual retrieval is user studies and
we haven't covered that.
I've put some references here
that you can look at if you want
to know more about that.
So, there are three
additional readings here.
These are three mini books about
evaluation and they are all excellent
in covering a broad review of
Information Retrieval Evaluation.
And it covers some of the things
that we discussed, but
they also have a lot of others to offer.
[MUSIC]