Hello welcome to CS410 DSO Text Information Systems.
This is an online course offered by University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.
My name is ChengXiang Zhai.
I also have a nickname, Cheng.
I'm a professor of Computer Science at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.
I'm the instructor of this course.
This first lecture is just an introduction to the course.
Let's first to start with some motivation.
The problem we are trying to address in this course is how to harness big text data.
Text data is all kinds of data in
the form of natural languages such as English and Chinese.
Now, this kind of data is everywhere and also growing very quickly.
For example, you can find all kinds of
web pages on the Internet and the number of pages is growing quickly.
You can also find the blogs articles, news articles,
or Emails and other kind of documents and enterprise environment.
Of course, we will also have a lot of scientific literature in text form.
And nowadays, social media has been growing quickly.
So we now see, tweets and other social media data also in the form of text.
All such text data encode a lot of useful knowledge about the world
because it's in some sense the data reported by human census about the observe the world.
So we can analyzed this kind of data to discover a lot of useful knowledge.
Especially the knowledge about the human opinions or preferences.
So this kind of data is very useful and we can use
computational methods to turn such data into useful knowledge,
which can then be further used in many applications.
The main techniques for making this happen include the Text Retrieval and Text Mining.
And these are the main techniques that we will cover in this course.
Logically, in order to make use a lot of text data.
We would first do text retrieval,
and that's due to a large set of text data
into a smaller but much more relevant set of data,
that we actually need for a particular problem.
And this step, is usually implemented by
using text retrieval techniques that involve humans in
the loop to find and locate the most relevant documents to a particular problem.
Once we find the relevant documents,
the next step is to do text mining,
which is to further analyze the found of relevant documents to
discover useful knowledge to extract
the knowledge that can be directly used in application,
especially in a application such as decision making.
These two steps corresponding to Text Retrieval and Text Mining Techniques,
that we will cover in this course.
Based on this picture that I show you,
this course is designed to leverage to corresponding books that I've offered on Coursera,
which cover Text Retrieval and Text Mining respectively.
The first book is called,
Text Retrieval and Search Engines.
The second book is called,
the Text Mining and Analytics.
These two books have
comprehensive lecture videos that cover
basic concepts and principles and
methods for text retrieval and text mining respectively.
So, this online course,
will leverage all those lecture videos and also
the online quizzes that are provided through the Coursera platform.
But in addition to that,
we also need to add additional components in order to explore applications because
those books have covered a general techniques without a necessary discussing in depths
how those techniques are using applications.
So, to make the coverage more complete in CS410,
we were adding two additional components as shown here.
That is of course Products and Technology Review.
Both are meant to give the students freedom to choose a particular way to apply some of
the techniques that you have learned in those two books to solve
a real world problem or to further learn about a particular topic.
In the project, you will have opportunities to apply the knowledge that you have
learned in those two books to solve a real world problem in an integrated manner.
In technical review, you can leverage what you have
learned to learn even more about either tool kit
or a particular technology that can be
used to extend your knowledge about how to solve a problem.
The format of the course thus is a mixture of online videos plus
some high engagement module which mostly consists of
our interactions through forums as I will explain later.
And also, we will have a lot of interactions to help you
finish the course Project and Technology Review.
There are a number of goals that we
have kept in mind when designing this course and I want to share with
you these goals because they would help you understand
why the course has this particular format and
why you are asked to do certain components of the tasks.
The first goal is we want to emphasize both theory and practice.
Theory is obviously very important because the basic concepts and
general principles covering the theoretical part would be applicable to all applications.
That means, they are not just used for
today's applications but they can be used for solving future problems as well so,
they are more general.
Therefore, they have long lasting impact and utility value.
And this is achieved by having you to watch all the lecture videos,
and then to use quizzes and exams to make sure
that you have mastered all the basic ideas,
basic concepts and general principles and those general methods.
Practical skills are also very important,
and because of specific practical skills can be immediately useful for solving
the problems today and maybe you will be able to
resolve the problems that you encountered in your job.
And this is achieved by having you to do Programming assignments,
where you would be able to use existing tool kits,
to look into some algorithms in depths and to use some of
the algorithms to have some sense about how they work or how to improve them.
And finally, of course it's very important to integrate the theory and practice.
And this will be done by,
having you to work on Course projects.
The second goal is to Personalized Learning,
because every one of you has a different in need and different in preference,
and you will have a different in schedules as well,
because many of you are full time workers, perhaps.
And so, Personalized Learning is very important to ensure
everyone to receive the best education.
So to achieve this goal,
we have intentionally designed
the deadlines and the format of the course to be flexible so that,
you can have a lot of freedom to do self-paced learning.
For example, you can watch over the lecture videos at anytime that you want to.
Watch it, watch that.
And you can also finish all the quizzes pretty much
anytime and you can do the assignment,
program assigns particularly again in a flexible way.
In addition to self paced learning,
you would also have a choices of topics for project and the technology review.
And you will be able to work on a topic that's most interesting to you,
for both course project and technology review.
Finally, we also have the goal of
collaborative learning because this would maximize the efficiency of learning.
Our common goal is to help everyone learn maximum amount of knowledge,
while spending hopefully minimum amount of effort.
So, this is a common goal that we should all work toward,
and we should help each other achieve this goal.
To promote collaborative learning and to facilitate collaborative learning,
we will use forum-based interactions to enable all of us,
including many of you from different time zones,
to interact with each other effectively.
Another way to support a collaborative learning is to have you to work in groups,
to finish cost projects and technology reviews.
So, both technology reviews and
products can be done by working together with others in a group.
So, overall the format is as follows: first,
you will have to watch the lecture videos of those two MOOCs,
and this is also shown here on this slide,
and then you also need to take quizzes.
And these quizzes are given in a weekly manner.
But as I said, the deadlines are actually flexible.
So, you should be able to finish quizzes as soon as you
finish the corresponding lecture videos.
These quizzes are two.
There are also two kinds of quizzes.
There are practice quizzes that you can use to help you understand some concepts.
And there are also test quizzes.
Those are of course to make sure that you have indeed mastered the materials.
Then there are two exams.
Those two exams will be given at the end of each MOOC corresponding.
So, the first exam will be given at the end of the first MOOC on Test Retrieval,
and the second one will be given at the end of the second MOOC on Test Mining.
And then, during this period of watching these videos,
you will be also working on programming assignments.
Then at the end of the semester,
we'll leave about two weeks time for you to work intensively on the course project,
although you will be working on the course project throughout the semester.
But most of the time will be in the end of the semester.
Now, the course project will be down sequentially by following multiple steps.
The first is for you to select a topic.
You can select the topic from a list of topics that
we provide or you can propose your topic,
and then we'll ask you to submit
a short proposal to be more specific about what you want to work on.
And then, in the middle of the semester,
you will be asked to provide
a short progress report so that we can check
your progress and we can provide help in a timely manner.
And then, at the end of the semester,
you will deliver two things: one is a software and its documentation.
You upload that to a public website so that it's available to people.
The second one is a tutorial presentation,
a short presentation to explain how your software can be used by people.
There is also a technology review component which is mandatory and
this component will be correlated based on completion.
Everyone is required to finish this component.
Now, this component is designed to give you
an opportunity to explore further any topic that you're interested in.
This can be in that examination of a tool kit that you are interested in,
perhaps a tool that you have used in the course project,
or a comparison of multiple tools that can do similar things,
and you might have looked into multiple tools,
and you have some opportunity to compare them and to figure out which one is the best.
Such a writing would be helpful for others to understand how to
use a tool kit or which one to choose.
Of course, those of you who are interested in the methods,
you can also go in-depth to examine a certain type
of methods and write a brief review of them,
or looking to a cutting edge topic in your research and write
a review of the recent papers about the topic.
Now, we hope that you might be able to align
the technology review with your course project so that the two will
be kind of synergistic in that technology review will help
you learn more about the topic related to your course project,
while the course project will give you also a motivation for doing
an in-depth study of the topic via technology review.
Of course, we will try to help you finish all these tasks,
and we'll do our best to help you.
That means, the TAs and I will interact with you in various ways to help you,
and one way is a synchronous question answering and discussing via forums.
And the other way is to have
synchronous weekly office hours and that will be down by using video teleconferencing.
The grading will be done as follows: 25% of your grade will be based on the quizzes,
all the quizzes for the two MOOCs;
30% will be based on the two exams,
those two exams will be proctored exams;
25% will be based on the programming assignments,
there will be multiple programming assignments throughout the semester.
The remaining 20% will be based on your course project and that's for
the distribution as follows: 5% is for topic selection,
5% is for proposal,
and another 5% for progress report,
65% in most of the grade of the course project will be based on software deposit,
your deliverable for the project.
And finally, 20% is based on the tutorial presentation.
Now, most of these components in the course project will be graded based on completion.
Indeed, a lot of tasks you see in programming assignments are graded in
the same way and that is because we believe we have
designed the program assignments and course project in such a way
that you will be able to learn a lot by simply going through these tasks.
So, this is the effective way of learning by
doing and that's why we choose to grade based on completion.
That also means you have a lot of control over these grades,
because you can ensure that you finish
all these tasks and then you will get most of these grades.
The only part that will be based on the quality of solution is the tutorial presentation.
This is actually not just based on the quality of
your tutorial presenting but rather based on whether
you are software actually work as you propose.
So, does it provide all the functions that you propose?
Does it really work?
And this will likely affect some of the grade for tutorial presentation,
meaning that if a software for some reason doesn't really pass our test,
then we would deduct the points from here.
As I said, the technology review is not actually contributing to you grade,
but it's a metric component and it will be graded based on completion.
We also provide up to 5% of
extra credit based on your participation in the forum discussions.
And this is to encourage you to help
each other and particularly by answering questions posed by others.
We will be able to use log data from the forum to give you credit,
extra credit, and these extra credit points will be actually added to the regular points.
So that will allow you to actually increase
your grade as will be shown here in more detail.
And this is how we are going to determine your final letter grades.
They are based on the grade points you have collected over
the semester using this map shown here on the slide.
Mostly it's five points for each bracket but not always.
And as you can see,
if you have earned 5% extra credit and when adding this extra credit,
will likely help you move your grades up by one bracket,
although it won't be more than one bracket.
So, we feel that this fixed mapping would give you complete control over your grade,
so you can monitor your grade over the semester and kind of assess
your progress and also to adjust your schedule accordingly.
So, this is a visualization of your workload.
Horizontally, we show the timeline,
from the first day of instruction to the last day of instruction.
And then vertically, you can see there are mainly six tasks for you over the semester.
First, you will spend most of your time on watching the lecture videos,
and this is why we have a thick black line
there that shows that most of
your effort probably will be spent on watching lecture videos.
And then, you will be taking 12 quizzes,
and these will be spreading over most of the semester,
corresponding to about 12 weeks when you are expected to watch those lecture videos.
Now, we want to emphasize that you should spend most of your time to
watch videos and make sure you understand the materials before you take quizzes,
and this will ensure that you don't leave any holes.
If you do it the other way and by using quizzes to guide you through the lecture videos,
then you might leave some holes,
and that might hurt your performance on exams.
There will be two proctored exams that will be
given in the middle of the semester and also later in the semester,
at the end of the two box.
So, this is your third task.
The fourth task is programming assignments,
and this will be,
again, through the entire semester,
actually not really all the weeks in the semester,
but most of the weeks,
because we don't want you to use up the last two weeks,
which we reserve for you to work on course project.
And the course project is the fifth component.
And finally, you need to finish technology review.
Now, although most of the work of
the project is expected to be done at the end of the semester,
you will actually start working on it from the very beginning.
And, soon after the semester starts,
we will ask you to think about the topics and you will discuss
the topics and then form teams to submit the proposal.
But of course, during the first 12 weeks,
you will be most occupied by the lecture videos, quizzes,
and your assignments for programming.
So, that's why you will likely have more time to work on the project in the end.
The technology review is kind of designed to extend your knowledge based on your project.
But of course, you have the complete freedom
to choose whatever topic that you want to review.
So, you don't have to tie it to the project.
And so, we imagine that you would start
working on it a little bit after you have decided the project,
the topic, so that you can decide whether you want to tie
the technology review with your project.
So, it's good to keep this picture in mind throughout
the semester because you might have irregular schedule sometimes.
For example, you might find that you are very busy in the middle of the semester,
then this picture can help you adjust your schedule and the degree you
probably want to then work more on some of the tasks at the beginning of the semester,
so that you don't overwhelm yourself in the middle of the semester.
And similarly, if you expect to be very busy the end of the semester,
you might want to start working on the project much earlier.
So, I hope this picture will be always in your mind,
and you will be able to adjust your schedule accordingly
and to particularly work on tasks proactively,
in case you anticipate any busy time period.
Some of you have already taken maybe both MOOCs.
Now, if you are one of them,
then I think naturally,
you will have more time to work on other problems in this course.
So, you should take advantage of this
to proactively finish some of the tasks much more quickly.
In particular, since you have already watched those videos and then you can
simply review them and then you try to work on the quizzes
so that you can finish all the quizzes much more quickly.
You may be able to finish most of the programming assignments quickly too.
This is not only going to be helpful for you
in the sense that you will have a lot of time to work on course project, but also,
it would allow you to help others by answering
their questions on forums or helping them in other way,
like teaming up with them to work on the project.
However, I should also say that there are a few tasks that are,
unfortunately, have very fixed time that you cannot really work on in advance.
For example, the two exams will be scheduled on
some particular dates that would have no flexibility for you to work on earlier.
There may be some tasks in the programming assignments that have to be synchronized.
For example, we might run competition of
some tasks and there may be some synchronization that's needed,
but we would like to minimize the dependency so that you
could hopefully work on many of those tasks as early as you can.
And of course, we encourage you to use more time to finish
a more challenging course project or to finish
a higher quality technology review.
Now, we rely a lot on forum discussion,
and this is because we are in different time zones
and it's very hard to find a time that works well for everyone.
But forum has important advantages
of being able to accommodate everyone in the discussion.
So, this will be the primary way of our interactions and engagement,
and in particular, we will be using Piazza,
which is a forum that we have used for many other courses,
and it has proven to be a useful forum with a lot of useful functions.
The second advantage of forum is it would also enable you
to ask your questions as soon as you have a question.
And therefore, we can hopefully accelerate question answering and
so that you can have your question answered quickly on
the forum without waiting until office hour.
Finally, we hope that the forum discussions would help us
identify difficult concepts in those lectures,
so that we can focus on discussing these concepts or
explaining these concepts that are hard to understand in our office hours.
This would make better use of our office hours to help all of you.
Because of these reasons,
so the protocol of question answering will be as follows,
and we want to emphasize that it's important to
follow this protocol so that we can make effective use of our office hours,
so that you can get your questions answered more quickly,
so that you can all help each other in learning.
So, first, as soon as you have a question or issue to discuss,
post it immediately on the forum.
And this has a number of advantages, and first is,
it will give you the opportunity to have the question answered quickly because often,
your question may be answered by your peers or may be answered by a teacher or by me.
So, by posting the question immediately,
you have a better chance of getting the question answered quickly,
so that you won't have to wait.
And secondly, your question might also help others because sometimes
other students may have a similar question or may not
realize that they have encountered this question,
but you just articulated this question.
So, this is helpful for your peers as well.
And discussing of this question is often also a good way to learn.
However, if your question is not answered in a timely manner on the forum,
or addressed adequately from your perspective,
then you should email the question to all of us including me and TAs.
Please use a subject line that contains the keyword CS410DSO all together.
Of course, your subject line,
you can contain other keywords based on your question.
And then, if you don't receive a reply
from us by email in a timely manner, join an office-hour.
Now, we would do our best to reply to your emails but then,
depending on the number of emails,
depending on our own schedule,
we may not be able to always reply to your emails in a timely manner.
Of course, we would do our best to respond quickly but if we can't,
then you should come to one of our office hours.
We would try to schedule our office hours in different time slots during the day.
For example, we would have some time slot in the morning,
or late morning, or early afternoon,
and then another time slot in the evening.
And this is so that,
we can hopefully accommodate different time zones,
because the same slot of time may not be equally convenient with all of you.
So, we'll do our best again,
to diversify the time slots,
both in terms of the time in a day,
and also in terms of the days in a week.
The format of office hours is as follows, and this again,
is based on our need to make effective use and
the efficient use of our limited office hours to help you in the best way.
So, we will hold weekly office hours,
as I said, and we'll publish those time slots.
And the office hours will be given by using video-teleconference,
and particularly using Zoom,
and its used for system that has worked well.
And you can join or leave an office hour at any time and that means you can join late,
or you can leave early,
and it's very flexible.
So, don't feel that you always have to come at the beginning of the office hour.
Feel free to stop by in the last ten minutes,
if that's the best time for you.
And again, by taking advantage of the forum discussion, hopefully,
by the time of going to office hour,
we will only need to deal with some of the relatively difficult questions.
And the priority we will use
is to give the highest priority to any issues that have already been posted on forums,
but have not been resolved even after some email communications.
Those are clearly the toughest issues
because it has been posted on forum without a good answer,
and then was emailed to us and still not satisfactory solved.
So, we would have to give those issues the highest priority,
that means if there are such issues being raised during office hour,
those issues would be given the first priority.
After that, we'll look at the any other unresolved issues on forums.
That's why it's very important for you to post the issue on the forum first,
and only after resolving those issues that have already been posted
on forums would we take
other questions or issues that have not yet been posted on forums.
And of course, you should not
hesitate to bring any questions that you have or any issues you want to discuss.
It's just that, we want to have a policy to prioritize the issues that we want to handle,
so that we can provide the maximum benefit to all of
you by using our office hours efficiently.
Finally, I want to just say something
in general about how to get the most out of this course.
Perhaps, the most important advice is to plan ahead based on your own schedule,
because many of you are very busy.
So, you want to kind of take a look at
the picture that I showed you earlier about the tasks,
and then consider your own schedule.
Try to imagine which periods will be a relatively busy period
for you and identify what tasks you're supposed to work on in that period,
and try to finish those tasks earlier,
so that you don't overlap with yourself during that busy period.
And of course, at any time,
please let us know how we can help, again,
by using the forums as the first step.
And another thing to mention is also to allocate a sufficient time
for the preparation of two proctored exams because they will be given only once.
That means, you only have one chance to take each exam,
so you want to really prepare well for them.
However, those exams are mostly to confirm that you have indeed mastered the materials.
So, they will have similar questions to the quiz questions that you have already seen.
And in fact, some questions may be exactly the same as the questions in the quizzes.
And we do that because this would allow you
to have some sense about what the questions might look like in the exams.
So, they should not be much surprise if you have actually worked on
all the questions in those quizzes and have made
sure that you have understood the answers to those questions.
Of course, if you can,
try to complete the quizzes and program assignments ahead of time.
This would be to your advantage because you can now raise
your questions earlier that would allow you to have
more time to get your questions answered.
Therefore, by the time when you take the quiz,
then you would have all the questions resolved.
And it also would allow you to actively help others and to discuss any of
the problems that you have encountered that would help you earn the extra credit also.
The second advice is to post questions on forum immediately and
whenever you have difficulty understanding any part of the course materials.
And again, I want to emphasize the immediate action of posting any issue,
any question on the forums.
We would do our best to resolve those issues through the forums.
And it's the effective way to also engage the peers to help each other.
So, do not hesitate to post questions and we
won't to penalize you for posting many questions.
In fact, we'll reward that perhaps,
because that's one way to contribute to the forum discussion.
Finally, you should leverage collaborative learning,
this is kind of related to you posting your questions on forums,
and again, to actively participate in the forum discussion.
You will actually learn a lot from reading other people's posts,
even if you know the answers because they are
often opinions expressed about those materials.
So, we do hope that you have active discussion on
forums to help each other and to help each other, particularly,
to save time, to understand the difficult concepts,
to do well in the quizzes and exams,
and to finish assignments smoothly.
And finally, we do encourage you to help each other understand materials too.
So, we encourage you to answer others' questions,
and the system will record those answers.
We'll have a statistics about that,
and then we'll use that to give extra credit.
So, this was just the overall introduction to the course.
For more information, you can visit the course website on Coursera.
We hope you enjoy this course,
and I look forward to working with you. Thank you.