[MUSIC]
So now let's take a look at the specific
method that's based on regression.
Now, this is one of the many
different methods, and in fact,
it's one of the simplest methods.
And I choose this to explain
the idea because it's simple.
So in this approach, we simply assume
that the relevance of document with
respect to a query is related to a linear
combination of all the features.
Here I used Xi to denote the feature.
So Xi of Q and D is a feature.
And we can have as many
features as we would like.
And we assume that these features
can be combined in a linear manner.
And each feature is controlled
by a parameter here,
and this beta i is a parameter.
That's a weighting parameter.
A larger value would mean the feature
would have a higher weight,
and it would contribute more
to the scoring function.
This specific form of the function
actually also involves
a transformation of
the probability of relevance.
So this is the probability of relevance.
And we know that the probability of
relevance is within the range from 0 to 1.
And we could have just assumed that
the scoring function is related to
this linear combination.
So we can do a linear regression.
But then, the value of this linear
combination could easily go beyond 1.
So this transformation
here would map the 0
to 1 range to the whole
range of real values,
you can verify it by yourself.
So this allows us then to connect
to the probability of variance
which is between 0 and 1 to a linear
combination of arbitrary features.
And if we rewrite this into a probability
function, we would get the next one.
So on this equation, now we'll
have the probability of relevance.
And on the right hand side,
we'll have this form.
Now, this form is clearly nonnegative, and
it still involves a linear
combination of features.
And it's also clear that if this value is,
this is actually negative of the linear
combination in the equation above.
If this value here is large,
then it would mean this value is small.
And therefore,
this whole probability would be large.
And that's we expect, that basically,
it would mean if this combination
gives us a high value, then
the document's more likely irrelevant.
So this is our hypothesis.
Again, this is not necessarily the best
hypothesis, but this is a simple
way to connect these features with
the probability of relevance.
So now we have this combination function.
The next task is to
estimate the parameters so
that the function cache will be applied.
But without knowing the beta values,
it's harder to apply this function.
So let's see how can
estimate our beta values.
All right,
let's take a look at a simple example.
In this example, we have three features.
One is the BM25 score of the document and
the query.
One is the PageRank score of the document,
which might or
might not depend on the query.
We might have a topic-sensitive PageRank,
that would depend on the query.
Otherwise, the general PageRank
doesn't really depend on the query.
And then we have BM25 score on
the anchor test of the document.
Now, these are then the feature values for
a particular document query pair.
And in this case, the document is D1 and
the judgment says that it's relevant.
Here's another training instance and
it's these feature values,
but in this case, it's not relevant.
This is an oversimplified case where
we just have two instances, but
it's sufficient to illustrate the point.
So what we can do is we use
the maximum likelihood estimator to
actually estimate the parameters.
Basically, we're going to
predict the relevance status
of the document based
on the feature values.
That is, given that we observed
these feature values here.
Can we predict the relevance here?
Now, of course, the prediction would be
using this function that you see here.
And we hypothesize that the probability
of relevance is related to
features in this way.
So we are going to see, for what values of
beta we can predict the relevance well.
What do we mean by predicting
the relevance well?
Well, we just mean, in the first case, for
D1 this expression right here
should give high values.
In fact, we'll hope this
to gave a value close to 1.
Why?
Because this is a relevant document.
On the other hand,
in the second case, for D2,
we hope this value will be small, right.
Why?
Because it's a non-relevant document.
So now let's see how this can
be mathematically expressed.
And this is similar to expressing
the probability of document,
only that we are not talking about
the probability of words, but
talking about the probability
of relevance, 1 or 0.
So what's the probability
of this document being
relevant if it has these feature values?
Well, this is just this expression.
We just need to plug in the Xi's.
So that's what we will get.
It's exactly like what we have seen above,
only that we replaced these
Xi's with now specific values.
So for example, this 0.7 goes to here and
this 0.11 goes to here.
And these are different feature values,
and we combine them in
this particular way.
The beta values are still unknown.
But this gives us the probability
that this document is relevant,
if we assume such a model.
Okay?
And we want to maximize this probability,
since this is a relevant document.
What do we do for the second document?
Well, we want to compute the probability
that the prediction is non-relevant.
So this would mean we have to
compute 1 minus this expression,
since this expression is actually
the probability of relevance.
So to compute the non-relevance
from relevance,
we just do 1 minus
the probability of relevance.
Okay?
So this whole expression then
just is our probability of
predicting these two relevance values.
One is 1 here, one is 0.
And this whole equation
is our probability of
observing a 1 here and observing a 0 here.
Of course, this probability
depends on the beta values.
So then our goal is to adjust
the beta values to make this whole
thing reach its maximum,
make it as large as possible.
So that means we're going to compute this.
The beta is just the parameter
values that would
maximize this whole likelihood expression.
And what it means is,
if you look at the function, is,
we're going to choose betas to
make this as large as possible and
make this also as large as possible,
which is equivalent to say,
make this part as small as possible.
And this is precisely what we want.
So once we do the training,
now we will know the beta values.
So then this function
would be well-defined.
Once beta values are known, both this and
this would be completely specified.
So for any new query and new document,
we can simply compute the features for
that pair.
And then we just use this formula
to generate the ranking score.
And this scoring function can be used to
rank documents for a particular query.
So that's the basic idea
of learning to rank.
[MUSIC]