[SOUND]
There are many
more of the Munster learning algorithms
than the regression based approaches and
they generally attempt to direct
the optimizer retrieval method.
Like a MAP or nDCG.
Note that the optimization object or
function that we have seen
on the previous slide is not directly
related to the retrieval measure.
By maximizing the prediction of one or
zero, we don't necessarily optimize
the ranking of those documents.
One can imagine that our
prediction may not be too bad.
And let's say both are around 0.5.
So it's kind of in the middle of zero and
one for the two documents.
But the ranking can be wrong, so we might
have a larger value for E2 and then E1.
So that won't be good from
retrieval perspective,
even though function, it's not bad.
In contrast, we might have another
case where we predicted the values, or
around the 0.9, it said.
And by the objective function,
the error would be larger.
But if we didn't get the order
of the two documents correct,
that's actually a better result.
So these new, more advanced approaches
will try to correct that problem.
Of course, then the challenge is
that the optimization problem will
be harder to solve.
And then, researchers have posed
many solutions to the problem,
and you can read more of the references at
the end, know more about these approaches.
Now, these learning ranked
approaches after the general.
So there accounts would be be applied
with many other ranking problems,
not just the retrieval problem.
So some people will go
with recommender systems,
computational advertising,
or summarization and
there are many others that you can
probably encounter in your applications..
To summarize this lecture we
have talked about using machine
learning to combine much more
features including ranking results.
Actually the use of machine learning
in information retrieval has
started since many decades ago.
So for example, the Rocchio feedback
approach that we talked about earlier
was a machine learning approach
prior to relevance feedback.
But the most recent use of machine
learning has been driven by some
changes in the environment of
applications of retrieval systems.
First, it's mostly freedom of
availability of a lot of training data
in the form of critical, such as
they are more available than before.
So the data can provide a lot of
useful knowledge about relevance and
machine learning methods can be
applied into a leverage list.
Secondly, it's also freedom by
the need for combining many features,
and this is not only just
because there are more
features available on the web that can
be naturally used for improved scoring.
It's also because by combining them,
we can improve the robustness
of ranking, so this is desired for
combating spams.
Modern search engines all use some
kind of machine learning techniques to
combine many features
to optimize ranking and
this is a major feature of these
commercial engines such a Google or Bing.
The topic of learning to rank is still
active research topic in the community,
and so we can expect to see new results
in development in the next few years,
perhaps.
Here are some additional readings
that can give you more information
about how learning to rank at works and
also some advanced methods.
[MUSIC]