[MUSIC]
This lecture is about
the Recommender Systems.
So far we have talked about a lot
of aspects of search engines.
We have talked about the problem
of search and ranking problem,
different methods for ranking,
implementation of search engine and
how to evaluate a search engine, etc.
This is important because we know
that web search engines are by far
the most important applications
of text retrieval.
And they are the most useful tools
to help people convert big raw text
data into a small set
of relevant documents.
Another reason why we spend so
many lectures on search engines,
is because many techniques used in search
engines are actually also very useful for
Recommender Systems,
which is the topic of this lecture.
And so, overall, the two systems
are actually well connected.
And there are many techniques
that are shared by them.
So this is a slide that
you have seen before,
when we talked about the two
different modes of text access.
Pull and the Push.
And we mentioned that recommender
systems are the main systems to serve
users in the Push Mode, where the systems
will take the initiative to recommend
the information to the user or
pushes information to the user.
And this often works
well when the user has
stable information need
in the system has a good.
So a Recommender System is sometimes
called a filtering system and
it's because recommending useful
items to people is like discarding or
filtering out the the useless articles,
and so
in this sense they are kind of similar.
And in all the cases the system
must make a binary decision and
usually there's a dynamic source
of information items, and
that you have some knowledge
about the users' interest.
And then the system would make a decision
about whether this item is
interesting to the user, and
then if it's interesting then the system
would recommend the article to the user.
So the basic filtering question here is
really will this user like this item?
Will U like item X?
And there are two ways to answer this
question, if you think about it.
And one is look at what items U likes and
then we can see if X is
actually like those items.
The other is to look at who likes X,
and we can see if this
user looks like a one of those users,
or like most of those users.
And these strategies can be combined.
If we follow the first strategy and
look at item similarity in the case
of recommending text objects,
then we're talking about a content-based
filtering or content-based recommendation.
If we look at the second strategy, then,
it's to compare users and in this case
we're user similarity and the technique
is often called collaborative filtering.
So, let's first look at
the content-based filtering system.
This is what the system would look like.
Inside the system, there will be
a Binary Classifier that would have some
knowledge about the user's interests, and
this is called a User Interest Profile.
It maintains this profile to keep
track of all users interests, and
then there is a utility function
to guide the user to make decision
a nice plan utility
function in the moment.
It helps the system decide
where to set the threshold.
And then the accepted documents will
be those that have passed the threshold
according to the classified.
There should be also an initialization
module that would take a user's input,
maybe from a user's specified keywords or
chosen category,
etc., and this would be to feed into
the system with the initiator's profile.
There is also typically a learning
module that would learn from
users' feedback over time.
Now note that in this case typical
users information is stable so
the system would have a lot more
opportunities to observe the users.
If the user has taken a recommended item,
has viewed that, and
this a signal to indicate that
the recommended item may be relevant.
If the user discarded it,
no, it's not relevant.
And so such feedback can be a long term
feedback, and can last for a long time.
And the system can collect a lot of
information about the user's interest and
this then can then be used
to improve the classify.
Now what's the criteria for
evaluating such a system?
How do we know this filtering
system actually performs well?
Now in this case we cannot use the ranking
evaluation measures like a map
because we can't afford waiting for
a lot of documents and
then rank the documents to
make a decision for the users.
And so the system must make
a decision in real time in general
to decide whether the item is
above the threshold or not.
So in other words, we're trying
to decide on absolute relevance.
So in this case,
one common user strategy is to use
a utility function to evaluate the system.
So here, I show linear utility function.
That's defined as for example three
multiplied the number of good items that
you delivered, minus two multiplied by the
number of bad items that you delivered.
So in other words, we could kind of just
treat this as almost in a gambling game.
If you delete one good item,
let's say you win three dollars,
you gain three dollars but if you deliver
a bad one you will lose two dollars.
And this utility function
basically kind of measures
how much money you are get by
doing this kind of game, right?
And so it's clear that if you want
to maximize this utility function,
this strategy should be delivered
as many good articles as possible,
and minimize the delivery of bad articles.
That's obvious, right?
Now one interesting question here is
how should we set these coefficients?
I just showed a three and
negative two as possible coefficients.
But one can ask the question,
are they reasonable?
So what do you think?
Do you think that's a reasonable choice?
What about the other choices?
So for example, we can have 10 and
minus 1, or 1, minus 10.
What's the difference?
What do you think?
How would this utility function affect
the systems' threshold of this issue.
Right, you can think of
these two extreme cases.
(10, -1) + (1, -10), which one do
you think would encourage this
system to over do it and which one would
encourage this system to be conservative?
If you think about it you will see that
when we get a bigger award for delivering
our good document you incur only a small
penalty for delivering a bad one.
Intuitively, you would be
encouraged to deliver more.
And you can try to deliver more in
hope of getting a good one delivered.
And then we'll get a big reward.
So on the other hand,
if you choose (1,-10),
you really don't get such a big prize
if you deliver a good document.
On the other hand, you will have
a big loss if you deliver a bad one.
You can imagine that,
the system would be very reluctant
to deliver a lot of documents.
It has to be absolutely
sure that it's not.
So this utility function has to be
designed based on a specific application.
The three basic problems in content-based
filtering are the following,
first, it has to make
a filtering decision.
So it has to be a binary decision maker,
a binary classifier.
Given a text document and
a profile description of the user,
it has to say yes or no, whether this
document should be deleted or not.
So that's a decision module, and
it should be an initialization
module as you have seen earlier and
this will get the system started.
And we have to initialize the system
based on only very limited
text exclusion or
very few examples from the user.
And the third model is
a learning model which you have,
has to be able to learn from limited
relevance judgements, because we
counted them from the user about their
preferences on the deliver documents.
If we don't deliver document
to the user we'll never
be able to know whether
the user likes it or not.
And we had accumulate a lot of documents
even then from entire history.
All these modules will have to be
optimized to maximize the utility.
So how can we deal with such a system?
And there are many different approaches.
Here we're going to talk about
how to extend a retrieval system,
a search engine for information filtering.
Again, here's why we've spent a lot of
time talking about the search engines.
Because it's actually not very hard
to extend the search engine for
information filtering.
So here's the basic idea for
extending a retrieval system for
information filtering.
First, we can reuse a lot of
retrieval techniques to do scoring.
Right, so we know how to score
documents against queries, etc.
We're going to match the similarity
between profile text description and
a document.
And then we can use a score threshold for
the filtering decision.
We do retrieval and then we kind of find
the scores of documents and then we'll
apply a threshold to see whether the
document is passing the threshold or not.
And if it's passing the threshold,
we're going to say it's relevant and
we're going to deliver it to the user.
Another component that we have to add is,
of course, to learn from the history, and
we had used is the traditional feedback
techniques to learn to improve scoring.
And we know rock hill can be using for
scoring improvement.
And, but we have to develop a new
approaches to learn how to accept this.
And we need to set it initially and
then we have to learn how to
update the threshold over time.
So here's what the system
might look like if we just
generalize the vector-space model for
filtering problems, right?
So you can see the document vector could
be fed into a scoring module which
already exists in a search engine
that implements a vector-space model.
And the profile will be treated
as a query essentially, and then
the profile vector can be matched with
the document vector to generate the score.
And then this score would be fed into a
thresholding module that would say yes or
no, and then the evaluation would be based
on the utility for the filtering results.
If it says yes and then the document
would be sent to the user.
And then user could give some feedback.
The feedback information would be
used to both adjust the threshold and
to adjust the vector representation.
So the vector learning is essentially
the same as query modification or
feedback in the case of search.
The threshold of learning
is a new component and
that we need to talk
a little bit more about.
[MUSIC]