[SOUND]
There are some interesting challenges
in threshold for
the learning the filtering problem.
So here I show the historical data that
you can collect in the filtering system,
so you can see the scores and
the status of relevance.
So the first one has a score of 36.5 and
it's relevant.
The second one is not relevant and
it's separate.
Of course, we have a lot of documents for
which we don't know the status,
because we have never
delivered them to the user.
So as you can see here,
we only see the judgements of
documents delivered to the user.
So this is not a random sample,
so it's a sensitive data.
It's kind of biased, so that creates
some difficultly for learning.
Secondly, there are in general very little
labeled data and very few relevant data,
so it's also challenging for
machine learning approaches,
typically they require more training data.
And in the extreme case at
the beginning we don't even have any
labeled data as well.
The system there has to make a decision,
so that's a very difficult
problem at the beginning.
Finally, there is also this issue of
exploration versus exploitation tradeoff.
Now, this means we also want
to explore the document
space a little bit and
to see if the user might be
interested in documents that
we have in data labeled.
So in other words, we're going to
explore the space of user interests
by testing whether the user might be
interested in some other documents that
currently are not matching
the user's interests so well.
So how do we do that?
Well, we could lower the threshold
a little bit until we just
deliver some near misses to the user
to see what the user would respond,
to see how the user would
respond to this extra document.
And this is a tradeoff, because on
the one hand, you want to explore, but
on the other hand,
you don't want to really explore too much,
because then you will over
deliver non-relevant Information.
So exploitation means you would
exploit what you learn about the user.
Let's say you know the user is
interested in this particular topic, so
you don't want to deviate that much, but
if you don't deviate at all then you don't
exploit so that's also are not good.
You might miss opportunity to learn
another interest of the user.
So this is a dilemma.
And that's also a difficulty
problem to solve.
Now, how do we solve these problems?
In general, I think one can use the
empirical utility optimization strategy.
And this strategy is basically to optimize
the threshold based on historical data,
just as you have seen
on the previous slide.
Right, so you can just compute
the utility on the training data for
each candidate score threshold.
Pretend that, what if I cut at this point.
What if I cut at the different scoring
threshold point, what would happen?
What's utility?
Since these are training data,
we can kind of compute the utility,
and we know that relevant status,
or we assume that we know
relevant status based on
approximation of click-throughs.
So then we can just choose the threshold
that gives the maximum utility
on the training data.
But this of course, doesn't account for
exploration that we just talked about.
And there is also the difficulty of
biased training sample, as we mentioned.
So, in general, we can only get the upper
bound for the true optimal threshold,
because the threshold might
be actually lower than this.
So, it's possible that this could
discarded item might be actually
interesting to the user.
So how do we solve this problem?
Well, we generally, and
as I said we can low with this
threshold to explore a little bit.
So here's on particular approach
called beta-gamma threshold learning.
So the idea is falling.
So here I show a ranked list of all the
training documents that we have seen so
far, and
they are ranked by their positions.
And on the y axis we show the utility,
of course, this function depends on
how you specify the coefficients
in the utility function, but
we can then imagine, that depending on the
cutoff position, we will have a utility.
Suppose I cut at this position and
that would be a utility.
For example,
identify some cutting cutoff point.
The optimal point,
theta optimal, is the point
when it will achieve the maximum utility
if we had chosen this as threshold.
And there is also zero utility threshold.
You can see at this cutoff
the utility is zero.
What does that mean?
That means if I lower the threshold
a little bit, now I reach this threshold.
The utility would be lower but
it's still non-active at least, right?
So it's not as high as
the optimal utility.
But it gives us as a safe point
to explore the threshold,
as I have explained, it's desirable
to explore the interest of space.
So it's desirable to lower the threshold
based on your training there.
So that means, in general, we want to set
the threshold somewhere in this range.
Let's say we can use the alpha to control
the deviation from
the optimal utility point.
So you can see the formula of the
threshold would be just the interpolation
of the zero utility threshold and
the optimal utility threshold.
Now, the question is,
how should we set alpha?
And when should we deviate more
from the optimal utility point?
Well, this can depend on multiple factors,
and the one way to solve the problem is to
encourage this threshold
mechanism to explore
up to the zero point, and
that's a safe point, but
we're not going to necessarily reach
all the way to the zero point.
Rather, we're going to use other
parameters to further define alpha and
this specifically is as follows.
So there will be a beta parameter to
control the deviation from the optimal
threshold and this can be based on can
be accounting for the over-fitting
to the training data let's say, and so
this can be just an adjustment factor.
But what's more interesting
is this gamma parameter.
Here, and you can see in this formula,
gamma is controlling the inference
of the number of examples
in training that are set.
So you can see in this formula as N which
denotes the number of training examples
becomes bigger, then it would
actually encourage less exploration.
In other words, when these very
small it would try to explore more.
And that just means if we have seen few
examples we're not sure whether we
have exhausted the space of interest.
So we need to explore but as we have
seen many examples from the user
many that have we feel that we
probably don't have to explore more.
So this gives us a beta gamma for
exploration, right.
The more examples we have seen
the less exploration we need to do.
So the threshold would be closer
to the optimal threshold so
that's the basic idea of this approach.
This approach actually has been working
well in some evaluation studies,
particularly effective.
And also can work on arbitrary utility
with the appropriate lower bound.
And explicitly addresses
the exploration-exploitation tradeoff and
it kind of uses the zero utility
threshold point as a safeguard for
exploration-exploitation tradeoff.
We're not never going to explore
further than the zero utility point.
So if you take the analogy of gambling,
and
you don't want to risk on losing money.
So it's a safe spend, really
conservative strategy for exploration.
And the problem is of course,
this approach is purely heuristic and
the zero utility lower boundary is also
often too conservative, and there are, of
course, more advance in machine learning
approaches that have been proposed for
solving this problems and
this is their active research area.
So to summarize, there are two
strategies for recommended systems or
filtering systems, one is content based,
which is looking at the item similarity,
and the other is collaborative filtering
that was looking at the user similarity.
We've covered content-based
filtering approach.
In the next lecture, we will talk
about the collaborative filtering.
In content-based filtering system,
we generally have to solve
several problems relative to
filtering decision and learning, etc.
And such a system can actually be
built based on a search engine system
by adding a threshold mechanism and
adding adaptive learning algorithm to
allow the system to learn from
long term feedback from the user.
[MUSIC]