This lecture is about
collaborative filtering.
In this lecture we're going to continue
the discussion of recommended systems.
In particular, we're going to look at
the approach of collaborative filtering.
You have seen this slide before when
we talked about the two strategies to
answer the basic question,
will user U like item X?
In the previous lecture,
we looked at the item similarity,
that's content-based filtering.
In this lecture, we're going to
look at the user similarity.
This is a different strategy,
called a collaborative filtering.
So first, what is collaborative filtering?
It is to make filtering decisions for
individual user based on
the judgements of other uses.
And that is to say we will
infer individual's interest or
preferences from that
of other similar users.
So the general idea is the following.
Given a user u, we're going to first
find the similar users, U1 through.
And then we're going to
predict the use preferences
based on the preferences of
these similar users, U1 through.
Now, the user similarity here can
be judged based their similarity,
the preferences on a common set of items.
Now here you can see the exact
content of item doesn't really matter.
We're going to look at the only the
relation between the users and the items.
So this means this
approach is very general.
It can be applied to any items,
not just the text of objects.
So this approach would work well
under the following assumptions.
First, users with the same interest
will have similar preferences.
Second, the users with similar preferences
probably share the same interest.
So for example, if the interest of
the user is in information retrieval,
then we can infer the user
probably favor SIGIR papers.
So those who are interested in
information retrieval researching,
probably all favor SIGIR papers.
That's an assumption that we make.
And if this assumption is true,
then it would help collaborative
filtering to work well.
We can also assume that if we see
people favor See SIGIR papers,
then we can infer their interest
is probably information retrieval.
So in these simple examples,
it seems to make sense, and
in many cases such assumption
actually does make sense.
So another assumption we have to make
is that there are sufficiently large
number of user preferences
available to us.
So for example, if you see a lot
of ratings of users for movies and
those indicate their
preferences on movies.
And if you have a lot of such data,
then cluttered and
filtering can be very effective.
If not, there will be a problem, and
that's often called a cold start problem.
That means you don't have many
preferences available, so
the system could not fully take advantage
of collaborative filtering yet.
So let's look at the filtering
problem in a more formal way.
So this picture shows that we are,
in general, considering a lot of users and
we're showing m users here, so U1 through.
And we're also considering
a number of objects.
Let's say n objects in
order to O1 through On.
And then we will assume that
the users will be able to judge those
objects and the user could for
example give ratings to those items.
For example, those items could be movies,
could be products and
then the users would give
ratings 1 through 5 and see.
So what you see here is that we have
shown some ratings available for
some combinations.
So some users have watched some movies,
they have rated those movies,
they obviously won't be able
to watch all the movies and
some users may actually
only watch a few movies.
So this is in general a small symmetrics.
So many items and
many entries have unknown values.
And what's interesting here is we
could potentially infer the value
of an element in this matrix
based on other values.
And that's after the essential question
in collaborative filtering, and that is,
we assume there's an unknown
function here, f.
That would map a pair of user and
object to a rating.
And we have observed the sum
values of this function.
And we want to infer the value
of this function for
other pairs that don't have
that as available here.
So this is very similar to other
machinery problems where we'd
know the values of the function
on some training data set.
And we hope to predict the values of
this function on some test data so
this is a function approximation.
And how can we pick out the function
based on the observed ratings.
So this is the setup.
Now there are many approaches
to solving this problem.
In fact,
this is a very active research area or
reason that there are special
conferences dedicated to the problem,
major conference devoted to the problem.
[MUSIC]