[SOUND]
And
here we're going to talk
about basic strategy.
And that would be based on
similarity of users and
then predicting the rating of and
object by an active user using the ratings
of similar users to this active user.
This is called a memory based approach
because it's a little bit similar to
storing all the user information and
when we are considering a particular
user we going to try to
retrieve the rating users or
the similar users to this user case.
And then try to use this
information about those users
to predict the preference of this user.
So here is the general idea and
we use some notations here, so
x sub i j denotes the rating
of object o j by user u i
and n sub i is average rating
of object by this user.
So this n i is needed because
we would like to normalize
the ratings of objects by this user.
So how do you do normalization?
Well, we're going to just subtract
the average rating from all the ratings.
Now, this is to normalize these ratings so
that the ratings from different
users would be comparable.
Because some users might be more generous,
and they generally give more high
ratings but some others might be
more critical so their ratings
cannot be directly compared with each
other or aggregate them together.
So we need to do this normalization.
Another prediction of
the rating on the item
by another user or
active user, u sub a here
can be based on the average
ratings of similar users.
So the user u sub a is the user that we
are interested in recommending items to.
And we now are interested in
recommending this o sub j.
So we're interested in knowing how
likely this user will like this object.
How do we know that?
Where the idea here is to look at
whether similar users to this user
have liked this object.
So mathematically this is to say
well the predicted the rating of
this user on this app object,
user a on object o j is basically
combination of the normalized
ratings of different users,
and in fact here,
we're taking a sum over all the users.
But not all users contribute
equally to the average,
and this is conjured by the weights.
So this weight controls the inference
of the user on the prediction.
And of course,
naturally this weight should be related to
the similarity between ua and
this particular user, ui.
The more similar they are,
then the more contribution
user ui can make in predicting
the preference of ua.
So, the formula is extremely simple.
You can see,
it's a sum of all the possible users.
And inside the sum we have their ratings,
well,
their normalized ratings
as I just explained.
The ratings need to be normalized in
order to be comparable with each other.
And then these ratings
are weighted by their similarity.
So you can imagine w of a and i is just
a similarity of user a and user i.
Now what's k here?
Well k is simply a normalizer.
It's just one over the sum of all
the weights, over all the users.
So this means, basically, if you consider
the weight here together with k, and
we have coefficients of weight that
will sum to one for all the users.
And it's just a normalization strategy so
that you get this predictor rating
in the same range as these ratings
that we used to make the prediction.
Right?
So this is basically the main idea
of memory-based approaches for
collaborative filtering.
Once we make this prediction,
we also would like to map
back through the rating that
the user would actually make,
and this is to further
add the mean rating or
average rating of this user u
sub a to the predicted value.
This would recover a meaningful rating for
this user.
So if this user is generous, then
the average it would be is somewhat high,
and when we add that the rating will be
adjusted to our relatively high rate.
Now when you recommend an item to a user
this actually doesn't really matter,
because you are interested in
basically the normalized reading,
that's more meaningful.
But when they evaluate these
rather than filter approaches,
they typically assume that
actual ratings of the user on
these objects to be unknown and
then you do the prediction and
then you compare the predicted
ratings with their actual ratings.
So, you do have access
to the actual ratings.
But, then you pretend that you don't know,
and
then you compare your systems
predictions with the actual ratings.
In that case, obviously, the systems
prediction would be adjusted to match
the actual ratings of the user and
this is what's happening here basically.
Okay so this is the memory based approach.
Now, of course,
if you look at the formula,
if you want to write
the program to implement it,
you still face the problem of
determining what is this w function?
Once you know the w function, then
the formula is very easy to implement.
So, indeed, there are many different ways
to compute this function or this weight,
w, and specific approaches generally
differ in how this is computed.
So here are some possibilities and
you can imagine there
are many other possibilities.
One popular approach is we use
the Pearson correlation coefficient.
This would be a sum over
commonly rated items.
And the formula is a standard
appears in correlation
coefficient formula as shown here.
So this basically measures
whether the two users tended
to all give higher ratings to similar
items or lower ratings to similar items.
Another measure is the cosine measure,
and this is going to treat the rating
vectors as vectors in the vector space.
And then,
we're going to measure the angle and
compute the cosine of
the angle of the two vectors.
And this measure has been using the vector
space model for retrieval, as well.
So as you can imagine there are just
as many different ways of doing that.
In all these cases, note that the user's
similarity is based on their preferences
on items and we did not actually use
any content information of these items.
It didn't matter these items are,
they can be movies,
they can be books, they can be products,
they can be text documents which
has been cabled the content and
so this allows such approach to be
applied to a wide range of problems.
Now in some newer approaches of course,
we would like to use more
information about the user.
Clearly, we know more about the user,
not just these preferences on these items.
So in the actual filtering system,
is in collaborative filtering,
we could also combine that
with content based filtering.
We could use more context information,
and those are all interesting approaches
that people are just starting, and
there are new approaches proposed.
But, this memory based approach has
been shown to work reasonably well,
and it's easy to implement in
practical applications this could be
a starting point to see if the strategy
works well for your application.
So, there are some obvious ways
to also improve this approach and
mainly we would like to improve
the user similarity measure.
And there are some practical
issues we deal with here as well.
So for example,
there will be a lot of missing values.
What do you do with them?
Well, you can set them to default values
or the average ratings of the user.
And that would be a simple solution.
But there are advanced approaches that
can actually try to predict those
missing values, and then use predictive
values to improve the similarity.
So in fact that the memory based apology
can predict those missing values, right?
So you get you have iterative approach
where you first use some preliminary
prediction and
then you can use the predictive values to
further improve the similarity function.
So this is a heuristic
way to solve the problem.
And the strategy obviously would affect
the performance of claritative filtering
just like any other heuristics would
improve these similarity functions.
Another idea which is actually very
similar to the idea of IDF that we
have seen in text search is called
a Inverse User Frequency or IUF.
Now here the idea is to look at where
the two users share similar ratings.
If the item is a popular item that
has been viewed by many people and
seen [INAUDIBLE] to people interested
in this item may not be so
interesting but if it's a rare item,
it has not been viewed by many users.
But these two users deal with this
item and they give similar ratings.
And, that says more
about their similarity.
It's kind of to emphasize
more on similarity
on items that are not
viewed by many users.
[MUSIC]