[SOUND]
So
to summarize our discussion of
recommender systems, in some sense,
the filtering task for
recommender task is easy, and
in some other sense,
the task is actually difficult.
So it's easy because
the user's expectation is low.
In this case the system takes initiative
to push information to the user.
The user doesn't really make any effort,
so
any recommendation is better than nothing.
All right.
So, unless you recommend the noise
items or useless documents.
If you can recommend
some useful information
users generally will appreciate it,
so that's, in that sense that's easy.
However, filtering is actually much harder
task than retrieval because you have to
make a binary decision and you can't
afford waiting for a lot of items and
then you're going to see whether
one item is better than others.
You have to make a decision
when you see this item.
Think about news filtering.
As soon as you see the news enough
to decide whether the news would be
interesting to the user.
If you wait for a few days, well, even if
you can make accurate recommendation of
the most relevant news, the utility is
going to be significantly decreased.
Another reason why it's hard
is because of data sparseness
if you think of this
as a learning problem.
Collaborative filtering, for
example, is purely based on
learning from the past ratings.
So if you don't have many ratings there's
really not that much you can do, right?
And yeah I just mentioned
this cold start problem.
This is actually a very serious,
serious problem.
But of course there are strategies that
have been proposed for the soft problem,
and there are different strategies that
you can use to alleviate the problem.
You can use, for example, more user
information to asses their similarity,
instead of using the preferences
of these users on these
items give me additional information
available about the user, etc.
And we also talk about two strategies for
filtering task.
One is content-based where
we look at items there
is collaborative filtering where
we look at Use a similarity.
And they obviously can be
combined in a practical system.
You can imagine they generally
would have to be combined.
So that would give us a hybrid
strategy for filtering.
And we also could recall that we talked
about push versus pull as two strategies
for getting access to the text data.
And recommender system easy to
help users in the push mode, and
search engines are serving
users in the pull mode.
Obviously the two should be combined,
and they can be combined.
The two have a system
that can support user
with multiple mode information access.
So in the future we could anticipate such
a system to be more useful the user.
And either,
this is an active research area so
there are a lot of new algorithms
being proposed all the time.
In particular those new algorithms tend
to use a lot of context information.
Now the context here could be
the context of the user and
could also be the context of the user.
Items.
The items are not the isolated.
They're connected in many ways.
The users might form
social network as well,
so there's a rich context there
that we can leverage in order to
really solve the problem well and
then that's active
research area where also machine
learning algorithms have been applied.
Here are some additional readings in
the handbook called
Recommender Systems and
has a collection of a lot
of good articles that
can give you an overview
of a number of specific
approaches through recommender systems.
[MUSIC]