[SOUND]
This
lecture is about the feedback
in text retrieval.
So in this lecture, we will continue with
the discussion of text retrieval methods.
In particular, we're going to talk
about the feedback in text retrieval.
This is a diagram that shows
the retrieval process.
We can see the user would type in a query.
And then, the query would be
sent to a retrieval engine or
search engine, and
the engine would return results.
These results would be issued to the user.
Now, after the user has
seen these results,
the user can actually make judgements.
So for example, the user says,
well, this is good and
this document is not very useful and
this is good again, etc.
Now, this is called a relevance judgment
or relevance feedback because we've
got some feedback information from
the user based on the judgements.
And this can be very useful to the system,
knowing what exactly is
interesting to the user.
So the feedback module would
then take this as input and
also use the document collection
to try to improve ranking.
Typically it would involve
updating the query so
the system can now render the results
more accurately for the user.
So this is called relevance feedback.
The feedback is based on relevance
judgements made by the users.
Now, these judgements are reliable but
the users generally don't want to make
extra effort unless they have to.
So the down side is that it involves
some extra effort by the user.
There's another form of feedback
called pseudo relevance feedback, or
blind feedback,
also called automatic feedback.
In this case, we can see once
the user has gotten [INAUDIBLE] or
in fact we don't have to invoke users.
So you can see there's
no user involved here.
And we simply assume that the top
rank documents to be relevant.
Let's say we have assumed
top 10 as relevant.
And then, we will then use this
assume the documents to learn
and to improve the query.
Now, you might wonder,
how could this help if we simply
assume the top rank of documents?
Well, you can imagine these top
rank of documents are actually
similar to relevant documents
even if they are not relevant.
They look like relevant documents.
So it's possible to learn some related
terms to the query from this set.
In fact, you may recall that we
talked about using language model to
analyze what association, to learn
related words to the word of computer.
And there, what we did is we
first use computer to retrieve
all the documents that contain computer.
So imagine now the query
here is a computer.
And then, the result will be those
documents that contain computer.
And what we can do then is
to take the top n results.
They can match computer very well.
And we're going to count
the terms in this set.
And then, we're going to then use
the background language model to choose
the terms that are frequent in this set
but not frequent in the whole collection.
So if we make a contrast between
these two what we can find
is that related to terms
to the word computer.
As we have seen before.
And these related words can then be added
to the original query to expand the query.
And this would help us bring the documents
that don't necessarily match computer but
match other words like program and
software.
So this is very effective for
improving the search result.
But of course, pseudo-relevancy
values are completely unreliable.
We have to arbitrarily set a cut off.
So there's also something in
between called implicit feedback.
In this case,
what we do is we do involve users, but
we don't have to ask
users to make judgments.
Instead, we're going to observe how the
user interacts with the search results.
So in this case we'll look
at the clickthroughs.
So the user clicked on this one.
And the user viewed this one.
And the user skipped this one.
And the user viewed this one again.
Now, this also is a clue about whether
the document is useful to the user.
And we can even assume that we're
going to use only the snippet
here in this document,
the text that's actually seen by the user
instead of the actual
document of this entry.
The link they are saying web search
may be broken but it doesn't matter.
If the user tries to fetch this
document because of the displayed text
we can assume these displayed
text is probably relevant
is interesting to you so
we can learn from such information.
And this is called interesting feedback.
And we can, again,
use the information to update the query.
This is a very important
technique used in modern.
Now, think about the Google and Bing and
they can collect a lot of user
activities while they are serving us.
So they would observe what documents
we click on, what documents we skip.
And this information is very valuable.
And they can use this to
improve the search engine.
So to summarize, we talked about
the three kinds of feedback here.
Relevant feedback where the user
makes explicit judgements.
It takes some user effort, but
the judgment information is reliable.
We talk about the pseudo feedback where
we seem to assume top brand marking
will be relevant.
We don't have to involve the user
therefore we could do that,
actually before we return
the results to the user.
And the third is implicit feedback
where we use clickthroughs.
Where we involve the users, but
the user doesn't have to make
it explicitly their fault.
Make judgement.
[MUSIC]