[SOUND]
This
lecture is about the feedback
in the vector space model.
In this lecture, we continue talking
about the feedback in text retrieval.
Particularly, we're going to talk about
feedback in the vector space model.
As we have discussed before,
in the case of feedback the task
of text retrieval system is removed from
examples in improved retrieval accuracy.
We will have positive examples.
Those are the documents that
assume would be relevant or
be charged with being relevant.
All the documents that
are viewed by users.
We also have negative examples.
Those are documents known
to be non-relevant.
They can also be the documents
that are skipped by users.
The general method in
the vector space model for
feedback is to modify our query vector.
We want to place the query vector in
a better position to make it accurate.
And what does that mean exactly?
Well, if we think about the query vector
that would mean we would have to do
something to the vector elements.
And in general,
that would mean we might add new terms.
Or we might just weight of old terms or
assign weights to new terms.
As a result, in general,
the query will have more terms.
We often call this query expansion.
The most effective method in
the vector space model for feedback
is called the Rocchio Feedback, which was
actually proposed several decades ago.
So the idea is quite simple.
We illustrate this idea by
using a two dimensional display
of all the documents in the collection and
also the query vector.
So now we can see the query
vector is here in the center,
and these are all the documents.
So when we use the query back there and
use the same narrative function to find
the most similar documents,
we are basically doing a circle here and
that these documents would be
basically the top-ranked documents.
And these process are relevant documents,
and
these are relevant documents,
for example, it's relevant, etc.
And then these minuses are negative
documents, like these.
So our goal here is trying to move
this query back to some position,
to improve the retrieval accuracy.
By looking at this diagram,
what do you think?
Where should we move the query vector so
that we can improve
the retrieval accuracy?
Intuitively, where do you
want to move query vector?
If you want to think more,
you can pause the video.
If you think about this picture, you can
realize that in order to work well in this
case you want the query vector to be as
close to the positive vectors as possible.
That means ideally, you want to place
the query vectors somewhere here.
Or we want to move the query
vector closer to this point.
Now so what exactly is this point?
Well, if you want these relevant
documents to rank on the top,
you want this to be in the center of
all these relevant documents, right?
Because then if you draw
a circle around this one,
you'll get all these relevant documents.
So that means we can move the query
vector towards the centroid of
all the relevant document vectors.
And this is basically the idea of Rocchio.
Of course, you can consider
the centroid of negative documents and
we want to move away from
the negative documents.
Now your match that we're talking about
moving vector closer to some other vec and
away from other vectors.
It just means that we have this formula.
Here you can see this is
original query vector and
this average basically is the centroid
vector of relevant documents.
When we take the average of these vectors,
then were computing
the centroid of these vectors.
Similarly, this is the average of
non-relevant document like this.
So it's essentially of
non-relevant documents.
And we have these three parameters here,
alpha, beta, and gamma.
They are controlling
the amount of movement.
When we add these two vectors together,
we're moving the query vector
closer to the centroid.
This is when we add them together.
When we subtracted this part,
we kind of move the query
vector away from that centroid.
So this is the main idea
of Rocchio feedback.
And after we have done this,
we will get a new query vector which
can be used to score documents.
This new query vector,
will then reflect the move of this
original query vector toward this
relevant centroid vector and
away from the non-relevant value.
Okay, so let's take a look at the example.
This is the example that
we've seen earlier.
Only that I deemed that display
of the actual documents.
I only showed the vector
representation of these documents.
We have five documents here and we have
to read in the documents here, right.
And they're displayed in red.
And these are the term vectors.
Now I have just assumed some of weights.
A lot of terms,
we have zero weights of course.
Now these are negative arguments.
There are two here.
There is another one here.
Now in this Rocchio method, we first
compute the centroid of each category.
And so let's see,
look at the centroid vector of
the positive documents, we simply just,
so it's very easy to see.
We just add this with this one
the corresponding element.
And then that's down here and
take the average.
And then we're going to add
the corresponding elements and
then just take the average.
And so we do this for all this.
In the end, what we have is this one.
This is the average vector of these two,
so it's a centroid of these two.
Let's also look at the centroid
of the negative documents.
This is basically the same.
We're going to take the average
of the three elements.
And these are the corresponding
elements in the three vectors, and so
on and so forth.
So in the end, we have this one.
Now in the Rocchio feedback
method we're going to combine all
these with the original
query vector which is this.
So now let's see how we
combine them together.
Well, that's basically this.
So we have a parameter alpha
controlling the original
query times weight that's one.
And now we have beta to control
the inference of the positive
centroid of the weight, that's 1.5.
That comes from here.
All right, so this goes here.
And we also have this negative
weight here gamma here.
And this way, it has come from,
of course, the negative centroid here.
And we do exactly the same for
other terms, each is for one term.
And this is our new vector.
And we're going to use this new query
vector, this one to rank the documents.
You can imagine what would happen, right?
Because of the movement that this one
would matches these red documents much
better because we moved
this vector closer to them.
And it's going to penalize these black
documents, these non relevent documents.
So this is precisely what
we wanted from feedback.
Now of course if we apply this method in
practice we will see one potential problem
and that is the original query has
only four terms that are now zero.
But after we do query explaining and
merging, we'll have many times
that would have non zero weights.
So the calculation will
have to involve more terms.
In practice,
we often truncate this matter and
only retain the terms
with highest weights.
So let's talk about how we
use this method in practice.
I just mentioned that they're
often truncated vector.
Consider only a small number of
words that have highest weights in
the centroid vector.
This is for efficiency concern.
I also said here that negative examples,
or non-relevant examples
tend not to be very useful, especially
compared with positive examples.
Now you can think about why.
One reason is because negative documents
tend to distract the query in all
directions.
So, when you take the average,
it doesn't really tell you where
exactly it should be moving to.
Whereas positive documents
tend to be clustered together.
And they will point you to
a consistent direction.
So that also means that sometimes we don't
have to use those negative examples.
But note that in some cases, in difficult
queries where most results are negative,
negative feedback after is very useful.
Another thing is to avoid over-fitting.
That means we have to keep relatively
high weight on the original query terms.
Why?
Because the sample that we see in
feedback Is a relatively small sample.
We don't want to overly
trust the small sample.
And the original query terms
are still very important.
Those terms are heightened by the user and
the user has decided that those
terms are most important.
So in order to prevent
the us from over-fitting or
drifting, prevent topic drifting due to
the bias toward the feed backing symbols.
We generally would have to keep a pretty
high weight on the original terms so
it was safe to do that.
And this is especially true for
pseudo relevance feedback.
Now, this method can be used for
both relevance feedback and
pseudo-relevance feedback.
In the case of pseudo-feedback, the prime
and the beta should be set to a smaller
value because the relevant examples
are assumed not to be relevant.
They're not as reliable as
the relevance feedback.
In the case of relevance feedback,
we obviously could use a larger value.
So those parameters,
they have to be set empirically.
And the Rocchio Method is
usually robust and effective.
It's still a very popular method for
feedback.
[MUSIC]