This lecture is about Web Search.
In this lecture,
we're going to talk about one
of the most important applications of
text retrieval, web search engines.
So let's first look at some
general challenges and
opportunities in web search.
Now, many informational
retrieval algorithms
had been developed
before the web was born.
So when the web was born,
it created the best opportunity to apply
those algorithms to major application
problem that everyone would care about.
So naturally, there have to be some
further extensions of the classical
search algorithms to address new
challenges encountered in web search.
So here are some general challenges.
First, this is a scalability challenge.
How to handle the size of the web and
ensure completeness of
coverage of all information.
How to serve many users quickly and
by answering all their queries.
And so that's one major challenge and
before the web was born the scale
search was relatively small.
The second problem is that there's
no quality information and
there are often spams.
The third challenge is
Dynamics of the Web.
The new pages are constantly create and
some pages may be updated very quickly,
so it makes it harder to
keep it indexed fresh.
So these are some of the challenges
that we have to solve in order to
deal with high quality web searching.
On the other hand there are also some
interesting opportunities that we can
leverage to include the search results.
There are many additional heuristics,
for example,
using links that we can
leverage to improve scoring.
Now everything that we talked about
such as the vector space model
are general algorithms.
They can be applied to any search
applications, so that's the advantage.
On the other hand, they also don't take
advantage of special characteristics
of pages or documents in the specific
applications, such as web search.
Web pages are linked with each other,
so obviously,
the linking is something
that we can also leverage.
So, because of these challenges and
opportunities and there are new techniques
that have been developed for
web search or due to need for web search.
One is parallel indexing and searching and
this is to address
the issue of scalability.
In particular, Google's imaging of
map reduce is very influential and
has been very helpful in that aspect.
Second, there are techniques
that are developing for
addressing the problem of spams,
so spam detection.
We'll have to prevent those spam
pages from being ranked high.
And there are also techniques
to achieve robust ranking.
And we're going to use a lot
of signals to rank pages, so
that it's not easy to spam the search
engine with a particular trick.
And the third line of techniques is link
analysis and these are techniques that can
allow us to improve such results
by leveraging extra information.
And in general in web searching,
we're going to use multiple features for
ranking not just for link analysis.
But also exploring all kinds
of crawls like the layout or
anchor text that describes
a link to another page.
So, here's a picture showing
the basic search engine technologies.
Basically, this is the web on the left and
then user on the right side and
we're going to help this user to get
the access for the web information.
And the first component is a Crawler that
would crawl pages and then the second
component is Indexer that would take
these pages create the inverted index.
The third component there is a Retriever
and that would use inverted index to
answer user's query by talking
to the user's browser.
And then the search results will be given
to the user and when the browser would
show those results, it allows
the user to interact with the web.
So, we're going to talk about
each of these components.
First of all, we're going to talk about
the crawler, also called a spider or
software robot that would do something
like crawling pages on the web.
To build a toy crawler is relatively easy,
because you just need to start
with a set of seed pages.
And then fetch pages from the web and
parse these pages and
figure out new links.
And then add them to the priority que and
then just explore those additional links.
But to be able to real crawler
actually is tricky and
there are some complicated issues
that we have to deal with.
For example robustness,
what if the server doesn't respond,
what if there's a trap that generates
dynamically generated webpages
that might attract your crawler to
keep crawling on the same side and
to fetch dynamic generated pages?
The results of this issue
of crawling courtesy and
you don't want to overload one particular
server with many crawling requests and
you have to respect the robot
exclusion protocol.
You also need to handle different
types of files, there are images,
PDF files,
all kinds of formats on the web.
And you have to also
consider URL extension, so
sometimes those are CGI scripts and
there are internal references,
etc, and sometimes you have
JavaScripts on the page and
they also create challenges.
And you ideally should also recognize
redundant pages because you don't have
to duplicate those pages.
And finally, you may be interested
in the discover hidden URLs.
Those are URLs that may not be linked
to any page, but if you truncate
the URL to a shorter path, you might
be able to get some additional pages.
So what are the Major Crawling Strategies?
In general,
Breadth-First is most common because
it naturally balances the sever load.
You would not keep probing a particular
server with many requests.
Also parallel crawling is very
natural because this task is very
easy to parallelize.
And there is some variations
of the crawling task,
and one interesting variation
is called a focused crawling.
In this case, we're going to crawl just
some pages about a particular topic.
For example,
all pages about automobiles, all right.
And this is typically going to
start with a query, and
then you can use the query to get some
results from a major search engine.
And then you can start it with those
results and then gradually crawl more.
The one channel in crawling,
is you will find the new
channels that people created and
people probably are creating
new pages all the time.
And this is very challenging if
the new pages have not been actually
linked to any old pages.
If they are, then you can probably find
them by re-crawling the old pages,
so these are also some interesting
challenges that have to be solved.
And finally, we might face the scenario
of incremental crawling or
repeated crawling, right.
Let's say,
if you want to build a web search engine,
and you first crawl a lot
of data from the web.
But then,
once you have cracked all the data,
in the future you just need
to crawl the updated pages.
In general, you don't have to
re-crawl everything, right?
It's not necessary.
So in this case, your goal is to
minimize the resource overhead
by using minimum resources
to just the update pages.
So, this is actually a very
interesting research question here,
and this is a open research question,
in that there aren't many
standard algorithms established yet
for doing this task.
But in general, you can imagine,
you can learn, from the past experience.
So the two major factors that
you have to consider are,
first will this page
be updated frequently?
And do I have to quote this page again?
If the page is a static page and
that hasn't being changed for months,
you probably don't have to re-crawl it
everyday because it's unlikely that it
will changed frequently.
On the other hand, if it's a sports score
page that gets updated very frequently and
you may need to re-crawl it and
maybe even multiple times on the same day.
The other factor to consider is,
is this page frequently accessed by users?
If it is, then it means that
it is a high utility page and
then thus it's more important to
ensure such a page to refresh.
Compared with another page that has
never been fetched by any users for
a year, then even though that
page has been changed a lot then.
It's probably not that necessary to
crawl that page or at least it's
not as urgent as to maintain the freshness
of frequently accessed page by users.
So to summarize, web search is one of
the most important applications of text
retrieval and there are some new
challenges particularly scalability,
efficiency, quality information.
There are also new opportunities
particularly rich link information and
layout, etc.
A crawler is an essential component
of web search applications and
in general, you can find two scenarios.
One is initial crawling and
here we want to have complete crawling
of the web if you are doing
a general search engine or
focused crawling if you want to just
target as a certain type of pages.
And then, there is another scenario that's
incremental updating of the crawl data or
incremental crawling.
In this case,
you need to optimize the resource,
try to use minimum resource
to get the [INAUDIBLE]
[MUSIC]