[SOUND]
This lecture is about the Web Indexing.
In this lecture, we will continue
talking about the Web Search and
we're going to talk about how
to create a Web Scale Index.
So once we crawl the web,
we've got a lot of web pages.
The next step is to use the indexer
to create the inverted index.
In general, we can use the same
information retrieval techniques for
creating an index and that is what we
talked about in previous lectures,
but there are there are new
challenges that we have to solve.
For web scale indexing, and the two main
challenges are scalability and efficiency.
The index would be so large,
that it cannot actually fit into
any single machine or single disk.
So we have to store the data
on virtual machines.
Also, because the data is so
large, it's beneficial to
process the data in parallel, so
that we can produce index quickly.
Now to address these challenges,
Google has made a number of innovations.
One is the Google File System that's
a general File system, that can help
programmers manage files stored
on a cluster of machines.
The second is MapReduce.
This is a general software framework for
supporting parallel computation.
Hadoop is the most well known open
source implementation of MapReduce.
Now used in many applications.
So, this is the architecture
of the google file system.
It uses a very simple centralized
management mechanism to manage
all the specific locations of.
Files, so
it maintains the file namespace and
look up a table to know where
exactly each file is stored.
The application client will then
talk to this GFS master, and
that obtains specific locations of
the files they want to process.
And once the GFS file kind obtained
the specific location about the files,
then the application client can talk
to the specific servers whether
data actually sits directly, so
you can avoid involving other node.
In the network.
So when this file system stores
the files on machines, the system also
with great fixed sizes of chunks, so
the data files are separated into.
Many chunks.
Each chunk is 64 MB, so it's pretty big.
And that's appropriate for
large data processing.
These chunks are replicated
to ensure reliability.
So this is something that the programmer
doesn't have to worry about,
and it's all taken care
of by this file system.
So from the application perspective,
the programmer would see this
as if it's a normal file.
And the programmer doesn't have to
know where exactly it is stored and
can just invoke high level.
Operators to process the file.
And another feature is that the data
transfer is directly between application
and chunk servers.
So it's efficient in this sense.
On top of the Google file system, Google
also proposed MapReduce as a general
framework for parallel programming.
Now, this is very useful to support
a task like building inverted index.
And so, this framework is,
Hiding a lot of low-level
features from the program.
As a result, the programmer can make
a minimum effort to create an application
that can be run a large
cluster in parallel.
So some of the low level details
are hidden in the framework including
the specific and network communications or
load balancing or
where the task are executed.
All these details are hidden
from the programmer.
There is also a nice feature which
is the built in fault tolerance.
If one server is broken,
the server is down, and
then some tasks may not be finished.
Then the MapReduce mapper will know
that the task has not been done.
So it automatically dispatches a task
on other servers that can do the job.
And therefore, again the program
doesn't have to worry about that So
here's how MapReduce works.
The input data would be separated
into a number of key value pairs.
Now what exactly is in the value
would depend on the data and
it's actually a fairly general framework
to allow you to just partition the data
into different parts and each part
can be then processed in parallel.
Each key value pair would be and
send it to a map function.
The program was right the map function,
of course.
And then the map function will
process this Key Value pair and
then generate a number of
other Key Value pairs.
Of course, the new key is usually
different from the old key
that's given to the map as input.
And these key value pairs
are the output of the map function and
all the outputs of all the map
functions would be then collected,
and then there will be for
the sorting based on the key.
And the result is that,
all the values that are associated
with the same key will be
then grouped together.
So now we've got a pair of of a key and
separate values attached to this key.
So this would then be sent
to a reduce function.
Now, of course, each reduce function
will handle a different key,
so we will send these output values to
multiple reduce functions
each handling a unique key.
A reduce function would then
process the input, which is
a key in a set of values to produce
another set of key values as the output.
So these output values would
be then corrected together
to form the final output.
And so, this is the general
framework of MapReduce.
Now the programmer only needs to write
the Map function and the Reduce function.
Everything else is actually taken
care of by the MapReduce framework.
So you can see the program really
only needs to do minimum work.
And with such a framework, the input data
can be partitioned into multiple parts,
which is processing parallel first by map,
and
then being the process after
we reach the reduced stage.
The much more reduced if I'm
[INAUDIBLE] can also further process
the different keys and
their associated values in parallel.
So it achieves some,
it achieves the purpose of parallel
processing of a large data set.
So let's take a look at a simple example.
And that's Word Counting.
The input is containing words,
and the output that we want to generate is
the number of occurrences of each word.
So it's the Word Count.
We know this kind of counting
would be useful to, for example,
assess the popularity of a word in
a large collection and this is useful for
achieving a factor of IDF wading for
search.
So how can we solve this problem?
Well, one natural thought is that,
well this task can be
done in parallel by simply counting
different parts of the file in parallel,
and then in the end we just
combine all the counts.
And that's precisely the idea of
what we can do with MapReduce.
We can parallelize on
lines in this input file.
So more specifically, we can assume
the input to each map function is
a key value pair that represents the line
number and the string on that line.
So the first line, for
example, has a key of one and
that is another word by word and
just the four words on that line.
So this key value pair would
be sent to a Map Function.
The Map Function then would just
count the words in this line.
And in this case,
of course there are only four words.
Each world gets a count of one and
these are the output that you see here
on this slide from this map function.
So the map function is really
very simple if you look at
what the pseudocode looks
like on the right side,
you see it simply needs to iterate
all the words and this line.
And then just collect the function
which means it would then send the word
and the count to the collector.
The collector would then try to
sort all these key value pairs from
different Map Functions, right?
So the function is very simple and
the programmer specifies
this function as a way to
process each part of the data.
Of course, the second line will be
handled by a different Map Function
which we will produce a single output.
Okay, now the output from the map
functions will be then and
send it to a collector and the collector
would do the internal grouping or sorting.
So at this stage, you can see,
we have collected a match for pairs.
Each pair is a word and
its count in a line.
So, once we see all these pairs.
Then we can sort them based on the key,
which is the word.
So we will collect all the counts
of a word, like bye here, together.
And similarly, we do that for other words.
Like Hadoop, Hello, etc.
So each word now is attached to
a number of values, a number of counts.
And these counts represent the occurrences
to solve this word in different lights.
So now we have got a new pair of a key and
a set of values, and
this pair will then be fed into reduce
function, so the reduce function now
would have to finish the job of counting
the total occurrences of this word.
Now, it has all ready got all
these puzzle accounts, so
all it needs to do is
simply to add them up.
So the reduce function here
is very simple, as well.
You have a counter, and
then iterate all the other words.
That you'll see in this array.
And that,
you just accumulate accounts, right?
And then finally, you output the P and
the proto account.
And that's precisely what we want as
the output of this whole program.
So you can see,
this is all ready very similar to.
To building an Invert index.
And if you think about it,
the output here is index.
And we have already got a dictionary,
basically.
We have got the count.
But what's missing is
the document the specific
frequency counts of words
in those documents.
So we can modify this slightly to
actually be able to index in parallel, so
here's one way to do that.
So in this case, we can assume the input
from Map Function is a pair of a key
which denotes the document ID,
and the value
denoting the screen for that document,
so it's all the words in that document.
And so, the map function would do
something very similar to what we have
seen in the word campaign example.
It simply groups all the counts of
this word in this document together.
And it would then generate
a set of key value pairs.
Each key is a word, and
the value is the count of this word in
this document plus the document ID.
Now, you can easily see why we need to
add document ID here, because later
in inverted index, we would like to
keep this formation, so the Map Function
should keep track of it, and this can then
be sent to the reduce function later.
Now similarly another document D2
can be processed in the same way.
So in the end, again, there is a sorting
mechanism that would group them together.
And then we will have just a key,
like a java,
associated with all the documents
that match this key.
Or all the documents where java occurred.
And the counts, so
the counts of java in those documents.
And this will be collected together.
And this will be, so
fed into the reduce function.
So now you can see the reduce function
has already got input that looks like
an inverted index entry.
So it's just the word and all
the documents that contain the word and
the frequencies of the word
in those documents.
So all you need to do is
simply to concatenate them
into a continuous chunk of data.
And this can be done
written to a file system.
So basically the reduce function
is going to do very minimal.
Work.
And so, this is a pseudo-code for
[INAUDIBLE] that's construction.
Here we see two functions,
procedure Map and procedure Reduce.
And a programmer would specify these two
functions to program on top of map reduce.
And you can see basically they
are doing what I just described.
In the case of map, it's going to count
the occurrences of a word
using the AssociativeArray.
And it would output all the counts
together with the document ID here.
So, this is the reduce function,
on the other hand,
simply concatenates all the input
that it has been given,
and then put them together as
one single entry for this key.
So this is a very simple
MapReduce function, yet
it would allow us to construct an inverted
index at very large scale, and
the data can be processed
by different machines.
And program doesn't have to
take care of the details.
So this is how we can do parallel
index construction for web search.
So to summarize,
web scale indexing requires some
new techniques that go beyond the.
Standard traditional indexing techniques.
Mainly, we have to store
index on multiple machines.
And this is usually done by using a filing
system, like a Google file system.
But this should be through a file system.
And secondly, it requires creating
an index an parallel, because it's so
large and takes long time to create
an index for all the documents.
So if we can do it in parallel,
it will be much faster and
this is done by using
the MapReduce framework.
Note that both the GFS and
MapReduce frameworks are very general, so
they can also support
many other applications.
[MUSIC]