[SOUND] This lecture is about
link analysis for web search.
In this lecture, we're going to talk
about the web search and particularly,
focusing on how to do link analysis and
use the results to improve search.
The main topic of this lecture is to look
at the ranking algorithms for Web Search.
In the previous lecture we talked
about how to create index.
Now that we have index, we want to see
how we can improve ranking of Pages.
The web.
Now standard IR models,
can be also applied here.
In fact,
they are important building blocks, for,
improve, for supporting web search.
But they aren't sufficient.
And mainly for the following reasons.
First, on the web, we tend to have
very different information needs, for
example, people might search for
a webpage, or an entry page.
And this is different from
the traditional library search,
where people are primarily interested
in collecting literature Information.
So this kind of query is often
called a navigational queries.
The purpose is to navigate into
a particular type of the page.
So for such queries we might benefit
from using link information.
Secondly, documents have additional
information and on the web pages,
are web format,
there are a lot of other clues,
such as the layout, the title,
or link information again.
So this has provided opportunity to use
extra context information of
the document to improve the scoring.
And finally,
information quality varies a lot.
That means we have to consider
many factors to improve
the range in the algorithm.
This would give us a more robust way
to rank pages, making it harder for
any spammer to just manipulate the one
signal to improve the ranking of a page.
So as a result,
people have made a number of major
extensions to the ranking algorithms.
One line is to exploit
links to improve scoring.
And that's the main topic of this lecture.
People have also proposed algorithms to
exploit the loudest, they are implicit.
Feedback information the form of
click throughs and that's of course
in the category of feedback techniques and
machine all is often used there.
In general in web search the ranking
algorithms are based on machine learning
algorithms to combine
all kinds of features.
Many of them are based on
the standard of virtual models such
as BM25 that we talked about [INAUDIBLE]
to score different parts of documents or
to provide additional features
based on content matching,
but link information
is also very useful so
they provide additional scoring signals.
So let's look at links in
more detail on the web.
So this is a snapshot of some
part of the web, let's say.
So we can see there are many links that
link the different pages together.
And in this case, you can also
look at the center here, there is
a description of a link that's pointing
to the document on the right side.
Now, this description text
is called anchor text.
Now if you think about this text,
it's actually quite useful
because it provides some extra
description of that page be points with.
So for example, if someone wants
to bookmark Amazon.com front page
the person might say the biggest
online bookstore and
then the link to Amazon, right?
So, the description here after is very
similar to what the user would type in
the query box when they are looking for
or such a page.
And that's why it's very useful for
managing pages.
Suppose someone types in
the query like online bookstore or
biggest online bookstore.
All right the query would match
this anchor text in the page here.
And then this actually
provides evidence for
matching the page that's being
pointed to that is the Amazon.
a entry page.
So if you match anchor text that
describes an anchor to a page,
actually that provides good evidence for
the elements of the page being pointed to.
So anchor text is very useful.
If you look at the bottom part of this
picture you can also see there are some
patterns of some links and these links
might indicate the utility of a document.
So for example,
on the right side you'll see this
page has received the many inlinks.
Now that means many other pages
are pointing to this page.
This shows that this page is quite useful.
On the left side you can see this
is another page that points to
many other pages.
So this is a director page
that would allow you to
actually see a lot of other pages.
So we can call the first
case authority page and
the second case half page, but this means
the link information can help intuit.
One is to provide extra text for matching.
The other is to provide some
additional scores for the webpage
to characterize how likely a page is
a hub, how likely a page is a authority.
So people then of course and proposed
ideas to leverage this link information.
Google's PageRank which was the main
technique that they used in early days
is a good example and
that is an algorithm to capture page and
popularity, basically to score authority.
So the intuitions here are links
are just like citations in literature.
Now think about one page
pointing you to another page,
this is very similar to one
paper citing another paper.
So, of course then,
if a page is cited often,
then we can assume this page
to be more useful in general.
So that's a very good intuition.
Now PageRank is essentially to take
advantage of this Intuition to
implement with the principal approach.
Intuitively, it is essentially doing
citation counting or in link counting.
It just improves the simple
idea in two ways.
One it will consider indirect citations.
So that means you don't just look
at how many in links you have.
You also look at what are those
pages that are pointing to you.
If those pages themselves have a lot
of in-links, that means a lot.
In some sense,
you will get some credit from that.
But if those pages that
are pointing to you are not
being pointed to by other pages they
themselves don't have many in-links,
then well, you don't get that much.
So that's the idea of
getting indirect citation.
All right, so
you can also understand this idea by
looking at again the research papers.
If you're cited by let's say ten papers,
and those ten papers
are just workshop papers or some papers
that are not very influential, right?
So although you've got ten in-links,
and that's not as good as if you
are cited by ten papers that themselves
have attracted a lot of other citations.
And so in this case where we would
like to consider indirect links and
page does that.
The other idea is it's
good to pseudo citations.
Assume that basically every page is having
a number zero pseudo citation count.
Essentially you are trying to
imagine there are many virtual
links that will link all
the pages together so
that you actually get the pseudo
citations from everyone.
The reason why they want to do that.
Is this will allow them
to solve the problem
elegantly with linear algebra technique.
So, I think maybe the best
way to understand
the PageRank is to think
of this as through computer
probability of random surfer
visiting every webpage.
[MUSIC]