[MUSIC]
So let's take a look at this in detail.
So in this random surfing
model at any page would assume
random surfer would choose
the next page to visit.
So this is a small graph here.
That's of course, over simplification
of the complicated web.
But let's say there are four
documents here, d1, d2, d3 and d4.
And let's assume that a random surfer or
random walker can be any of these pages.
And then the random
surfer could decide to,
just randomly jumping to any page or
follow a link and
then visit the next page.
So if the random surfer is at d1,
then there is some probability that
random surfer will follow the links.
Now there are two outlinks here,
one is pointing to d3,
the other is pointing to d4.
So the random surfer could pick any
of these two to reach d3 and d4.
But it also assumes that the random so
far might get bore sometimes.
So the random surfing which decide
to ignore the actual links and
simply randomly jump
into any page in the web.
So if it does that, it would be able
to reach any of the other pages even
though there's no link you actually,
you want from that page.
So this is to assume that
random surfing model.
Imagine a random surfer is
really doing surfing like this,
then we can ask the question how
likely on average the surfer
would actually reach a particular
page like a d1, a d2, or a d3.
That's the average probability of
visiting a particular page and
this probability is precisely
what a page ranker computes.
So the page rank score of
the document is the average
probability that the surfer
visits a particular page.
Now intuitively, this would basically
capture the inlink account, why?
Because if a page has a lot of inlinks,
then it would have a higher
chance of being visited.
Because there will be more
opportunities of having the server to
follow a link to come to this page.
And this is why the random surfing model
actually captures the ID
of counting the inlinks.
Note that it also considers
the interacting links, why?
Because if the page is that point then
you have themselves a lot of inlinks.
That would mean the random surfer would
very likely reach one of them and
therefore, it increase
the chance of visiting you.
So this is just a nice way to capture
both indirect and a direct links.
So mathematically, how can we compute this
problem in a day in order to see that,
we need to take a look at how this
problem there is a computing.
So first of all let's take a look
at the transition metrics here.
And this is just metrics with
values indicating how likely
the random surfer would go
from one page to another.
So each rule stands for a starting page.
For example, rule one would
indicate the probability of going
to any of the other four pages from d1.
And here we see there are only
2 non 0 entries which is 1/2.
So this is because if you look at
the graph d1 is pointing to d3 and d4.
There is no link from d1 or d2.
So we've got 0s for the first 2
columns and 0.5 for d3 and d4.
In general, the M in this matrix,
M sub ij is the probability
of going from di to dj.
And obviously for each rule,
the values should sum to 1,
because the surfer would have to go to
precisely one of these other pages.
So this is a transition metric.
Now how can we compute the probability
of a surfer visiting a page?
Well if you look at the surf
model then basically,
we can compute the probability
of reaching a page as follows.
So here on the left hand side,
you see it's the probability
visiting page dj at time plus 1,
so it's the next time point.
On the right hand side, you can see
the equation involves the probability
of at page di at time t.
So you can see the subscript
in that t here, and
that indicates that's the probability that
the server was at a document at time t.
So the equation basically,
captures the two
possibilities of reaching
at dj at the time t plus 1.
What are these two possibilities?
Well one is through random surfing and
one is through following a link,
as we just explained.
So the first part captures the probability
that the random surfer would reach
this page by following a link.
And you can see the random
surfer chooses this strategy
with probability 1 minus
alpha as we assume.
And so
there is a factor of 1 minus alpha here.
But the main party is realist
sum over all the possible pages
that the surfer could have been at time t.
There are n pages so
it's a sum over all possible n pages.
Inside the sum is a product
of two probabilities.
One is the probability that the surfer
was at di at time t, that's p sub t of di.
The other is the transition
probability from di to dj.
And so in order to reach this dj page,
the surfer must first be at di at time t.
And then also, would also have to
follow the link to go from di to dj.
So the probability is the probability
of being at di at time t multiplied by
the probability of going from that
page to the target page, dj here.
The second part is a similar sum, the only
difference is that now the transition
probability is a uniform
transition probability.
1 over n and
this part of captures is the probability
of reaching this page
through random jumping.
So the form is exactly the same and
this also allows us to
see on why PageRank is essentially assumed
a smoothing of the transition matrix.
If you think about this 1 over n as
coming from another transition matrix
that has all the elements being
1 over n in uniform matrix.
Then you can see very clearly
essentially we can merge the two parts,
because they are of the same form.
We can imagine there's a different
metrics that's combination of this m and
that uniform metrics where
every m is 1 over n.
And in this sense PageRank uses
this idea of smoothing and
ensuring that there's no zero entry
in such as transition matrix.
Now of course this is the time dependent
the calculation of the probabilities.
Now we can imagine, if we'll compute
the average of the probabilities,
the average of probabilities probably
with the sets of file this equation
without considering the time index.
So let's drop the time index and
just assume that they will be equal.
Now this would give us any equations,
because for
each page we have such equation.
And if you look at the what
variables we have in these equations
there are also precisely n variables.
So this basically means,
we now have a system of
n equations with n variables and
these are linear equations.
So basically, now the problem boils
down to solve this system of equations.
And here, I also show
the equations in the metric form.
It's the vector p here equals a matrix or
the transpose of the matrix here and
multiplied by the vector again.
Now, if you still remember some knowledge
that you've learned from linear algebra
and then you will realize, this is
precisely the equation for eigenvector.
When multiply the metrics by this vector,
you get the same value as this matter and
this can be solved by
using iterative algorithm.
So because the equations here
on the back are basically
taken from the previous slide.
So you'll see the relation between the
page that ran sports on different pages.
And this iterative approach or
power approach,
we simply start with s
randomly initialized vector p.
And then we repeatedly
just update this p by
multiplying the metrics
here by this p factor.
I also show a concrete example here.
So you can see this now.
If we assume alpha is 0.2,
then with the example that
we show here on the slide,
we have the original
transition matrix is here.
That includes the graph, the actual links
and we have this smoothing transition
metrics, uniform transition metrics
representing random jumping.
And we can combine them together with
a liner interpolation to form another
metric that would be like this.
So essentially,
we can imagine now the web looks like
this and can be captured like that.
They're all virtual links
between all the pages now.
The page we're on now would just
initialize the p vector first and
then just computed the updating of this
p vector by using this
metrics multiplication.
Now if you rewrite this
metric multiplication in
terms of individual equations,
you'll see this.
And this is basically,
the updating formula for
this particular pages and page score.
So you can also see if you want to compute
the value of this updated score for d1.
You basically multiply
this rule by this column,
and we'll take the third
product of the two.
And that will give us the value for
this value.
So this is how we updated the vector
we started with an initial values for
these guys for this.
And then we just revise
the scores which generate a new
set of scores and
the updating formula is this one.
So we just repeatedly apply this and
here it converges.
And when the matrix is like this,
where there's no 0 values and
it can be guaranteed to converge.
And at that point the we will just have
the PageRank scores for all the pages.
We typically go to sets of
initial values just to 1 over n.
So interestingly,
this updating formula can be
also interpreted as propagating
scores on the graph, can you see why?
Or if you look at this formula and
then compare that with this graph and
can you imagine,
how we might be able to interpret this as
essentially propagating
scores over the graph.
I hope you will see that indeed,
we can imagine we have values
initialized on each of these pages.
So we can have values here and
say, that's a 1 over 4 for each.
And then we're going to use these
metrics to update this the scores.
And if you look at the equation here
this one, basically we're going
to combine the scores of the pages that
possibly would lead to reaching this page.
So we'll look at all the pages
that are pointing to this page and
then combine this score and propagate the
sum of the scores to this document, d1.
To look at the scores that we present
the probability that the random
surfer would be visiting the other
pages before it reached d1.
And then just do
the propagation to simulate
the probability of reaching this page, d1.
So there are two interpretations here.
One is just the matrix multiplication.
We repeat the multiplying
that by these metrics.
The other is to just think
of it as a propagating
these scores repeatedly on the web.
So in practice, the combination of
PageRank score is actually efficient.
Because the matrices is fast and there
are some, ways we transform the equation.
So that you avoid actually
literally computing the values for
all those elements.
Sometimes you may also normalize the
equation and that will give you a somewhat
different form of the equation, but
then the ranking of pages will not change.
The results of this potential
problem of zero-outlink problem.
In that case, if a page does not have
any outlink then the probability of
these pages would not sum to 1.
Basically, the probability of reaching the
next page from this page would not sum to
1, mainly because we have lost
some probability to mass.
One would assume there's some probability
that the surfer would try to follow
the links, but
then there is no link to follow.
And one possible solution is simply to use
a page that is specific damping factor,
and that could easily fix this.
Basically, that's to say alpha would
be 1.0 for a page with no outlink.
In that case,
the surfer would just have to
randomly jump to another page
instead of trying to follow a link.
There are many extensions of PageRank, one
extension is to topic-specific PageRank.
Note that PageRank doesn't merely
use the query information.
So we can make PageRank specific however.
So for example,
at the top of a specific page you rank,
we can simply assume
when the surfer is bored.
The surfer is not randomly
jumping to any page on the web.
Instead, he's going to jump to only those
pages that are relevant to our query.
For example, if the query is not sports
then we can assume that when it's
doing random jumping, it's going
to randomly jump to a sports page.
By doing this, then we can buy
a PageRank through topic and sports.
And then if you know the current
theory is about sports, and
then you can use this specialized
PageRank score to rank documents.
That would be better than if you
use the generic PageRank score.
PageRank is also a channel that can be
used in many other applications for
network analysis particularly for
example, social networks.
You can imagine if you compute
the PageRank scores for
social network, where a link
might indicate a friendship or
a relation, you would get some
meaningful scores for people
[MUSIC]