[SOUND]
So
we talked about PageRank as
a way to capture the assault.
Now, we also looked at some other examples
where a hub might be interesting.
So there is another algorithm called HITS,
and
that going to compute the scores for
authorities and hubs.
The intuitions are pages that are widely
cited are good authorities and
whereas pages that cite many
other pages are good hubs.
I think that the most interesting
idea of this algorithm HITS,
is it's going to use
a reinforcement mechanism
to kind of help improve the scoring for
hubs and the authorities.
And so here's the idea,
it was assumed that good
authorities are cited by good hubs.
That means if you are cited by many
pages with good hub scores then
that inquiry says, you're an authority.
And similarly, good hubs are those
that point at good authorities.
So if you pointed to a lot
of good authority pages,
then your hubs score would be increased.
So then you will have literally reinforced
each other, because you have pointed so
some good hubs.
And so you have pointed to some good
authorities to get a good hubs score,
whereas those authority
scores would be also
improved because they
are pointing to by a good hub.
And this is algorithms is also general it
can have many applications in graph and
network analysis.
So just briefly, here's how it works.
We first also construct a matrix, but this
time we're going to construct an adjacent
matrix and
we're not going to normalize the values.
So if there's a link there's a 1,
if there's no link that's 0.
Again, it's the same graph.
And then we're going to
define the hubs score of page
as the sum of the authority scores of
all the pages that it appoints to.
So whether you are hub,
really depends on whether you are pointing
to a lot of good authority pages.
That's what it says in the first equation.
In the second equation,
we define the authorities of a page
as a sum of the hub scores of all
those pages that appoint to you.
So whether you are good authority
would depend on whether those
pages that are pointing
to you are good hubs.
So you can see this forms
iterative reinforcement mechanism.
Now, these three questions can be
also written in the metrics format.
So what we get here is then the hub
vector is equal to the product
of the adjacency matrix and
the authority vector,
and this is basically the first equation.
And similarly, the second equation
can be returned as the authority
vector is equal to the product of
a transpose multiplied by the hub vector.
Now, these are just different ways
of expressing these equations.
But what's interesting is that
if you look at the matrix form,
you can also plug in the authority
equation into the first one.
So if you do that, you have actually
eliminated the authority vector completely
and you get the equations
of only hubs scores.
The hubs score vector is
equal to a multiplied
by a transpose multiplied
by the hub score again.
Similarly, we can do a transformation
to have equation for
just the authorities also.
So although we frame the problem
as computing hubs and authorities,
we can actually eliminate one of them to
obtain equation just for one of them.
Now, the difference between this and page
random is that now the matrix is actually
a multiplication of the adjacency
matrix and it's transpose.
So this is different from page rank.
But mathematically, then we will
be computing the same problem.
So in HITS,
we typically would initialize the values.
Let's say, 1 for all these values, and
then we would iteratively apply
these equations, essentially.
And this is equivalent to multiply
that by the metrics a and a transpose.
So the arrows of these is exactly
the same in the PageRank.
But here because the adjacency
matrix is not normalized.
So what we have to do is after each
iteration we're going to normalize, and
this would allow us to
control the growth of value.
Otherwise they would grow larger and
larger.
And if we do that, and
that will basically get HITS.
That was the computer, the hubs scores,
and authority scores for all the pages.
And these scores can then be used in
branching just like the PageRank scores.
So to summarize in this lecture, we have
seen that link information's very useful.
In particular,
the anchor text is very useful to
increase the text
representation of a page.
And we also talk about the PageRank and
page anchor as two major
link analysis algorithms.
Both can generate scores for web pages
that can be used in the ranking function.
Note that PageRank and
the HITS are also very general algorithms.
So they have many applications in
analyzing other graphs or networks.
[MUSIC]