[SOUND]
>> This lecture is about Natural Language
of Content Analysis.
As you see from this picture,
this is really the first step
to process any text data.
Text data are in natural languages.
So computers have to understand
natural languages to some extent,
in order to make use of the data.
So that's the topic of this lecture.
We're going to cover three things.
First, what is natural
language processing,
which is the main technique for processing
natural language to obtain understanding.
The second is the state of
the art of NLP which stands for
natural language processing.
Finally we're going to cover the relation
between natural language processing and
text retrieval.
First, what is NLP?
Well the best way to explain it
is to think about if you see
a text in a foreign language
that you can understand.
Now what do you have to do in
order to understand that text?
This is basically what
computers are facing.
So looking at the simple sentence like
a dog is chasing a boy on the playground.
We don't have any problems
understanding this sentence.
But imagine what the computer would
have to do in order to understand it.
Well in general,
it would have to do the following.
First, it would have to know dog
is a noun, chasing's a verb, etc.
So this is called lexical analysis,
or part-of-speech tagging, and
we need to figure out the syntactic
categories of those words.
So that's the first step.
After that, we're going to figure
out the structure of the sentence.
So for example, here it shows that A and
the dog would go together
to form a noun phrase.
And we won't have dog and is to go first.
And there are some structures
that are not just right.
But this structure shows what we might
get if we look at the sentence and
try to interpret the sentence.
Some words would go together first, and
then they will go together
with other words.
So here we show we have noun phrases
as intermediate components, and
then verbal phrases.
Finally we have a sentence.
And you get this structure.
We need to do something called
a semantic analysis, or parsing.
And we may have a parser
accompanying the program, and
that would automatically
created this structure.
At this point you would know
the structure of this sentence, but
still you don't know
the meaning of the sentence.
So we have to go further
to semantic analysis.
In our mind we usually can map
such a sentence to what we already
know in our knowledge base.
For example, you might imagine
a dog that looks like that.
There's a boy and
there's some activity here.
But for a computer would have
to use symbols to denote that.
We'd use a symbol (d1) to denote a dog.
And (b)1 can denote a boy and
then (p)1 can denote a playground.
Now there is also a chasing
activity that's happening here so
we have a relationship chasing
that connects all these symbols.
So this is how a computer would obtain
some understanding of this sentence.
Now from this representation we could
also further infer some other things,
and we might indeed naturally think of
something else when we read a text and
this is called inference.
So for example, if you believe
that if someone's being chased and
this person might be scared,
but with this rule,
you can see computers could also
infer that this boy maybe scared.
So this is some extra knowledge
that you'd infer based on
some understanding of the text.
You can even go further to understand
why the person say at this sentence.
So this has to do as a use of language.
This is called pragmatic analysis.
In order to understand the speak
actor of a sentence, right?
We say something to
basically achieve some goal.
There's some purpose there.
And this has to do with
the use of language.
In this case the person who said
this sentence might be reminding
another person to bring back the dog.
That could be one possible intent.
To reach this level of
understanding would require
all of these steps and
a computer would have to go through all
these steps in order to completely
understand this sentence.
Yet we humans have no trouble
with understanding that,
we instantly would get everything.
There is a reason for that.
That's because we have a large
knowledge base in our brain and
we can use common sense knowledge
to help interpret the sentence.
Computers unfortunately are hard
to obtain such understanding.
They don't have such a knowledge base.
They are still incapable of doing
reasoning and uncertainties,
so that makes natural language
processing difficult for computers.
But the fundamental reason why natural
language processing is difficult for
computers is simply because natural
language has not been designed for
computers.
Natural languages are designed for
us to communicate.
There are other languages designed for
computers.
For example, programming languages.
Those are harder for us, right?
So natural languages is designed to
make our communication efficient.
As a result,
we omit a lot of common sense knowledge
because we assume everyone
knows about that.
We also keep a lot of ambiguities because
we assume the receiver or the hearer could
know how to decipher an ambiguous word
based on the knowledge or the context.
There's no need to demand different
words for different meanings.
We could overload the same word with
different meanings without the problem.
Because of these reasons this makes every
step in natural language of processing
difficult for computers,
ambiguity is the main difficulty.
And common sense and reasoning is
often required, that's also hard.
So let me give you some
examples of challenges here.
Consider the word level ambiguity.
The same word can have
different syntactic categories.
For example design can be a noun or
a verb.
The word of root may
have multiple meanings.
So square root in math sense or
the root of a plant.
You might be able to think
about it's meanings.
There are also syntactical ambiguities.
For example, the main topic of this
lecture, natural language processing,
can actually be interpreted in two
ways in terms of the structure.
Think for a moment and
see if you can figure that out.
We usually think of this as
processing of natural language,
but you could also think of this as do
say, language processing is natural.
So this is an example
of synaptic ambiguity.
What we have different is
structures that can be
applied to the same sequence of words.
Another common example of an ambiguous
sentence is the following.
A man saw a boy with a telescope.
Now in this case the question is,
who had a telescope.
This is called a prepositional
phrase attachment ambiguity or
PP attachment ambiguity.
Now we generally don't have a problem with
these ambiguities because we have a lot of
background knowledge to help
us disambiguate the ambiguity.
Another example of difficulty
is anaphora resolution.
So think about the sentence John
persuaded Bill to buy a TV for himself.
The question here is does
himself refer to John or Bill?
So again this is something that
you have to use some background or
the context to figure out.
Finally, presupposition
is another problem.
Consider the sentence,
he has quit smoking.
Now this obviously implies
that he smoked before.
So imagine a computer wants to understand
all these subtle differences and meanings.
It would have to use a lot of
knowledge to figure that out.
It also would have to maintain a large
knowledge base of all the meanings of
words and how they are connected to our
common sense knowledge of the world.
So this is why it's very difficult.
So as a result, we are steep not perfect,
in fact far from perfect in understanding
natural language using computers.
So this slide sort of gains a simplified
view of state of the art technologies.
We can do part of speech
tagging pretty well, so
I showed 97% accuracy here.
Now this number is obviously
based on a certain dataset, so
don't take this literally.
This just shows that we
can do it pretty well.
But it's still not perfect.
In terms of parsing,
we can do partial parsing pretty well.
That means we can get noun phrase
structures, or verb phrase structure,
or some segment of the sentence, and
this dude correct them in
terms of the structure.
And in some evaluation results,
we have seen above 90%
accuracy in terms of partial
parsing of sentences.
Again, I have to say these numbers
are relative to the dataset.
In some other datasets,
the numbers might be lower.
Most of the existing work has been
evaluated using news dataset.
And so a lot of these numbers are more or
less biased toward news data.
Think about social media data,
the accuracy likely is lower.
In terms of a semantical analysis,
we are far from being able to do
a complete understanding of a sentence.
But we have some techniques
that would allow us to
do partial understanding of the sentence.
So I could mention some of them.
For example, we have techniques that can
allow us to extract the entities and
relations mentioned in text articles.
For example,
recognizing dimensions of people,
locations, organizations, etc in text.
So this is called entity extraction.
We may be able to recognize the relations.
For example,
this person visited that place or
this person met that person or
this company acquired another company.
Such relations can be extracted by using
the computer current
Natural Language Processing techniques.
They're not perfect but
they can do well for some entities.
Some entities are harder than others.
We can also do word sense
disintegration to some extend.
We have to figure out whether this word in
this sentence would have certain meaning
in another context the computer could
figure out, it has a different meaning.
Again, it's not perfect, but
you can do something in that direction.
We can also do sentiment analysis,
meaning, to figure out whether
a sentence is positive or negative.
This is especially useful for
review analysis, for example.
So these are examples
of semantic analysis.
And they help us to obtain partial
understanding of the sentences.
It's not giving us a complete
understanding, as I showed it before, for
this sentence.
But it would still help us gain
understanding of the content.
And these can be useful.
In terms of inference,
we are not there yet,
probably because of the general difficulty
of inference and uncertainties.
This is a general challenge
in artificial intelligence.
Now that's probably also because
we don't have complete semantical
representation for
natural [INAUDIBLE] text.
So this is hard.
Yet in some domains perhaps,
in limited domains when you have a lot of
restrictions on the word uses, you may be
able to perform inference to some extent.
But in general we can not
really do that reliably.
Speech act analysis is also
far from being done and
we can only do that analysis for
very special cases.
So this roughly gives you some
idea about the state of the art.
And then we also talk a little
bit about what we can't do,
and so we can't even do 100%
part of speech tagging.
Now this looks like a simple task, but
think about the example here,
the two uses of off may
have different syntactic categories if you
try to make a fine grained distinctions.
It's not that easy to figure
out such differences.
It's also hard to do
general complete parsing.
And again, the same sentence
that you saw before is example.
This ambiguity can be very hard to
disambiguate and you can imagine example
where you have to use a lot of knowledge
in the context of the sentence or
from the background, in order to figure
out who actually had the telescope.
So although the sentence looks very
simple, it actually is pretty hard.
And in cases when the sentence is
very long, imagine it has four or
five prepositional phrases, and there
are even more possibilities to figure out.
It's also harder to do precise
deep semantic analysis.
So here's an example.
In the sentence "John owns a restaurant."
How do we define owns exactly?
The word own,
it is something that we can understand but
it's very hard to precisely describe
the meaning of own for computers.
So as a result we have a robust and
a general
Natural Language Processing techniques
that can process a lot of text data.
In a shallow way,
meaning we only do superficial analysis.
For example, parts of speech tagging or a
partial parsing or recognizing sentiment.
And those are not deep understanding,
because we're not really understanding
the exact meaning of the sentence.
On the other hand of the deep
understanding techniques tend not to scale
up well, meaning that they would
fill only some restricted text.
And if you don't restrict
the text domain or
the use of words, then these
techniques tend not to work well.
They may work well based on machine
learning techniques on the data
that are similar to the training data
that the program has been trained on.
But they generally wouldn't work well on
the data that are very different from
the training data.
So this pretty much summarizes the state
of the art of Natural Language Processing.
Of course, within such a short amount
of time we can't really give you
a complete view of NLP,
which is a big field.
And I'd expect to see multiple courses on
Natural Language Processing topic itself.
But because of its relevance to the topic
that we talk about, it's useful for
you to know the background in case
you happen to be exposed to that.
So what does that mean for Text Retrieval?
Well, in Text Retrieval we
are dealing with all kinds of text.
It's very hard to restrict
text to a certain domain.
And we also are often dealing
with a lot of text data.
So that means The NLP techniques must
be general, robust, and efficient.
And that just implies today we can only
use fairly shallow NLP techniques for
text retrieval.
In fact,
most search engines today use something
called a bag of words representation.
Now, this is probably the simplest
representation you can possibly think of.
That is to turn text data
into simply a bag of words.
Meaning we'll keep individual words, but
we'll ignore all the orders of words.
And we'll keep duplicated
occurrences of words.
So this is called a bag
of words representation.
When you represent text in this way,
you ignore a lot of valid information.
That just makes it harder to understand
the exact meaning of a sentence
because we've lost the order.
But yet this representation tends
to actually work pretty well for
most search tasks.
And this was partly because the search
task is not all that difficult.
If you see matching of some of
the query words in a text document,
chances are that that document is about
the topic, although there are exceptions.
So in comparison of some other tasks, for
example, machine translation would require
you to understand the language accurately.
Otherwise the translation would be wrong.
So in comparison such tasks
are all relatively easy.
Such a representation is often sufficient
and that's also the representation that
the major search engines today,
like a Google or Bing are using.
Of course, I put in parentheses but
not all, of course there are many queries
that are not answered well by
the current search engines, and
they do require the replantation that
would go beyond bag of words replantation.
That would require more natural
language processing to be done.
There was another reason why we
have not used the sophisticated
NLP techniques in modern search engines.
And that's because some
retrieval techniques actually,
naturally solved the problem of NLP.
So one example is word
sense disintegration.
Think about a word like Java.
It could mean coffee or
it could mean program language.
If you look at the word anome,
it would be ambiguous, but
when the user uses the word in the query,
usually there are other words.
For example, I'm looking for
usage of Java applet.
When I have applet there,
that implies Java means program language.
And that contest can help us
naturally prefer documents
which Java is referring
to program languages.
Because those documents would
probably match applet as well.
If Java occurs in that
documents where it means coffee
then you would never match applet or
with very small probability.
So this is the case when
some retrieval techniques
naturally achieve the goal of word.
Another example is some technique called
feedback which we will talk about
later in some of the lectures.
This technique would allow us to add
additional words to the query and
those additional words could
be related to the query words.
And these words can help matching
documents where the original query words
have not occurred.
So this achieves, to some extent,
semantic matching of terms.
So those techniques also helped us
bypass some of the difficulties
in natural language processing.
However, in the long run we still need
a deeper natural language processing
techniques in order to improve the
accuracy of the current search engines.
And it's particularly needed for
complex search tasks.
Or for question and answering.
Google has recently launched a knowledge
graph, and this is one step toward
that goal, because knowledge graph would
contain entities and their relations.
And this goes beyond the simple
bag of words replantation.
And such technique should help us
improve the search engine utility
significantly, although this is the open
topic for research and exploration.
In sum, in this lecture we
talked about what is NLP and
we've talked about the state
of that techniques.
What we can do, what we cannot do.
And finally, we also explain why
the bag of words replantation
remains the dominant replantation
used in modern search engines,
even though deeper NLP would be needed for
future search engines.
If you want to know more, you can take
a look at some additional readings.
I only cited one here and
that's a good starting point.
Thanks.
[MUSIC]