[SOUND]
In this lecture,
we're going to talk about the text access.
In the previous lecture, we talked about
the natural language content, analysis.
We explained that the state of the are
natural language processing techniques
are still not good enough to process
a lot of unrestricted text data
in a robust manner.
As a result,
bag of words remains very popular in
applications like a search engine.
In this lecture, we're going to talk
about some high-level strategies to
help users get access to the text data.
This is also important step to convert
raw big text data into small random data.
That are actually needed
in a specific application.
So the main question we'll address here,
is how
can a text information system, help users
get access to the relevant text data?
We're going to cover two complimentary
strategies, push versus pull.
And then we're going to talk about
two ways to implement the pull mode,
querying versus browsing.
So first push versus pull.
These are two different ways connect
the users with the right information
at the right time.
The difference is which
takes the initiative,
which party takes the initiative.
In the pull mode,
the users take the initiative to
start the information access process.
And in this case, a user typically would
use a search engine to fulfill the goal.
For example,
the user may type in the query and
then browse the results to
find the relevant information.
So this is usually appropriate for
satisfying a user's ad
hoc information need.
An ad hoc information need is
a temporary information need.
For example, you want to buy a product so
you suddenly have a need to read
reviews about related product.
But after you have cracked information,
you have purchased in your product.
You generally no longer
need such information, so
it's a temporary information need.
In such a case, it's very hard for
a system to predict your need, and
it's more proper for
the users to take the initiative, and
that's why search engines are very useful.
Today because many people have many
information needs all the time.
So as we're speaking Google is probably
processing many queries from this.
And those are all, or mostly adequate.
Information needs.
So this is a pull mode.
In contrast in the push mode in
the system would take the initiative
to push the information to the user or
to recommend information to the user.
So in this case this is usually
supported by a recommender system.
Now this would be appropriate if.
The user has a stable information.
For example you may have a research
interest in some topic and
that interest tends to stay for a while.
So, it's rather stable.
Your hobby is another example of.
A stable information need is such a case
the system can interact with you and
can learn your interest, and
then to monitor the information stream.
If the system hasn't seen any
relevant items to your interest,
the system could then take the initiative
to recommend the information to you.
So, for example, a news filter or
news recommended system could
monitor the news stream and
identify interesting news to you and
simply push the news articles to you.
This mode of information access may be
also a property that when this system
has good knowledge about the users need
and this happens in the search context.
So for example, when you search for
information on the web
a search engine might infer you might be
also interested in something related.
Formation.
And they would recommend the information
to you, so that just reminds you, for
example, of an advertisement
placed on the search page.
So this is about the two high level
strategies or two modes of text access.
Now let's look at the pull
mode in more detail.
In the pull mode, we can further
distinguish it two ways to help users.
Querying versus browsing.
In querying,
a user would just enter a query.
Typical the keyword query, and
the search engine system would
return relevant documents to use.
And this works well when the user knows
what exactly are the keywords to be used.
So if you know exactly
what you are looking for,
you tend to know the right keywords.
And then query works very well,
and we do that all of the time.
But we also know that sometimes
it doesn't work so well.
When you don't know the right
keywords to use in the query, or
you want to browse information
in some topic area.
You use because browsing
would be more useful.
So in this case, in the case of browsing,
the users would simply navigate it,
into the relevant information
by following the paths
supported by the structures of documents.
So the system would maintain
some kind of structures and
then the user could follow
these structures to navigate.
So this really works well when the user
wants to explore the information space
or the user doesn't know what
are the keywords to using the query.
Or simply because the user finds it
inconvenient to type in a query.
So even if a user knows what query to
type in if the user is using a cellphone
to search for information.
It's still harder to enter the query.
In such a case, again,
browsing tends to be more convenient.
The relationship between browsing and
querying is best understood by making and
imagine you're site seeing.
Imagine if you're touring a city.
Now if you know the exact
address of attraction.
Taking a taxi there is
perhaps the fastest way.
You can go directly to the site.
But if you don't know the exact address,
you may need to walk around.
Or you can take a taxi to a nearby
place and then walk around.
It turns out that we do exactly
the same in the information studies.
If you know exactly what you
are looking for, then you can
use the right keywords in your query
to find the information you're after.
That's usually the fastest way to do,
find information.
But what if you don't know
the exact keywords to use?
Well, you clearly probably won't so well.
You will not related pages.
And then, you need to also walk
around in the information space,
meaning by following the links or
by browsing.
You can then finally get
into the relevant page.
If you want to learn about again.
You will likely do a lot of browsing so
just like you are looking around in
some area and you want to see some
interesting attractions
related in the same.
[INAUDIBLE].
So this analogy also tells us that
today we have very good support for
query, but we don't really have
good support for browsing.
And this is because in order
to browse effectively,
we need a map to guide us,
just like you need a map to.
Of Chicago,
through the city of Chicago, you need a
topical map to tour the information space.
So how to construct such a topical
map is in fact a very interesting
research question that might bring us
more interesting browsing experience
on the web or in applications.
So, to summarize this lecture,
we've talked about the two high level
strategies for text access; push and pull.
Push tends to be supported by
the Recommender System, and
Pull tends to be supported
by the Search Engine.
Of course, in the sophisticated
[INAUDIBLE] information system,
we should combine the two.
In the pull mode, we can further this
[INAUDIBLE] Querying and Browsing.
Again we generally want to combine
the two ways to help you assist,
so that you can support
the both querying nad browsing.
If you want to know more about
the relationship between pull and
push, you can read this article.
This give excellent discussion of the
relationship between machine filtering and
information retrieval.
Here informational filtering is similar
to information recommendation or
the push mode of information access.
[MUSIC]