[MUSIC]
This lecture is about
the text retrieval problem.
This picture shows our overall plan for
lectures.
In the last lecture, we talked about
the high level strategies for text access.
We talked about push versus pull.
Such engines are the main tools for
supporting the pull mode.
Starting from this lecture,
we're going to talk about the how
search engines work in detail.
So first it's about
the text retrieval problem.
We're going to talk about
the three things in this lecture.
First, we define Text Retrieval.
Second we're going to make a comparison
between Text Retrieval and
the related task Database Retrieval.
Finally, we're going to talk about
the Document Selection versus
Document Ranking as two strategies for
responding to a user's query.
So what is Text Retrieval?
It should be a task that's familiar for
the most of us because we're using
web search engines all the time.
So text retrieval is basically a task
where the system would respond to
a user's query With relevant documents.
Basically, it's for supporting a query
as one way to implement the poll
mode of information access.
So the situation is the following.
You have a collection of
text retrieval documents.
These documents could be all
the webpages on the web, or
all the literature articles
in the digital library.
Or maybe all the text
files in your computer.
A user will typically give a query to
the system to express information need.
And then, the system would return
relevant documents to users.
Relevant documents refer to those
documents that are useful to
the user who typed in the query.
All this task is a phone call
that information retrieval.
But literally information retrieval would
broadly include the retrieval of other
non-textual information as well,
for example audio, video, etc.
It's worth noting that
Text Retrieval is at the core
of information retrieval in
the sense that other medias such as
video can be retrieved by
exploiting the companion text data.
So for example,
current the image search engines actually
match a user's query was
the companion text data of the image.
This problem is also
called search problem.
And the technology is often called
the search technology industry.
If you ever take a course in databases it
will be useful to pause
the lecture at this point and
think about the differences between
text retrieval and database retrieval.
Now these two tasks
are similar in many ways.
But, there are some important differences.
So, spend a moment to think about
the differences between the two.
Think about the data, and the information
managed by a search engine versus
those that are managed
by a database system.
Think about the different between
the queries that you typically specify for
database system versus queries that
are typed in by users in a search engine.
And then finally think about the answers.
What's the difference between the two?
Okay, so if we think about the information
or data managed by the two systems,
we will see that in text retrieval.
The data is unstructured, it's free text.
But in databases, they are structured data
where there is a clear defined schema
to tell you this column is the names
of people and that column is ages, etc.
The unstructured text is not obvious
what are the names of people
mentioned in the text.
Because of this difference, we also see
that text information tends to be more
ambiguous and we talk about that in the
processing chapter, whereas in databases.
But they don't tend to have
where to find the semantics.
The results important
difference in the queries, and
this is partly due to the difference
in the information or data.
So test queries tend to be ambiguous.
Whereas in their research,
the queries are typically well-defined.
Think about a SQL query that would clearly
specify what records to be returned.
So it has very well-defined semantics.
Keyword queries or electronic queries tend
to be incomplete,
also in that it doesn't really
specify what documents
should be retrieved.
Whereas complete specification for
what should be returned.
And because of these differences,
the answers would be also different.
Being the case of text retrieval, we're
looking for it rather than the documents.
In the database search,
we are retrieving records or
match records with the sequel
query more precisely.
Now in the case of text retrieval,
what should be the right answers
to the query is not very well specified,
as we just discussed.
So it's unclear what should be
the right answers to a query.
And this has very important consequences,
and that is,
textual retrieval is
an empirically defined problem.
So this is a problem because
if it's empirically defined,
then we can not mathematically prove one
method is better than another method.
That also means we must rely
on empirical evaluation
involving users to know
which method works better.
And that's why we have.
You need more than one lectures
to cover the issue of evaluation.
Because this is very important topic for
Sir Jennings.
Without knowing how to evaluate heroism
properly, there's no way to tell
whether we have got the better or
whether one system is better than another.
So now let's look at
the problem in a formal way.
So, this slide shows a formal formulation
of the text retrieval problem.
First, we have our vocabulary set, which
is just a set of words in a language.
Now here,
we are considering only one language, but
in reality, on the web,
there might be multiple natural languages.
We have texts that are in
all kinds of languages.
But here for simplicity, we just
assume that is one kind of language.
As the techniques used for retrieving
data from multiple languages Are more or
less similar to the techniques used for
retrieving documents in one end, which
although there is important difference,
the principle methods are very similar.
Next, we have the query,
which is a sequence of words.
And so here, you can see
the query is defined as
a sequence of words.
Each q sub i is a word in the vocabulary.
A document is defined in the same way,
so it's also a sequence of words.
And here,
d sub ij is also a word in the vocabulary.
Now typically, the documents
are much longer than queries.
But there are also cases where
the documents may be very short.
So you can think about what
might be a example of that case.
I hope you can think of Twitter search.
Tweets are very short.
But in general,
documents are longer than the queries.
Now, then we have
a collection of documents,
and this collection can be very large.
So think about the web.
It could be very large.
And then the goal of text retrieval
is you'll find the set of relevant in
the documents, which we denote by R'(q),
because it depends on the query.
And this in general, a subset of all
the documents in the collection.
Unfortunately, this set of relevant
documents is generally unknown,
and user-dependent in the sense that,
for the same query typed
in by different users, they expect
the relevant documents may be different.
The query given to us by
the user is only a hint
on which document should be in this set.
And indeed, the user is generally
unable to specify what exactly should
be in this set, especially in the case
of web search, where the connection's so
large, the user doesn't have complete
knowledge about the whole production.
So the best search system
can do is to compute
an approximation of this
relevant document set.
So we denote it by R'(q).
So formerly,
we can see the task is to compute this
R'(q) approximation of
the relevant documents.
So how can we do that?
Now imagine if you are now asked
to write a program to do this.
What would you do?
Now think for a moment.
Right, so these are your input.
The query, the documents.
And then you are to compute
the answers to this query,
which is a set of documents that
would be useful to the user.
So, how would you solve the problem?
Now in general,
there are two strategies that we can use.
The first strategy is we do a document
selection, and that is, we're
going to have a binary classification
function, or binary classifier.
That's a function that
would take a document and
query as input, and then give a zero or
one as output to indicate whether this
document is relevant to the query or not.
So in this case, you can see the document.
The relevant document is set,
is defined as follows.
It basically, all the documents that
have a value of 1 by this function.
So in this case,
you can see the system must have decide
if the document is relevant or not.
Basically, it has to say
whether it's one or zero.
And this is called absolute relevance.
Basically, it needs to know
exactly whether it's going to be
useful to the user.
Alternatively, there's another
strategy called document ranking.
Now in this case,
the system is not going to make a call
whether a document is random or not.
But rather the system is going to
use a real value function, f here.
That would simply give us a value
that would indicate which
document is more likely relevant.
So it's not going to make a call whether
this document is relevant or not.
But rather it would say which
document is more likely relevant.
So this function then can be
used to random documents, and
then we're going to let
the user decide where to stop,
when the user looks at the document.
So we have a threshold theta
here to determine what
documents should be in
this approximation set.
And we're going to assume
that all the documents that
are ranked above the threshold
are in this set, because in effect,
these are the documents that
we deliver to the user.
And theta is a cutoff
determined by the user.
So here we've got some collaboration
from the user in some sense,
because we don't really make a cutoff.
And the user kind of helped
the system make a cutoff.
So in this case,
the system only needs to decide
if one document is more
likely relevant than another.
And that is, it only needs to
determine relative relevance,
as opposed to absolute relevance.
Now you can probably already sense that
relative relevance would be easier to
determine than absolute relevance.
Because in the first case,
we have to say exactly whether
a document is relevant or not.
And it turns out that ranking is indeed
generally preferred to document selection.
So let's look at these two
strategies in more detail.
So this picture shows how it works.
So on the left side,
we see these documents, and
we use the pluses to indicate
the relevant documents.
So we can see the true relevant
documents here consists this set
of true relevant documents, consists
of these process, these documents.
And with the document selection function,
we're going to basically
classify them into two groups,
relevant documents, and non-relevant ones.
Of course, the classified will not
be perfect so it will make mistakes.
So here we can see, in the approximation
of the relevant documents,
we have got some number in the documents.
And similarly,
there is a relevant document that's
misclassified as non-relevant.
In the case of document ranking,
we can see the system seems like,
simply ranks all the documents in
the descending order of the scores.
And then, we're going to let the user
stop wherever the user wants to stop.
If the user wants to
examine more documents,
then the user will scroll down some
more and then stop [INAUDIBLE].
But if the user only wants to
read a few random documents,
the user might stop at the top position.
So in this case, the user stops at d4.
So in fact, we have delivered
these four documents to our user.
So as I said ranking is generally
preferred, and one of the reasons is
because the classifier in the case of
document selection is unlikely accurate.
Why?
Because the only clue
is usually the query.
But the query may not be accurate in the
sense that it could be overly constrained.
For example, you might expect relevant
documents to talk about all these
topics by using specific vocabulary.
And as a result,
you might match no relevant documents.
Because in the collection,
no others have discussed the topic
using these vocabularies, right?
So in this case,
we'll see there is this problem of
no relevant documents to return in
the case of over-constrained query.
On the other hand,
if the query is under-constrained,
for example, if the query
does not have sufficient descriptive
words to find the random documents.
You may actually end up having of
over delivery, and this when you
thought these words my be sufficient
to help you find the right documents.
But, it turns out they
are not sufficient and
there are many distractions,
documents using similar words.
And so, this is a case of over delivery.
Unfortunately, it's very hard to find the
right position between these two extremes.
Why?
Because whether users looking for
the information in general the user does
not have a good knowledge about
the information to be found.
And in that case, the user does not
have a good knowledge about what
vocabularies will be used in
those relevent documents.
So it's very hard for
a user to pre-specify the right
level of constraints.
Even if the classifier is accurate,
we also still want to rend these
relevant documents, because they
are generally not equally relevant.
Relevance is often a matter of degree.
So we must prioritize these documents for
a user to examine.
And note that this
prioritization is very important
because a user cannot
digest all the content
the user generally would have to
look at each document sequentially.
And therefore, it would make sense to
users with the most relevant documents.
And that's what ranking is doing.
So for these reasons,
ranking is generally preferred.
Now this preference also has
a theoretical justification and
this is given by the probability
ranking principle.
In the end of this lecture,
there is reference for this.
This principle says, returning a ranked
list of documents in descending order
of probability that a document
is relevant to the query
is the optimal strategy under
the following two assumptions.
First, the utility of
a document (to a user)
Is independent of the utility
of any other document.
Second, a user would be assumed to
browse the results sequentially.
Now it's easy to understand why these
assumptions are needed in order to justify
Site for the ranking strategy.
Because if the documents are independent,
then we can evaluate the utility
of each document that's separate.
And this would allow the computer
score for each document independently.
And then, we are going to rank these
documents based on the scrolls.
The second assumption is to say that the
user would indeed follow the rank list.
If the user is not going to follow
the ranked list, is not going to examine
the documents sequentially, then obviously
the ordering would not be optimal.
So under these two assumptions, we can
theoretically justify the ranking strategy
is, in fact, the best that you could do.
Now, I've put one question here.
Do these two assumptions hold?
I suggest you to pause the lecture,
for a moment, to think about this.
Now, can you think of
some examples that would
suggest these assumptions
aren't necessarily true.
Now, if you think for a moment,
you may realize none of
the assumptions Is actually true.
For example, in the case of
independence assumption we might
have documents that have similar or
exactly the same content.
If we look at each of them alone,
each is relevant.
But if the user has already seen
one of them, we can assume it's
generally not very useful for the user to
see another similar or duplicated one.
So clearly the utility
on the document that
is dependent on other documents
that the user has seen.
In some other cases you might see
a scenario where one document that may not
be useful to the user, but when three
particular documents are put together.
They provide answers to
the user's question.
So this is a collective relevance and
that also suggests that
the value of the document might
depend on other documents.
Sequential browsing generally would make
sense if you have a ranked list there.
But even if you have a rank list,
there is evidence showing that
users don't always just go strictly
sequentially through the entire list.
They sometimes will look at the bottom for
example, or skip some.
And if you think about the more
complicated interfaces that
we could possibly use like
two dimensional in the phase.
Where you can put that additional
information on the screen then
sequential browsing is a very
restricted assumption.
So the point here is that
none of these assumptions is
really true but less than that.
But probability ranking principle
establishes some solid foundation for
ranking as a primary pattern for
search engines.
And this has actually been the basis for
a lot of research work in
information retrieval.
And many hours have been designed
based on this assumption,
despite that the assumptions
aren't necessarily true.
And we can address this problem
by doing post processing
Of a ranked list, for example,
to remove redundancy.
So to summarize this lecture,
the main points that you can
take away are the following.
First, text retrieval is
an empirically defined Problem.
And that means which algorithm is
better must be judged by the users.
Second, document ranking
is generally preferred.
And this will help users prioritize
examination of search results.
And this is also to bypass the difficulty
in determining absolute relevance
Because we can get some help from users
in determining where to make the cut off,
it's more flexible.
So, this further suggests that the main
technical challenge in designing a search
engine is the design
effective ranking function.
In other words, we need to define
what is the value of this function F
on the query and document pair.
How we design such a function is the main
topic in the following lectures.
There are two suggested
additional readings.
The first is the classical paper on
the probability ranking principle.
The second one is a must-read for anyone
doing research on information retrieval.
It's a classic IR book, which has
excellent coverage of the main research
and results in early days up to
the time when the book was written.
Chapter six of this book has
an in-depth discussion of
the Probability Ranking Principle and
Probably for retrieval models in general.
[MUSIC]