[SOUND]
This lecture is a overview of
text retrieval methods.
In the previous lecture, we introduced
the problem of text retrieval.
We explained that the main problem
is the design of ranking function
to rank documents for a query.
In this lecture,
we will give an overview of different
ways of designing this ranking function.
So the problem is the following.
We have a query that has
a sequence of words and
the document that's also
a sequence of words.
And we hope to define a function f
that can compute a score based
on the query and document.
So the main challenge you hear is with
design a good ranking function that
can rank all the relevant documents
on top of all the non-relevant ones.
Clearly, this means our function
must be able to measure
the likelihood that a document
d is relevant to a query q.
That also means we have to have
some way to define relevance.
In particular, in order to
implement the program to do that,
we have to have a computational
definition of relevance.
And we achieve this goal by
designing a retrieval model,
which gives us
a formalization of relevance.
Now, over many decades,
researchers have designed many
different kinds of retrieval models.
And they fall into different categories.
First, one family of the models
are based on the similarity idea.
Basically, we assume that if
a document is more similar to
the query than another document is,
then we will say the first document
is more relevant than the second one.
So in this case,
the ranking function is defined as
the similarity between the query and
the document.
One well known example in this
case is vector space model,
which we will cover more in
detail later in the lecture.
A second kind of models
are called probabilistic models.
In this family of models, we follow a very
different strategy, where we assume that
queries and documents are all
observations from random variables.
And we assume there is a binary
random variable called R here
to indicate whether a document
is relevant to a query.
We then define the score of document with
respect to a query as a probability that
this random variable R is equal to 1,
given a particular document query.
There are different cases
of such a general idea.
One is classic probabilistic model,
another is language model,
yet another is divergence
from randomness model.
In a later lecture, we will talk more
about one case, which is language model.
A third kind of model are based
on probabilistic inference.
So here the idea is to associate
uncertainty to inference rules,
and we can then quantify
the probability that we can
show that the query
follows from the document.
Finally, there is also a family of models
that are using axiomatic thinking.
Here, an idea is to define
a set of constraints that we
hope a good retrieval function to satisfy.
So in this case, the problem is
to seek a good ranking function
that can satisfy all
the desired constraints.
Interestingly, although these different
models are based on different thinking,
in the end, the retrieval function
tends to be very similar.
And these functions tend to
also involve similar variables.
So now let's take a look at the common
form of a state of the art retrieval model
and to examine some of the common
ideas used in all these models.
First, these models are all
based on the assumption
of using bag of words to represent text,
and
we explained this in the natural
language processing lecture.
Bag of words representation remains
the main representation used in all
the search engines.
So with this assumption,
the score of a query,
like a presidential campaign news
with respect to a document of d here,
would be based on scores computed
based on each individual word.
And that means the score would
depend on the score of each word,
such as presidential, campaign, and news.
Here, we can see there
are three different components,
each corresponding to how well the
document matches each of the query words.
Inside of these functions,
we see a number of heuristics used.
So for example, one factor that
affects the function d here
is how many times does the word
presidential occur in the document?
This is called a term frequency, or TF.
We might also denote as
c of presidential and d.
In general, if the word occurs
more frequently in the document,
then the value of this
function would be larger.
Another factor is,
how long is the document?
And this is to use the document length for
scoring.
In general, if a term occurs in a long
document many times,
it's not as significant as
if it occurred the same number
of times in a short document.
Because in a long document, any term
is expected to occur more frequently.
Finally, there is this factor
called document frequency.
That is, we also want to look at how
often presidential occurs in the entire
collection, and we call this document
frequency, or df of presidential.
And in some other models,
we might also use a probability
to characterize this information.
So here, I show the probability of
presidential in the collection.
So all these are trying to characterize
the popularity of the term in
the collection.
In general, matching a rare term in
the collection is contributing more
to the overall score than
matching up common term.
So this captures some of the main ideas
used in pretty much older state of
the art original models.
So now, a natural question is,
which model works the best?
Now it turns out that many
models work equally well.
So here are a list of
the four major models
that are generally regarded as
a state of the art original models,
pivoted length normalization,
BM25, query likelihood, PL2.
When optimized,
these models tend to perform similarly.
And this was discussed in detail in this
reference at the end of this lecture.
Among all these,
BM25 is probably the most popular.
It's most likely that this has been used
in virtually all the search engines,
and you will also often see this
method discussed in research papers.
And we'll talk more about this
method later in some other lectures.
So, to summarize, the main points made
in this lecture are first the design
of a good ranking function pre-requires a
computational definition of relevance, and
we achieve this goal by designing
appropriate retrieval model.
Second, many models are equally effective,
but we don't have a single winner yet.
Researchers are still active and
working on this problem,
trying to find a truly
optimal retrieval model.
Finally, the state of the art
ranking functions tend
to rely on the following ideas.
First, bag of words representation.
Second, TF and
document frequency of words.
Such information is used in
the weighting function to determine
the overall contribution of matching
a word and document length.
These are often combined in interesting
ways, and we'll discuss how
exactly they are combined to rank
documents in the lectures later.
There are two suggested additional
readings if you have time.
The first is a paper where you can
find the detailed discussion and
comparison of multiple
state of the art models.
The second is a book with
a chapter that gives a broad
review of different retrieval models.
[MUSIC]