[SOUND]
This lecture is about the
vector space retrieval model.
We're going to give
an introduction to its basic idea.
In the last lecture, we talked about
the different ways of designing
a retrieval model, which would give
us a different arranging function.
In this lecture, we're going to
talk about a specific way of
designing a ramping function called
a vector space retrieval model.
And we're going to give a brief
introduction to the basic idea.
Vector space model is a special case of
similarity based models
as we discussed before.
Which means we assume relevance
is roughly similarity,
between the document and the query.
Now whether is this assumption
is true is actually a question.
But in order to solve the search problem,
we have to convert the vague notion
of relevance into a more precise
definition that can be implemented
with the program analogy.
So in this process,
we have to make a number of assumptions.
This is the first assumption
that we make here.
Basically, we assume that if a document
is more similar to a query than
another document.
Then the first document will be assumed it
will be more relevant than the second one.
And this is the basis for
ranking documents in this approach.
Again, it's questionable whether this is
really the best definition for randoms.
As we will see later there
are other ways to model randoms.
The basic idea of vectors for
base retrieval model is actually
very easy to understand.
Imagine a high dimensional space where
each dimension corresponds to a term.
So here I issue a three dimensional
space with three words,
programming, library and presidential.
So each term here defines one dimension.
Now we can consider vectors in this,
three dimensional space.
And we're going to assume
that all our documents and
the query will be placed
in this vector space.
So for example, on document might
be represented by this vector, d1.
Now this means this document
probably covers library and
presidential, but
it doesn't really talk about programming.
What does this mean in terms
of representation of document?
That just means we're going to look at
our document from the perspective of
this vector.
We're going to ignore everything else.
Basically, what we see here is only
the vector root condition of the document.
Of course,
the document has all information.
For example, the orders of
words are [INAUDIBLE] model and
that's because we assume that
the [INAUDIBLE] of words will [INAUDIBLE].
So with this presentation
you can really see
d1 simply suggests a [INAUDIBLE] library.
Now this is different from another
document which might be recommended as
a different vector, d2 here.
Now in this case, the document that
covers programming and library, but
it doesn't talk about presidential.
So what does this remind you?
Well you can probably guess the topic
is likely about program language and
the library is software lab library.
So this shows that by using
this vector space reproduction,
we can actually capture the differences
between topics of documents.
Now you can also imagine
there are other vectors.
For example,
d3 is pointing into that direction,
that might be a presidential program.
And in fact we can place all
the documents in this vector space.
And they will be pointing
to all kinds of directions.
And similarly,
we're going to place our query also
in this space, as another vector.
And then we're going to measure the
similarity between the query vector and
every document vector.
So in this case for example,
we can easily see d2 seems to be
the closest to this query vector.
And therefore,
d2 will be rendered above others.
So this is basically the main
idea of the vector space model.
So to be more precise,
vector space model is a framework.
In this framework,
we make the following assumptions.
First, we represent a document and
query by a term vector.
So here a term can be any basic concept.
For example, a word or a phrase or
even n gram of characters.
Those are just sequence of
characters inside a word.
Each term is assumed that will
be defined by one dimension.
Therefore n terms in our vocabulary,
we define N-dimensional space.
A query vector would consist
of a number of elements
corresponding to the weights
on different terms.
Each document vector is also similar.
It has a number of elements and
each value of each element is
indicating the weight of
the corresponding term.
Here, you can see,
we assume there are N dimensions.
Therefore, they are N elements
each corresponding to the weight
on the particular term.
So the relevance in this case
will be assumed to be the similarity
between the two vectors.
Therefore, our ranking function
is also defined as the similarity
between the query vector and
document vector.
Now if I ask you to write a program
to implement this approach
in a search engine.
You would realize that
this was far from clear.
We haven't said a lot of things in detail,
therefore it's impossible to actually
write the program to implement this.
That's why I said, this is a framework.
And this has to be refined
in order to actually
suggest a particular ranking function
that you can implement on a computer.
So what does this framework not say?
Well, it actually hasn't said many things
that would be required in order
to implement this function.
First, it did not say how we should define
or select the basic concepts exactly.
We clearly assume
the concepts are orthogonal.
Otherwise, there will be redundancy.
For example, if two synonyms or somehow
distinguish it as two different concepts.
Then they would be defining
two different dimensions and
that would clearly cause redundancy here.
Or all the emphasizing of
matching this concept,
because it would be as if
you match the two dimensions
when you actually matched
one semantic concept.
Secondly, it did not say how we
exactly should place documents and
the query in this space.
Basically that show you some examples
of query and document vectors.
But where exactly should the vector for
a particular document point to?
So this is equivalent to how
to define the term weights?
How do you compute the lose
element values in those vectors?
This is a very important question,
because term weight in the query vector
indicates the importance of term.
So depending on how you assign the weight,
you might prefer some terms
to be matched over others.
Similarly, the total word in
the document is also very meaningful.
It indicates how well the term
characterizes the document.
If you got it wrong then you clearly
don't represent this document accurately.
Finally, how to define the similarity
measure is also not given.
So these questions must be addressed
before we can have a operational
function that we can actually
implement using a program language.
So how do we solve these problems
is the main topic of the next lecture.
[MUSIC]