In this lecture we're going to talk
about how to instantiate
vector space model so
that we can get very
specific ranking function.
So this is to continue the discussion
of the vector space model,
which is one particular approach
to design a ranking function.
And we're going to talk about how
we use the general framework of
the the vector space
model as a guidance to
instantiate the framework to derive
a specific ranking function.
And we're going to cover the symbolist
instantiation of the framework.
So as we discussed in
the previous lecture,
the vector space model
is really a framework.
And this didn't say.
As we discussed in the previous lecture,
vector space model is really a framework.
It does not say many things.
So, for example,
here it shows that it did not say
how we should define the dimension.
It also did not say how we place
a document vector in this space.
It did not say how we place a query
vector in this vector space.
And, finally, it did not say how we
should measure the similarity between
the query vector and the document vector.
So you can imagine,
in order to implement this model,
we have to say specifically
how we compute these vectors.
What is exactly xi?
And what is exactly yi?
This will determine where
we place a document vector,
where we place a query vector.
And, of course,
we also need to say exactly what
should be the similarity function.
So if we can provide a definition
of the concepts that would define
the dimensions and these xi's or
yi's and namely weights of terms for
queries and document, then we will be
able to place document vectors and
query vectors in this well defined space.
And then,
if we also specify similarity function,
then we'll have a well
defined ranking function.
So let's see how we can do that and
think about the instantiation.
Actually, I would suggest you to
pause the lecture at this point,
spend a couple minutes to think about.
Suppose you are asked
to implement this idea.
You have come up with the idea of vector
space model, but you still haven't figured
out how to compute these vectors exactly,
how to define the similarity function.
What would you do?
So, think for a couple of minutes,
and then proceed.
So, let's think about some simplest ways
of instantiating this vector space model.
First, how do we define the dimension?
Well, the obvious choice is to use
each word in our vocabulary
to define the dimension.
And show that there are N
words in our vocabulary.
Therefore, there are N dimensions.
Each word defines one dimension.
And this is basically
the bag of words with
Now let's look at how we
place vectors in this space.
Again here, the simplest strategy is to
use a Bit Vector to represent
both the query and a document.
And that means each element, xi and
yi will be taking a value
of either zero or 1.
When it's 1,
it means the corresponding word is
present in the document or in the query.
When it's 0,
it's going to mean that it's absent.
So you can imagine if the user
types in a few words in the query,
then the query vector will only
have a few 1's, many, many zeros.
The document vector,
generally we have more 1's, of course.
But it will also have many zeros since
the vocabulary is generally very large.
Many words don't really
occur in any document.
Many words will only occasionally
occur in a document.
A lot of words will be absent
in a particular document.
So now we have placed the documents and
the query in the vector space.
Let's look at how we
measure the similarity.
So, a commonly used similarity
measure here is Dot Product.
The Dot Product of two
vectors is simply defined as
the sum of the products of the
corresponding elements of the two vectors.
So, here we see that it's
the product of x1 and y1.
So, here.
And then, x2 multiplied by y2.
And then, finally, xn multiplied by yn.
And then, we take a sum here.
So that's a Dot Product.
Now, we can represent this in a more
general way using a sum here.
So this is only one of the many different
ways of measuring the similarity.
So, now we see that we have
defined the dimensions,
we have defined the vectors, and we have
also defined the similarity function.
So now we finally have the simplest
vector space model, which is based
on the bit vector [INAUDIBLE] dot product
similarity and bag of words [INAUDIBLE].
And the formula looks like this.
So this is our formula.
And that's actually a particular retrieval
function, a ranking function right?
Now we can finally implement this
function using a program language,
and then rank the documents for query.
Now, at this point you should
again pause the lecture
to think about how we can
interpreted this score.
So, we have gone through the process
of modeling the retrieval problem
using a vector space model.
And then,
we make assumptions about how we place
vectors in the vector space, and
how do we define the similarity.
So in the end, we've got a specific
retrieval function shown here.
Now, the next step is to think about
whether this retrieval function
actually makes sense, right?
Can we expect this function
to actually perform well
when we used it to rank documents for
user's queries?
So it's worth thinking about what is
this value that we are calculating.
So, in the end, we'll get a number.
But what does this number mean?
Is it meaningful?
So, spend a couple minutes
to sort of think about that.
And, of course,
the general question here is do you
believe this is a good ranking function?
Would it actually work well?
So, again,
think about how to interpret this value.
Is it actually meaningful?
Does it mean something?
This is related to how well
the document matched the query.
So, in order to assess
whether this simplest
vector space model actually works well,
let's look at the example.
So, here I show some sample documents and
a sample query.
The query is news about
the presidential campaign.
And we have five documents here.
They cover different terms in the query.
And if you look at these documents for
a moment, you may realize that
some documents are probably relevant, and
some others are probably not relevant.
Now, if I asked you to rank these
documents, how would you rank them?
This is basically our ideal ranking.
When humans can examine the documents,
and then try to rank them.
Now, so think for a moment,
and take a look at this slide.
And perhaps by pausing the lecture.
So I think most of you would
agree that d4 and d3 are probably
better than others because they
really cover the query well.
They match news,
presidential and campaign.
So, it looks like these documents
are probably better than the others.
They should be ranked on top.
And the other three d2, d1, and
d5 are really not relevant.
So we can also say d4 and
d3 are relevant documents, and
d1, d2 and d5 are non-relevant.
So now let's see if our simplest
vector space model could do the same,
or could do something closer.
So, let's first think about
how we actually use this model
to score documents.
All right.
Here I show two documents, d1 and d3.
And we have the query also here.
In the vector space model, of course we
want to first compute the vectors for
these documents and the query.
Now, I showed the vocabulary here as well.
So these are the end dimensions
that we'll be thinking about.
So what do you think is the vector for
the query?
Note that we're assuming
that we only use zero and 1
to indicate whether a term is absent or
present in the query or in the document.
So these are zero,1 bit vectors.
So what do you think is the query vector?
Well, the query has four words here.
So for these four words,
there will be a 1.
And for the rest, there will be zeros.
Now, what about the documents?
It's the same.
So d1 has two rows, news and about.
So, there are two 1's here,
and the rest are zeroes.
Similarly, so now that we
have the two vectors,
let's compute the similarity.
And we're going to use Do Product.
So you can see when we use Dot Product,
we just multiply the corresponding
elements, right?
So these two will be formal product,
and these two will
generate another product,
and these two will generate yet
another product and so on, so forth.
Now you can easily see if we do that,
we actually don't have to care about
these zeroes because whenever we have
a zero the product will be zero.
So when we take a sum
over all these pairs,
then the zero entries will be gone.
As long as you have one zero,
then the product would be zero.
So, in the fact, we're just
counting how many pairs of 1 and 1.
In this case, we have seen two,
so the result will be 2.
So what does that mean?
Well, that means this number, or
the value of this scoring function,
is simply the count of how many unique
query terms are matched in the document.
Because if a term is matched in the
document, then there will be two one's.
If it's not, then there will
be zero on the document side.
Similarly, if the document has a term but
the term is not in the query,
there will be a zero in the query vector.
So those don't count.
So, as a result,
this scoring function basically
measures how many unique query
terms are matched in a document.
This is how we interpret this score.
Now, we can also take a look at d3.
In this case, you can see the result
is 3 because d3 matched to the three
distinctive query words news, presidential
campaign, whereas d1 only matched the two.
Now in this case, this seems
reasonable to rank d3 on top of d1.
And this simplest vector
space model indeed does that.
So that looks pretty good.
However, if we examine this model in
detail, we likely will find some problems.
So, here I'm going to show all
the scores for these five documents.
And you can easily verify they're
correct because we're basically
counting the number of unique query
terms matched in each document.
Now note that this measure
actually makes sense, right?
It basically means if a document
matches more unique query terms,
then the document will be
assumed to be more relevant.
And that seems to make sense.
The only problem is here we can note that
there are three documents, d2, d3 and d4.
And they tied with a 3 as a score.
So, that's a problem because if you look
at them carefully, it seems that the d4
should be ranked above d3 because
d3 only mentions the presidential once,
but d4 mentioned it multiple times.
In the case of d3,
presidential could be an dimension.
But d4 is clearly above
the presidential campaign.
Another problem is that d2 and
d3 also have the same score.
But if you look at the three words
that are matched, in the case of d2,
it matched the news, about and campaign.
But in the case of d3, it matched news,
presidential and campaign.
So intuitively this reads better
because matching presidential
is more important than matching about,
even though about and
the presidential are both in the query.
So intuitively,
we would like d3 to be ranked above d2.
But this model doesn't do that.
So that means this model
is still not good enough.
We have to solve these problems.
To summarize,
in this lecture we talked about how
to instantiate a vector space model.
We mainly need to do three things.
One is to define the dimension.
The second is to decide how to place
documents as vectors in the vector space,
and to also place a query in
the vector space as a vector.
And third is to define
the similarity between two vectors,
particularly the query vector and
the document vector.
We also talked about various simple way
to instantiate the vector space model.
Indeed, that's probably the simplest
vector space model that we can derive.
In this case,
we use each word to define the dimension.
We use a zero, 1 bit vector to
represent a document or a query.
In this case, we basically only care
about word presence or absence.
We ignore the frequency.
And we use the Dot Product
as the similarity function.
And with such a instantiation,
we showed that the scoring
function is basically to score
a document based on the number of distinct
query words matched in the document.
We also showed that such a simple vector
space model still doesn't work well, and
we need to improve it.
And this is a topic that we're
going to cover in the next lecture.
[MUSIC]